<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | Journal of Information Technology</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/journal/journal-of-information-technology</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers for Journal of Information Technology.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 03:18:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | Journal of Information Technology</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/journal/journal-of-information-technology</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Futuring: ‘Digital’ Futures as a Novel Site of Inquiry and Imagination]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-futuring-digital-futures-as-a-novel-site-of-inquiry-and-imagination</link>
            <guid>jit-futuring-digital-futures-as-a-novel-site-of-inquiry-and-imagination</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 03:16:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Dirk S. Hovorka</strong>, The University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Benjamin Mueller</strong>, University of Bremen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Elizabeth Davidson</strong>, University of Hawaii - Manoa</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mike Chiasson</strong>, University of British Columbia</p>
        
    
    
    <p>What attention do we owe the future(s)? The Information Systems (IS) and adjacent research fields engage with the design, implementation, and evaluation of increasingly powerful digital technologies and with studies of their impact on work, knowledge, sustainability, and organizing. Given the rich and growing body of theories and findings from research on these wide and long-term impacts, the potential for researchers to help envision, inform, critique, and shape how these technologically-infused futures – &#39;digital futures&#39; – develop are immense.</p>
    
    <p>Despite this rich potential, most discussions of the future implications of digitalization in IS research are abstract and nominal, typically assuming a singular &#39;future&#39; will arise from the technological advances studied. Discourses on the future with digital technologies rarely bring the worlds and practices that emerge from, shape, and transform futures to the foreground for a close and critical examination. Similarly, whether or to what extent such worlds and practices will discernibly be digital to any meaningful degree is often just assumed, which focuses our attention on specific aspects that may no longer be salient in futures. As a result, researchers tend to cede these important discussions and considerations to visionaries, technology firms, and &#39;evangelists&#39; in business and consultancy.</p>
    
    <p>To the degree that IS research does consider the future, the implications of digital technologies in the discourse are often contradictory. On the one hand, an optimistic, instrumental view depicts the broad range of technologies as &#39;tools&#39; under social control, which can (and will) produce an economically, socially, and environmentally sustainable future. On the other hand, a substantive view of technology casts technology as dark, uncontrollable forces that (inevitably) result in personal, societal, and environmental distress. For instance, the dominating discussions of AI in research illustrate these contradictory &#39;hopes and fears&#39;. Neither view of technology sufficiently challenges researchers to engage actively with futuring – that is, the envisioning, informing, critiquing, and helping to shape possible futures systematically through research practices. Hence, the purpose and focus of this special issue is on futuring work – active, imaginary, forward-looking research work in IS or related fields that is informing or shaping our &#39;digital&#39; futures.</p>
    
    <p>Research approaches that address the worlds and practices that shape digital possibilities and the multiplicity of futures that could result are possible. These strategies can overcome nominal approaches to considering the future and build on the rich socio-technical positions already present in IS research. To do so, researchers need to consider new ways of futuring that go beyond simple extrapolations of current trends into the future or tacit acceptance of technology’s inevitable path. One way to do so is to loosen the grip of empiricism in IS research and broaden our relationship to futures, for instance, by engaging with speculation and imagination in research, creating speculative engagements with future possibilities, and deconstructing the narratives and expectations of the present. These and other approaches to futuring can be highly significant to what emerging phenomena can be observed, where present-day research interests and practices are directed, and ultimately, what future worlds are realized through the technologies we study.</p>
    
    <p>There is enormous potential for present-day research to consider the futures of lived social life, environmental conditions, and economies with digitalization and technological enactments. To foray into, conceptualize, and perform the variety of futuring approaches, we must take the theoretical, methodological, and philosophical implications of futures seriously in our research. Our goal in this special issue is to encourage researchers in the IS and adjacent managerial fields to do so. The intended types of contributions to this special issue follow the &#39;digital futures&#39; editorial referenced above and encourage submissions with novel contributions within (or across) three main categories: Engaging in Futuring, Envisioning Futures, and Conceptualizing Futures.  Submissions may examine our relationships with short-term events and technologies or with the long, slow shifts in social norms; moral reasoning; and the power, weight, and significance of institutions, practices, and technologies. We encourage consideration of the philosophical bases for connecting past-present-futures, new methods of futuring, and conceptions of the future as a site of inquiry. Traditional futures-studies approaches are welcome insofar as they contribute to the special issue’s goals. The special issue seeks to be inclusive in terms of diverse approaches to futuring and studying digital futures.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Researching futures to inform present theory and action.</li>
        
        <li>Anthropologic, ethnographic, or speculative design approaches.</li>
        
        <li>Ethical futures: what do we owe the future?</li>
        
        <li>Beyond trajectories of the digital: Anticipating and modelling future worlds.</li>
        
        <li>Precautionary principles: guardrails for dual-use technologies?</li>
        
        <li>Socio-technical construction of the future.</li>
        
        <li>Utopias, dystopias, and science fiction as forms of speculative science.</li>
        
        <li>Non-empirical approaches to knowledge.</li>
        
        <li>Bridging epistemic distance.</li>
        
        <li>Digital transformation in a digital world.</li>
        
        <li>Reconceptualizing the organization.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Invalid DateTime: Target publication date.</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2025: AOM workshop introducing special issue.</li>
        
        <li>August 15, 2025: Submit extended abstract for feedback and workshop admission, max 1500 words, via submission system</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2025: Abstracts invited for workshop.</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2025: Special Issue Workshop Hybrid at ICIS 2025 and online (recommended).</li>
        
        <li>February 15, 2026: First round submission deadline.</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2026: First round decision to authors.</li>
        
        <li>October 15, 2026: Second round submission deadline.</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2026: Second round decision to authors. Papers will be accepted or rejected after the second round of peer review.</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2027: Final revision due (if applicable).</li>
        
        <li>February 28, 2027: Final decision to authors.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Human - AI Collaboration, Emerging Digital Work Configurations and the Changing Nature of Work]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-human-ai-collaboration-emerging-digital-work-configurations-and-the-changing-nature-of-work</link>
            <guid>jit-human-ai-collaboration-emerging-digital-work-configurations-and-the-changing-nature-of-work</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 10:51:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Alexander Richter</strong>, Victoria University of Wellington</p>
        
        <p><strong>João Baptista</strong>, Lancaster University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ella Hafermalz</strong>, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mareike Möhlmann</strong>, Bentley University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Daniel Schlagwein</strong>, The University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mari-Klara Stein</strong>, Tallinn University of Technology</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Digital technologies, in particular artificial intelligence (AI), are reconfiguring how, where, and when work gets done, marking a shift from tools designed to support human tasks to agentic systems that collaborate with and even manage human workers. AI technologies are evolving to work autonomously or within hybrid collaboration systems of human and digital agents. Research on AI and human-AI collaboration has advanced from studying AI that supports human tasks to AI agents’ ability to make independent management decisions and regulate and manage human work. The future of working with AI is, however, still unknown and emergent, with both utopian and dystopian perspectives shaping our understanding of opportunities and challenges of their adoption and use in organizations, work, and other spheres of our lives.</p>
    
    <p>Prior research has helped make sense of and anticipate important side effects of AI-driven management, new forms of hidden and unrecognized ‘meta-work’ performed by employees, and the ‘ripple effects’ of introducing such technologies to the workplace. This includes the reconfiguration of spatial-temporal dimensions and ‘ways of seeing’ in the workplace, tensions between craft and mechanical work, and a wide range of unintended effects in work contexts such as loss of critical thinking and changes in how human work is coordinated as well as the authority and values that underpin it. New research is needed to develop relevant theories and methods to study human-AI collaboration and how this is reconfiguring work.</p>
    
    <p>This special issue invites submissions that critically examine the current and expected future effects of human-AI collaboration and other emerging digital work configurations. It seeks theoretical, empirical, and design-oriented contributions that study the transformative potential of digital-human collaboration, aiming to gather research that fosters ethical solutions and sustainable models for AI- and digitally-driven work, while informing future digital work scenarios. It encourages work that inspires innovative strategies and follows good research practice in the use of AI, but is also open to developing prospective scenarios and actively creating preferable futures.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Emerging Human - AI Work Configurations</li>
        
        <li>Effects of AI and Agentic Systems in the Workplace, Work, and Organizing</li>
        
        <li>Governance, Responsibility, and Ethics of AI Agents</li>
        
        <li>Adaptive Practices and Human - AI Dynamics</li>
        
        <li>Strategic and Organizational Implications of Human - AI Collaboration</li>
        
        <li>New Digital Work Configurations and Changing Nature of Work Beyond AI</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical and Methodological Advancements</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>August 15, 2025: Submissions due</li>
        
        <li>November 15, 2025: Notifications (submissions)</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2026: Revisions due</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2026: Notifications (revision 1)</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2026: Second revision due</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2026: Notifications (revision 2)</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2026: Target publication</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Future of Information Systems in the Enterprise]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-the-future-of-information-systems-in-the-enterprise</link>
            <guid>jit-the-future-of-information-systems-in-the-enterprise</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 03:00:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Robert Winter</strong>, University of St. Gallen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Karlheinz Kautz</strong>, RMIT University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Sabherval</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Leona Chandra Kruse</strong>, University of Agder</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The use of information systems in the enterprise is the backbone of digital transformation and digital business, acting as the binding force between technological, managerial, and organizational innovations. The design and use of information systems in the enterprise evolve alongside technological advancements, shifting managerial strategies, and changing organisational forms and needs (Kotusev, 2019).</p>
    
    <p>&quot;Enterprise information systems&quot; has been the key term for information systems that transcend narrow functions, processes, products, markets, or concerns (e.g., ERP, SCM, CRM) and integrate these elements, supporting end-to- end, creating synergy, and ensuring coherence in the enterprise context (Cao et al., 2022; Robey et al., 2002).</p>
    
    <p>Given the rapid pace of change and advancements in emerging technologies (e.g., artificial intelligence, edge computing), alternative approaches to information systems used in enterprises (e.g., shadow IT, cloud/as-a-service), and structures beyond single enterprises (e.g., platforms, ecosystems), this special issue is focused on the future of information systems in the enterprise context and deliberately uses this broader term to emphasise our interest in both conventional enterprise information systems and alternative IS/IT solutions used for similar enterprise-level issues.</p>
    
    <p>Information systems in the enterprise have undergone fundamental paradigm shifts in the past four decades. First, the integration scope of such systems has expanded to include customer activities, supply chains, and business ecosystems (Ignatiadis &amp; Nandhakumar, 2007; Sambhara et al., 2022). Second, technological innovations have fundamentally changed the characteristics and positioning of information systems in the enterprise. These innovations include, among others, transitioning from on-premises to cloud-based operations, shifting from traditional license to as-a-service models, incorporating analytic and execution functionalities, integrating with or evolving into digital platforms, adopting edge computing, and adding artificial intelligence functionalities (Dong et al., 2009; Flak et al., 2022). These developments set the stage for future challenges, such as how enterprises will further enhance agility and innovation through emerging technologies.</p>
    
    <p>Third, managerial innovations require greater flexibility from information systems in the enterprise. These include, among others, the rise of digital platforms and business ecosystems, end-to-end process integration, agile business organization, and continuous development and integration (Aral et al., 2024). Fourth, new types of enterprise systems and other information systems in the enterprise enhance value creation for old and new stakeholders, justifying significant investment while necessitating more sophisticated approaches for their design, development, governance, and operations (see further, Nah et al., 2001; Scott &amp; Vessey, 2002; Dong et al., 2009; Pang et al., 2014; Haki et al., 2020; Mikalef et al., 2020; Flak et al., 2022).</p>
    
    <p>The future of information systems in the enterprise is complex. IS practice must adapt to technological, managerial, and organizational innovations while IS research may need to integrate insights from work on enterprise systems, enterprise architecture, as well as IS governance, digital transformation, IS sourcing, and digital platforms. This special issue aims to address these challenges by inviting disciplinary and interdisciplinary submissions that provide important insights on the direction and future of information systems in the enterprise. Specifically, &quot;The Future of Information Systems in the Enterprise&quot; special issue seeks to generate new knowledge that addresses key practical or theoretical challenges.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Alternatives to traditional enterprise information systems such as digital platforms, shadow IT, no-code/low-code, and how the challenges they bring for coherent management, and our understanding of enterprise-level systems</li>
        
        <li>Designing future information systems in the enterprise with concerns for both business and societal values</li>
        
        <li>Exploring how technological or organizational innovations in the enterprise / enterprise-level context challenge and extend existing knowledge and theory</li>
        
        <li>Extending and adapting the body of knowledge to encompass specific contexts, such as strategies, industries, ecosystems, or specific organizational configurations</li>
        
        <li>Horizontal (cross-unit) and vertical (technology-to-business) integration through information systems in the enterprise</li>
        
        <li>Specific integration challenges of technology, organization, and humans in the enterprise / enterprise-level context</li>
        
        <li>Intersection of artificial intelligence and other emerging technologies in information systems in the enterprise</li>
        
        <li>Intersection/relation of enterprise and platform/ecosystem-level systems and technologies, and the corresponding challenges such as for organizational strategy</li>
        
        <li>Understanding and harnessing the complexity of enterprise computing</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 1, 2024: Extended abstract submissions via email to the corresponding special issue editor for early feedback and invitation to the special issue paper development workshop.</li>
        
        <li>November 15, 2024: Results are announced.</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2024: Special issue paper development workshop at ICIS 2024.</li>
        
        <li>April 1, 2025: First-round submissions.</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2025: First-round decisions.</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2025: Second-round submissions.</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2026: Second-round decisions (Papers are either acceptable with minor changes or rejected).</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2026: Final versions (Final decisions and online publication soon afterwards).</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Pär Ågerfalk</strong>, Uppsala University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rainer Alt</strong>, University of Leipzig</li>
        
        <li><strong>Vanessa Cooper</strong>, RMIT University Melbourne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rob Gleasure</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kazem Haki</strong>, HES Geneva</li>
        
        <li><strong>Taha Havakhor</strong>, McGill University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hartmut Hoehle</strong>, University of Mannheim</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sherah Kurnia</strong>, University of Melbourne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, UNSW</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jan Mendling</strong>, Humboldt-Universität</li>
        
        <li><strong>Annette Mills</strong>, University of Canterbury</li>
        
        <li><strong>Petter Nielsen</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ralf Plattfaut</strong>, University Duisburg-Essen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Matti Rossi</strong>, Aalto University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Helana Scheepers</strong>, Swinburne University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Priya Seetharaman</strong>, Indian Institute of Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pankaj Setia</strong>, Indian Institute of Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Matthias Söllner</strong>, University of Kassel</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zach Steelman</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tuure Tuunanen</strong>, University of Jyväskylä</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Regulation in the Age of Digitalization]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-regulation-in-the-age-of-digitalization</link>
            <guid>jit-regulation-in-the-age-of-digitalization</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:32:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Daniel Gozman</strong>, University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Tom Butler</strong>, University College Cork</p>
        
        <p><strong>Kalle Lyytinen</strong>, Case Western Reserve University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The rise of information technology (IT) in organizations has been an inherent part of an agenda to increase and shape forms of social control. Despite the inherent link between uses of IT and social control, the topic of regulation has not received significant attention in the information system field – neither theoretically nor empirically. This special issue seeks to address this gap.</p>
    
    <p>The issue explores the growing and significant interplay between IT and regulation in the age of digitalization, where new challenges with social control with IT are emerging. In this special issue, we are interested in two broad domains of research related to regulation and IT: regulation through IT and regulation of IT.</p>
    
    <p>The first domain – regulation through IT – concerns new forms and arenas of regulation enacted through innovative IT solutions (often called “RegTech”). These technologies which are increasingly implicated in regulatory practices include new forms of real-time big data analytics, machine learning and other artificial intelligence (AI) techniques, use of blockchains and distributed ledgers, Internet of Things solutions or natural language processing techniques. These technologies change the ways organizations and industrial sectors respond to and comply with a growing number of regulatory obligations and needs. These technologies are also driving changes in the ways in which regulators seek to supervise and monitor firms and the ways in which firms comply with laws and regulations. Greater market and organizational transparency and enhanced supervision are now advocated as critical responses to organizational misconduct and associated risks. This has resulted in an increasing call for bureaucratization and (over-) regulation. Call for greater monitoring, supervision and sanctioning have been driven by concerns regarding the environment, health and safety risks, corporate fiscal and fiduciary scandals, financial failures leading to financial crisis in 2007-2008, or growing violations of data privacy that increased the “volume, velocity and variety” of laws and regulations that organizations must comply with and the range of novel IT based solutions they need to comply to such demands. Regulators have also shown a growing appetite to measure performance, to quantify financial, regulatory and operational risk and to improve compliance reporting through new technologies that assign accountability, enforce security and behavioural control, automate monitoring and enhance record keeping.</p>
    
    <p>The second domain – regulation of IT – is the wide range deployment and associated regulatory effects of new IT (especially concerns of security, privacy and/or safety). There is a notable gap in the field’s knowledge regarding new demands and ways of regulating IT (e.g., social media) given its scale, complexity and pervasive use. Concerns regarding the pervasive effects of platform businesses on privacy, competition and information veracity have invited calls to control and scrutinize technology vendors. Similar issues are likely to emerge in autonomous cars, user-based insurance, health policies and so on. There are consequently increased demands to regulate various IT solutions and to increase regulatory powers of governments related to IT uses, including through introducing entirely new regulatory bodies. If platform providers and vendors, or organizations offering extensive algorithmic solutions as parts of their related services, are subjected to new regulatory structures, then important questions arise regarding what degrees of transparency and reporting are appropriate and how related forms of supervision and sanctioning would function that need to regulate actual systems and their functioning and those who are implicated in their design.</p>
    
    <p>We invite empirical and theoretical research that contribute to our understanding and application how regulation is enacted through IT or how uses of IT can be regulated. We encourage submissions that use diverse epistemological and methodological approaches to focus on emerging and new regulatory solutions and practices. Submissions may engage in cross-disciplinary inquiries and should offer novel knowledge and fresh methodological, theoretical and empirical insights how regulation and IT evolve and are related. The papers will be evaluated for their interestingness, novelty and credibility of the contribution. If in doubt, interested authors should consult the special issue guest editors whether their papers fall within the scope of the special issue. To this end, authors are encouraged to submit an extended abstract to the editors for initial feedback.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Regulatory technologies for supervising and complying (regulation through IT)</li>
        
        <li>Regulation of social media technologies and platforms</li>
        
        <li>Regulation of IT solutions and related solutions during design, implementation and use</li>
        
        <li>Regulation of AI</li>
        
        <li>How to bridge the gap between ethics and policy (e.g., for AI)</li>
        
        <li>Strategic implications of regulating technologies for nations, industries and firms</li>
        
        <li>Solutions for data privacy, protection, governance and &quot;fake news&quot;</li>
        
        <li>Cybersecurity obligations and mitigating related risks at the organizational level</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>January 31, 2021: First round submission</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2021: Round 1 decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2021: Second round submission</li>
        
        <li>September 1, 2021: Second round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>November 1, 2021: Third and Final Round submissions</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2021: Final decision to authors</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Barney Tan</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Chris Parker</strong>, American University</li>
        
        <li><strong>David Tilson</strong>, University of Rochester</li>
        
        <li><strong>Eric Lim</strong>, University New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>Francois de Vaujany</strong>, Université Paris - Dauphine</li>
        
        <li><strong>Frantz Rowe</strong>, Université de Nantes</li>
        
        <li><strong>Heiko Gewald</strong>, Neu - Ulm University of Applied Science</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jonas Hedman</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>M. Lynne Markus</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Markos Zachariadis</strong>, University of Warwick</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michael zur Muehlen</strong>, Stevens Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michel Avital</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mikhail Oet</strong>, Northeastern University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nicholas Berente</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pierangelo Rosati</strong>, Dublin City University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Roman Beck</strong>, IT University of Copenhagen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shazia Sadiq</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Silvia Masiero</strong>, Loughborough University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stefan Haefliger</strong>, City University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Theo Lynn</strong>, Dublin City University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Uri Gal</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Vladislav Fomin</strong>, University of Vilnius</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Emerging Technologies and IS Sourcing]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-emerging-technologies-and-is-sourcing</link>
            <guid>jit-emerging-technologies-and-is-sourcing</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:31:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ilan Oshri</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Oliver Krancher</strong>, IT University of Copenhagen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Sabherwal</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The last decade has seen a significant proliferation of new technologies. These include robotic process automation, big data, machine/deep learning and artificial intelligence, blockchain, and other &quot;emerging technologies&quot;. Consulting and market research companies have consistently predicted that the current wave of technologies will transform both front and back office operations, requiring firms to rethink their business models and strategies.</p>
    
    <p>While evidence suggests that firms will continue to invest in emerging technologies, there has so far been little evidence about the involvement of service providers and advisory in the selection, design, and adoption of such emerging technologies. IS sourcing research has conventionally accounted for three main areas of interest: sourcing decision, contractual structures, and relationship management. Emerging technologies challenge these traditional conventions in the IS sourcing literature. Particular challenges include but are not limited to: greater dependency on data in emerging technologies, which triggers clients to source data science services; the actual implementation of emerging technology often happens through platforms that involve multiple players and services; the asset transfer model has become less relevant and yet client firms are still expected to reduce their headcount; there is greater emphasis on the redesign of the value chain as services have become digitized and decisions are now driven by smart algorithms; emerging technologies are viewed as a black box, posing a skills and expertise challenge to client firms to ensure acquiring and retaining knowledge of the technology.</p>
    
    <p>Further, the IS sourcing literature which has traditionally relied on three main reference theories, namely, transaction cost economics, resource dependency, and social exchange. Emerging technologies emphasize the need to expand this theoretical base and accommodate new paradigms of capturing and analyzing data in IS sourcing research. Taking into account the above observations, the IS sourcing literature thus begs for the re-examination of client-supplier-advisory relationships by challenging core concepts of sourcing decision, contractual structure, and relationship management as offering new theoretical landscapes that accommodate the sourcing phenomenon in a digital age.</p>
    
    <p>This special issue seeks to facilitate an empirical and theoretical re-examination of &quot;IS sourcing&quot; in the light of the current wave of emerging technologies. We invite research papers that investigate issues relating to emerging technologies and IS sourcing, particularly focusing on robotic process automation, big data, machine/deep learning and artificial intelligence, and blockchain. Other technologies are less of interest for this special issue.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Governance and control structures between client-supplier-advisory in emerging technology settings</li>
        
        <li>Sourcing decision making in emerging technology settings</li>
        
        <li>Ecosystem and platforms in emerging technology sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Contract management in emerging technology sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Full data lifecycle in emerging technologies and its implications for sourcing management</li>
        
        <li>Skills and capability development and retention in emerging technology sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Implications for innovations within the client-supplier-advisory eco-system</li>
        
        <li>Ethical and societal implications deriving from such sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Impact of emerging technologies on client’s, supplier’s and advisory’s strategies, business models and capabilities</li>
        
        <li>Implications of crowdsourcing, big data, analytics as well as machine/deep learning and artificial intelligence for the contemporary IS outsourcing</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>April 15, 2021: First round submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>July 25, 2021: First round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>October 25, 2021: Second round submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>January 28, 2022: Second round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2022: Third and final round submissions deadline</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2022: Final decision to authors</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ethical Issues and Unintended Consequences of Digitalization and Platformization]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-ethical-issues-and-unintended-consequences-of-digitalization-and-platformization</link>
            <guid>jit-ethical-issues-and-unintended-consequences-of-digitalization-and-platformization</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:30:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Matti Rossi</strong>, Aalto University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Christy M. K. Cheung</strong>, Hong Kong Baptist University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Supratek Sarker</strong>, University of Virginia</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jason B. Thatcher</strong>, Temple University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Disruptive digital innovations do not come without pain – the disorder that they introduce can create negative externalities and unintended consequences for people, communities, industries and economies. In the worst case, there is disruption with little innovation. This can lead to job losses for individuals, loss of human dignity, negative health impacts, lost revenue for communities, obsolescence of industries and loss of the traditional values that underpin modern societies.</p>
    
    <p>Sarker et al. (2019) note that “humanistic concerns arising from the curtailing of human freedom and development, and from racism, sexism and commodification of the human body are overlooked for the apparent benefits that systems, including widely used search engines and medical databases, promise to deliver (Noble 2018; Wachter-Boettcher 2017). Indeed, there is a rising need for a thorough ethical interrogation of algorithms (O’Neil 2016) that underlie systems mediating many critical human activities, so as not to marginalize certain stakeholders, especially those ‘who are already in the margin’ (Noble 2018, p. 171).</p>
    
    <p>In this special issue, we take this critical, yet constructive view of technological and social changes associated with “digital transformation” (Zuboff 2015, Wood et al. 2019, Larsson and Teigland 2020). We are interested in contrarian papers that reject the taken-for-granted assumptions of positive impacts of technology, as in cases of digital platforms, telework enabled by mobility, growth of the gig economy, fintech/blockchain, and so on, and investigate relatively unexamined platform externalities as a means to identify ways to resolve paradoxes, discontinuities and challenges posed by technology and the unintended consequences of technology applications.</p>
    
    <p>We also seek papers that shed light on the problems of information technology (IT)-enabled phenomena such as the implications of winner-takes-all platform economics; highlight the social, environmental and economic implications of blockchain and similar innovative digital technologies; or propose solutions that mitigate negative societal impacts of innovation (e.g., through leveraging the power social networks to disseminate information and strengthen democratic discourse).</p>
    
    <p>We encourage the submission of manuscripts taking either of two stances: 1) Submissions considering a critical or dystopian view of the social, technological and moral implications of digitization and digital transformation. Here, “the dark side” – ethical issues, unintended digitalization and other problematic aspects – of digitalization and platformization are front and centre the argument. An example may be Zuboff’s (2015, 2019) recent work on surveillance capitalism and her analyses of large-scale digitization “gone wrong”. 2) Submissions seeking to balance or reconcile “the dark side” and “the bright side” of digitalization and platformization. Here, analyses, exemplars and theoretical frameworks considered ethical issues and negative consequences explicitly, in addition to intended benefits of digitalization too often exclusively focused on. An example may be social media research: initial writings trumpeted the benefits of social media for building relationships, with later work highlighting problematic behaviours such as cyberbullying or doxxing.</p>
    
    <p>In this special issue, we are open to all forms of inquiry, including surveys, experiments, case studies, design science projects and conceptual work that probe “the dark side”, ethical issues and unintended consequences of digitization, platformization and the rapid diffusion of digital infrastructures and digital work models based thereon.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Digital Taylorism and the race to the bottom for workers</li>
        
        <li>Destruction of jobs by “botization”</li>
        
        <li>Risks for society from fast-spreading false information</li>
        
        <li>Systemic risks and vulnerability of digital platforms</li>
        
        <li>Management incompetence in digital transformation</li>
        
        <li>Risks of IoT and blockchain</li>
        
        <li>Dark side and ethics of sharing economy and gig economy</li>
        
        <li>Digital privacy and surveillance capitalism</li>
        
        <li>Bias in algorithms and artificial intelligence</li>
        
        <li>Digital inequity and digital divide between “the North” and “the South”</li>
        
        <li>Fake news, misinformation, and disinformation in social media</li>
        
        <li>Fake and biased online reviews and co-creation on digital platforms</li>
        
        <li>The emergence of deep web/dark net marketplaces</li>
        
        <li>Subjective well-being (e.g., FOMO and social media fatigue)</li>
        
        <li>Cyberharassment, cyberbullying and cyberstalking</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>June 1, 2021: First round submission</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2021: First round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2022: Second round submission</li>
        
        <li>April 1, 2022: Second round decision to authors (reject or accept with minor revision)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Margunn Aanestad</strong>, Agder University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Benlian</strong>, TU Darmstadt</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michelle Carter</strong>, Washington State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tommy Chan</strong>, Northumbria University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mike Dinger</strong>, University of South Carolina - Upstate</li>
        
        <li><strong>Taha Havakor</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>J. J. Po - An Hsieh</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hanna Krasnova</strong>, University of Potsdam</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, UNSW Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alvin Leung</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juho Lindman</strong>, University of Gothenburg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jani Merikivi</strong>, Grenoble Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Daniel Pienta</strong>, Baylor University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marten Risius</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Markus Salo</strong>, University of Jyvaskyla</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sebastian Schuetz</strong>, Florida International University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carsten Sorensen</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ali Sunyaev</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Lancaster University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Manuel Trenz</strong>, University of Göttingen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xiao Xiao</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Products of Theorizing: Towards Native Theories of Emerging IT]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-products-of-theorizing-towards-native-theories-of-emerging-it</link>
            <guid>jit-products-of-theorizing-towards-native-theories-of-emerging-it</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:29:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Nik Hassan</strong>, University of Minnesota Duluth</p>
        
        <p><strong>Suzanne Rivard</strong>, HEC Montreal</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ulrike Schultze</strong>, Southern Methodist University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Leslie Willcocks</strong>, London School of Economics and Political Science</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Theorizing is one of the defining aspects of academic research. Articulating insights generated from situated empirical observations into relatively stable abstractions (e.g., concepts, propositions, models) that elucidate, explain or predict events occurring at another time and place is the hallmark of knowledge generation (King 2021). Of late, much attention has been paid to theory development in the Information Systems (IS) field. For example, the MIS Quarterly (MISQ) special issue on &#39;Next-Generation Information Systems Theorizing&#39; reflects a sense of urgency felt within the IS field to make sense of an increasingly unruly and complex reality given the increasing pace of technological innovation (Burton-Jones et al. 2021). In similar vein, two 2021 Journal of Information Technology (JIT) debates sections focused on &#39;IS Research and Science&#39; (Siponen and Klaavuniemi 2020, and commentaries) and &#39;Theorising as Craft&#39; (Rivard 2021, and commentaries) and a recent Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS) special issue focused on &#39;Envisioning Digital Transformation – Advancing Theoretical Diversity&#39;. New and native IS theories ensure that the IS field remains vibrant, diverse, academically and socially relevant and influential (Hassan 2011; Hassan and Willcocks 2021; Lowry et al. 2020; Markus and Saunders 2007). Researchers, however, often set the bar too high for theory delivered within individual research contributions by viewing theory as a comprehensive and detailed explanation of a phenomenon (Rivard 2021), an object that Weick (1995) refers to as a &#39;theory that sweeps away all others&#39; (p. 386). This mindset may lead IS researchers to adopt theories from other fields as a foundation rather than creatively developing new and native theories from empirical observations (Grover and Lyytinen 2015).</p>
    
    <p>To maintain the long-term growth and vitality of the IS field, a definition of theory that encourages cumulative and novel theorizing over time is needed (Hassan and Willcocks 2021; King 2021). One way of achieving this is by advancing a &#39;products of theorizing&#39; perspective (Weick 1995). The theorizing perspective celebrates both the final outcomes and the &#39;interim struggles&#39; that characterize theory generation (Weick 1995). It holds the promise that interim conceptual artifacts of theorizing such as metaphors, frameworks and concepts (Lowry et al. 2020) are valuable to the discipline as they can be leveraged and exploited further in subsequent research. In this way, a discipline might inch its way towards native theories over time. The goal of this special issue is to solicit and showcase exemplars from the &#39;products of theorizing&#39; approach. We are looking for articles that go beyond verification dimensions of the natural-science approach to IS research (Schlagwein 2021) and push the envelope of theorizing towards native products of theorizing (Hassan et al. forthcoming): theory frame devices (i.e., questions, paradigms, laws and frameworks), theory generators (i.e., myths, analogies, metaphors and models) and theory components (i.e., concepts, constructs, statements and hypotheses).</p>
    
    <p>The time is ripe to embark upon the development of native theories in the IS field, as IT has leaped into the consciousness of the public in unprecedented ways. Big data and AI applications are part of consumers’ and workers’ everyday lives, either enhancing them or increasing their visibility (Aral 2020; Benbya et al. 2021; Zuboff 2019); firms increasingly deploy robotic process automation and cognitive automation, aiming to achieve benefits for themselves, their employees and their customers (Lacity and Willcocks 2021); and governments rely on new forms of data collection about citizens (e.g., blood samples, vaccination data, fingerprints, iris-recognition systems) in support of the services they provide (Kolas et al. 2021). To take advantage of the theorizing opportunities that these emergent information technology (IT) phenomena provide, the goal of this special issue is to encourage research that generates products of theorizing derived from and related to IT phenomena. We are seeking contributions that develop products of theorizing, that is, interim constructions, that are useful as precursors to strong native IS theory. To increase the likelihood of a theorizing product’s value, we are particularly interested in research that tackles phenomena that are core to the IS discipline. Given the multifaceted nature of the IS discipline, we do not expect agreement on what constitutes a core IS phenomenon. We therefore encourage authors to make the case that the products of theorizing they develop are valuable for articulating native theories that are defining of the field of IS or are substantially valuable for their specific area.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Use of theory generators (e.g., analogies, myths, models and metaphors) for understanding and guiding research of emergent phenomena such as surveillance capitalism, fake news, social media, or the performativity of big data and AI.</li>
        
        <li>Constructing or formulating novel frameworks derived from or relevant to emerging technologies.</li>
        
        <li>Adopting a genealogical lens to uncover the products of theorizing that have been instrumental in the theories that have become popular in the IS discipline (e.g., socio-technical, sociomateriality, imbrication).</li>
        
        <li>Reviewing and analysing the foundations of core concepts of the IS field such as that of &#39;information,&#39; &#39;system&#39; and &#39;technology&#39;.</li>
        
        <li>Re-theorizing areas or subfields within IS (e.g., design science, data analytics, big data, AI) where native products of theorizing are sparse.</li>
        
        <li>Problematizing the IS field (i.e., going beyond gap-spotting and borrowing theory from reference disciplines) to identify questions and challenges that the field of IS is uniquely qualified to address.</li>
        
        <li>Inventing native original concepts in the IS field that will serve as foundations for the scientific IS research method and declare to the world, the field’s core concerns.</li>
        
        <li>Exploring the role of scientific laws in IS research as a product of theorizing with relevance to emerging phenomena.</li>
        
        <li>Unpacking products of theorizing (e.g., questions, models and frameworks) that uncover deep-seated assumptions about contemporary IS phenomena (e.g., symbols of value, solidarity, social structure, conflict and contradictions within a technology-driven society) that are especially relevant to emerging technologies.</li>
        
        <li>Distinguishing between non-observable constructs from more observable concepts that are rarely discussed in IS research but form the mainstay of scientific studies.</li>
        
        <li>Aggregating the statements, claims and propositions that have been made by a stream of IS literature and that are deemed most impactful on and relevant for contemporary users, organizations and society, to set the stage for the further progress towards native IS theory.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>October 24, 2021: Extended abstracts (for workshop and feedback) due</li>
        
        <li>December 12, 2021: Workshop at ICIS 2021 SIG PHIL</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2022: First-round submissions version due</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2022: First-round reviews returned</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2022: Second-round submissions due</li>
        
        <li>August 30, 2022: Second-round reviews returned</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2022: Final versions due</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2022: Final decisions and publication online</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Transformation as Geo-Political, Organizational and Technological Nexus]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-digital-transformation-as-geo-political-organizational-and-technological-nexus</link>
            <guid>jit-digital-transformation-as-geo-political-organizational-and-technological-nexus</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:28:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Wendy L. Currie</strong>, Audencia Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Carol Hsu</strong>, The University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ben Van Vliet</strong>, Illinois Institute of Technology</p>
        
        <p><strong>Vishanth Weerakkody</strong>, University of Bradford</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue focuses on the currently ongoing – and recently COVID-19 -accelerated – digital transformation(s) of economy and society. That is, how industry sectors and societal domains are reshaped by the geo-political, organizational and technological nexus that is &#39;digital transformation&#39;. The literature on digital transformation is interdisciplinary, spanning fields such as information systems (Vial, 2019), management (Hanelt et al., 2021) and other business disciplines (Verhoef et al., 2021). However, this work&#39;s broad range and somewhat incoherent framings show a lack of consensus of &#39;digital transformation&#39; as both a theoretical concept and an empirical field (Warner and Wager, 2019).</p>
    
    <p>Thus far, most digital transformation studies have focused on the organization as the unit of analysis. Why a single definition of digital transformation may be elusive, the digital transformation seems most often used to as a just a shorthand for IT-enabled organizational transformation (Besson and Rowe, 2012; Wessel et al, 2020), an organization-centric approach. Digital transformation processes increasingly take place at wider scales, beyond individual organizations and their business processes. Digital transformation(s) affect financial markets (Currie et al., 2018), healthcare (Pouloudi et al., 2016) or government (Weerakkody et al., 2016). Digital transformation(s) hence often have disruptive effects in relation to industry structures, corporate strategy, consumer experiences, policies and overall economic and societal trajectories (Legner et al., 2017; Zuboff, 2015; Vial, 2019).</p>
    
    <p>In this special issue, we invite especially that a) study digital transformation as a process (preferred over simplistic &#39;cause-and-effect&#39; hypotheses), and b) understand digital transformation in a broad sense, that is, in relation to industries, governments, economies and societies (preferred over organization-centric approaches).</p>
    
    <p>We are interested in work that understands digital transformation as a process. Studies of interest may use process theories, process analyses and/or process data to provide explanations (Langley, 1999). Process studies offer a means of conceptualizing events and identifying patterns (Gehman et al., 2018). These aspects have often been neglected in IS studies in favour of simplistic variance models (Karpovsky and Galliers 2015). Approaching digital transformation fundamentally as a process promises to produce theoretical accounts with nuanced explanations of change (Weick and Quinn, 1999). Variance models (and other types of models) are also welcomed to the special issue. Still, they will be expected to pay attention to digital transformation as a process and not to neglect the relevant processual patterns or temporal order.</p>
    
    <p>We are interested in work that studies digital transformation in a broad sense. Such work may see digital transformation as a nexus of technological, organizational, industrial, economic, governmental, societal and geo-political changes. This nexus invites theoretical and empirical studies which extend organization-centric views to understanding wider processes in which digital IT plays a key role. Emerging IT (artificial intelligence and machine learning, robotics and automation, blockchains and cryptocurrencies, meta- verses, remote working technologies, etc.) may generate specific opportunities for such research. Digital transformations come with significant challenges for businesses and societies, governments, and regulators across jurisdictions. Organization-centric approaches are welcomed to the special issue but must pay attention to wider developments and contexts and argue why the organization is the best locus of study.</p>
    
    <p>In preparing papers for this special issue, authors are expected to engage with the concept of digital transformation as a process and provide critical theoretical and/or empirical analysis extending beyond IT-driven change of isolated business processes.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Study digital transformation as a process</li>
        
        <li>Understand digital transformation in a broad sense, in relation to industries, governments, economies and societies</li>
        
        <li>Digital transformation of industry sectors (e.g., health, finance, retail)</li>
        
        <li>Digital transformation driven by ecosystems and platforms</li>
        
        <li>Regulation and governance of digital transformation</li>
        
        <li>Process studies on digital transformation identifying episodic and/or continuous changes</li>
        
        <li>Revealing unintended consequences of digital transformation or the corresponding policies, strategies, and operations</li>
        
        <li>Multi-disciplinary studies on digital transformation, especially if leading to novel theoretical perspectives</li>
        
        <li>Extreme or revealing digital transformation cases or scenarios</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>April 15, 2022: Abstracts submissions (optional; authors are invited to submit extended abstracts of papers for early reactions)</li>
        
        <li>August 15, 2022: First-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>October 20, 2022: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2023: Second-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2023: Second-round decisions (papers are either acceptable with minor changes or rejected at this stage)</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2023: Final versions due (final decisions and online publication soon afterwards)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Next-Generation Information Systems Research Methods]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-next-generation-information-systems-research-methods</link>
            <guid>jit-next-generation-information-systems-research-methods</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:27:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Ivo Blohm</strong>, University of St. Gallen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Susanna Ho</strong>, Australian National University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Oklahoma</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jan Marco Leimeister</strong>, University of St. Gallen</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue is interested in &#39;next-generation&#39; research methods for studying information technology (IT) phenomena – particularly in the information system (IS) research field. So far, IS researchers have applied a range of quantitative, qualitative and engaged methods to study IT-related phenomena. Quantitative IS research has often followed a positivist approach of hypothesis testing, with sometimes &#39;first-generation&#39; regression models distinguished from &#39;second-generation&#39; structural equation models (Gerow et al. 2011). Data used in such methods stems from surveys, experiments, panel studies, etc. The primary objective of this research stream typically is theory testing. Qualitative IS research has ranged from positivist to interpretivist, seeking rich situated insights via case studies, grounded theory or ethnographies. One objective of this research stream is theory construction. Critical and emancipatory IS research adds a strong value orientation and theoretical basis to qualitative research. Another type of IS research seeks to generate new knowledge with &#39;engaged&#39; methods like design science or action research. The objective of this stream that differentiates it from the first two is the focus on solving important individual, organizational or societal challenges; or extending the boundaries of human and organizational capabilities by creating new and innovative artifacts (Baskerville and Wood-Harper 1996; Hevner et al. 2004).</p>
    
    <p>In recent years, the scope of and possibilities for IS research have tremendously widened. Digital IT have become mainstream at the individual, organizational and societal levels (Burton-Jones et al. 2021). Digital IT is key to innovation in various domains from medicine to education, from psychology to the arts. Hence, these domains have become of interest and relevance to IS researchers, yet also overlap with other fields and are hence interdisciplinary in nature. These innovations are increasing the volume and variety of trace data available to researchers but necessitate a shift in our research practices (Johnson et al. 2019). Further, big data, machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI) technologies provide a plethora of powerful approaches for collecting and analysing data at a scale not possible before such that we might need to adapt our research methods and tools to make this data actionable and to generate novel knowledge. These ML technologies are being applied not only to theory testing but also to theory construction – in conjunction with or independent of qualitative methods (Miranda et al. 2022).</p>
    
    <p>This special issue focuses on the next generation of research methods to study IT – new methods relevant to the IS research field that account for a) the interdisciplinary nature and wider scope of IT phenomena, and/or b) the novel capacities afforded by new technologies/techniques (e.g., ML/AI). The way that novel technologies and techniques afford new possibilities is quite apparent in quantitative IS research. In contrast to &#39;first-generation&#39; regression-based approaches and &#39;second-generation&#39; structural equation modelling, a new generation of research methods including the predictive analytics (Shmueli and Koppius 2011), data mining (Smith 2020), ML (Shrestha et al. 2020) or explainable AI (Gunning et al. 2019) come with substantial new opportunities and challenges. For instance, these methods potentially allow for more fine-grained measurements and analyses to extend our knowledge of existing phenomena and may help us study novel phenomena including those that were, methodologically speaking, &#39;out of reach&#39; (George et al. 2016). These technological advancements enable us to progress our research toolkit and inform new ways of generating knowledge and theorizing (Burton-Jones et al. 2021; Shrestha et al. 2020). Increased recognition of abduction as a counterpart to deductive and inductive reasoning (Behfar and Okhuysen 2018; Sætre and Van de Ven 2021) pits concerns about practices such as HARKing (Kerr 1998) – hypothesizing after the results are known (aka p-hacking) – believed to lead to logically and scientifically flawed hypotheses, against concerns about stifling the advancement of knowledge (Pratt et al. 2019). ML/AI techniques are now so powerful that they can test millions of models on large data sets to find the &#39;best-matching&#39; model (of all possible) for what needs to be explained. This is a fundamental gear change in what can be done with quantitative data sets, the promise and validity of which are hotly debated (Kitchin 2014; Smith 2020).</p>
    
    <p>In terms of changes to the nature of the IS domains, qualitative-interpretative researchers seek to find new methods suitable for the wider, interdisciplinary scope of IS research. This is done via finding or developing analytical new grounds and looking at digital IT differently (e.g. via sociomaterial or affordances perspectives), seeking additional foundations in other fields (e.g., Zuboff’s (2015) political economy informed analysis of surveillance capitalism and &#39;Big Tech&#39;) or via the modification of methods to suit digital environments (e.g., virtual ethnographies or computational grounded theory). Other forms of qualitative research such as meta-synthesis, qualitative comparative analysis and discourse analysis also seem promising and relevant but are seldomly used in IS research. Digital IT (e.g., social media, digital platforms, AI/ML) has increasing and substantial impacts on society (e.g., mental health, trust in science, misinformation and polarization, monopolization and industry disruption). Hence, ethical, critical, value-based and political-economy questions are increasingly and necessarily asked about digital IT. Similarly, today’s pace of innovation may also warrant novel approaches to engaged scholarship and design science. For instance, researchers are calling for methods that can accumulate and update evidence more effectively (Lacity et al. 2021) and better ensure the generalizability of prescriptive knowledge (Brendel et al. 2021; Iivari et al. 2021).</p>
    
    <p>This special issue invites contributions that propose, introduce, debate or critique novel quantitative, qualitative or design-oriented methods research, with a focus on the &#39;how&#39; (i.e., origins, processes, steps of the method) and the &#39;why&#39; (e.g., &#39;rigour vs relevance&#39; and &#39;it is new, but is it better&#39; questions) these approaches should be used in IS research. The goal of the special issue is to provide a space for introducing and discussing innovative &#39;next-generation&#39; methods for studying IT-related phenomena, relative to the IS research field.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Critical reflection of research methods used in IS.</li>
        
        <li>Introducing new qualitative, quantitative or design research methods.</li>
        
        <li>Transferability of non-IS research methods such as from other fields or praxis.</li>
        
        <li>Novel combinations of research methods such as cross-disciplinary or mixed-method approaches.</li>
        
        <li>Innovative approaches to analyze big data.</li>
        
        <li>Approaches dealing with special types of unstructured data.</li>
        
        <li>Problems of null hypothesis testing via big data and AI/ML.</li>
        
        <li>AI, ML and explainable AI for knowledge creation and theory generation.</li>
        
        <li>Transparent, robust and replicable research designs and methodologies.</li>
        
        <li>Transferability and generalizability of insights generated with specific methods.</li>
        
        <li>Approaches to evaluating and communicating practical relevance of findings.</li>
        
        <li>Critical assessment of novel approaches on practical, conceptual, ethical or philosophical grounds.</li>
        
        <li>Philosophy of science-based proposals for or critiques of methods.</li>
        
        <li>Culture and values-driven proposals for or critiques of methods.</li>
        
        <li>Methods to study the past, the present and/or the future.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 20, 2022: Abstract submissions: (optional; authors are invited to submit extended abstracts of papers for early reactions)</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2023: First-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2023: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2023: Second-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>February 15, 2024: Second-round decisions: (papers are either acceptable with minor changes or rejected at this stage)</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2024: Final versions due: (final decisions and online publication soon afterwards)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Decentralised Information Systems: New Thinking and New Paradigms]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-decentralised-information-systems-new-thinking-and-new-paradigms</link>
            <guid>jit-decentralised-information-systems-new-thinking-and-new-paradigms</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:26:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Ali Sunyaev</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mary Lacity</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Michel Avital</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue seeks to explore and extend the conceptualisation, design, development, implementation and governance of contemporary “decentralised” information systems. “Decentralised” information systems are often seen as an important anti-thesis to “centralised” such systems. Modern societies and economies rely more highly on data, information systems, and technologies than ever. Pioneering organisations brought forth major milestones in developing and providing information technologies (e.g., TCP/IP and the Internet). However, with the significance of information technology increasing over the past decades, a small number of organisations have emerged as “tech giants” (e.g., Alphabet/Google or Meta/Facebook). Those organisations offer digital services and infrastructures for data processing that gained large-scale adoption by individuals, organisations, governments and society at large. As a result, societies, economies and technical systems became strongly dependent on services from a handful of organisations. The increase of the resulting dependencies leads to a centralisation of information systems. Highly-centralised information systems can result in global organisations and central social actors that abuse their power and pursue their own interests at the expense of others (e.g., by manipulation), exclude participation from social actors who disagree with them (e.g., by censorship) or invade their privacy through monitoring (e.g., by tracking actions of individuals on the internet). Highly-centralised information systems can also pose several further risks. For example, governance rights – such as rights of access, validation, software updates, data policies, and data overrides – may be centralised with few social actors in control. From a technical perspective, successful attacks on and crashes of central computing devices for network message propagation can interrupt communication in computing systems and even bring about system failures.</p>
    
    <p>To avert risks of over-centralization, the purposeful decentralisation of information systems has become a prominent topic of public discourse, for example, around Internet search, cloud computing, social media and financial systems. An information system’s degree of decentralisation refers to the degree to which the information system is independent of central actors and technical constructs. Several attempts have been made to design decentralised information systems to improve collaboration between actors while reducing dependencies on central authorities. Such endeavours include the development of decentralised token economies based on distributed ledger technology, decentralised identity management systems and distributed collaborative machine learning systems (e.g., federated learning systems). Although information systems decentralisation may resolve several of the above issues of over-centralisation, it also comes with its own challenges. For example, maintaining decentralised information systems can become difficult when multiple social actors need to update their technical components independently. Extensive data replication across technical components in decentralised information systems (e.g., in blockchain systems) can facilitate detecting and exploiting software vulnerabilities. If too many social actors have opposing ideas, decentralised governance risks never reaching an agreement. When only a few social actors participate in governance, information systems envisioned to be decentralised may de facto centralise.</p>
    
    <p>To purposefully achieve the benefits of information system decentralisation, we need to consider both the design of information systems as such and the behaviour of the social actors involved. Information systems decentralisation is driven by interdependent economic, political, social and technical factors. As an example of technical factors, the innovation of blockchain technology supports the decentralisation of asset ownership management. Changes to corporate information system designs, corporate ecosystems, and regulatory refinements are required to facilitate the development and adoption of such technical innovations. Such changes can lead to the centralisation of information systems in other aspects, such as their organisational structures. The entanglement of interdisciplinary factors tightly makes information systems decentralisation an interdisciplinary topic, relevant to several research fields, including computer science, organisational studies and information systems. The interdependence between information system designs and the influence of interdisciplinary factors makes the purposeful decentralisation of information systems an important yet complex undertaking that this special issue seeks new knowledge about.</p>
    
    <p>The complexity of information system decentralisation leads to various open questions, such as “how to achieve and sustain appropriate degrees of decentralisation of information systems so that individuals, organisations, and entire business ecosystems can benefit”, “how decentralised enterprise information systems need to be designed”, and “what technical know-how and involvement is required from actors to decentralise information systems appropriately”? This special issue seeks to improve the understanding of how the various factors affect the decentralisation of information systems used in business and other societal contexts, how different degrees of decentralisation of such information systems emerge over time, and how different degrees of decentralisation of information systems can affect business ecosystems, business processes, and societies overall. We invite applied, empirical, and theoretical research works that investigate information system decentralisation in a way that acknowledges its interdisciplinary nature and significantly contributes to understanding information system decentralisation, its manifestations, antecedents, and its impact on individuals and organisations, ecosystems and societies. We welcome and encourage submissions from researchers using diverse epistemological and methodological approaches. The manuscripts will be evaluated for the interestingness and novelty of their contributions.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Decentralised information systems for enterprises (e.g., information systems design and implementation for enterprises)</li>
        
        <li>Decentralised organisations and information systems decentralisation, including decentralised autonomous organizations (DAOs), decentralised platforms, token-driven governance and work practices</li>
        
        <li>Asset monetisation and similar information systems decentralisation, including web3, non-fungible tokens (NFTs) and digital assets</li>
        
        <li>Consumer privacy and information systems decentralisation, including self-sovereignty vs. self-responsibility</li>
        
        <li>The token economy, including tokenomics business models, effects of regulation and standardisation on decentralised token economies</li>
        
        <li>Digital resilience and information systems decentralisation, including critical information infrastructures</li>
        
        <li>Information systems decentralisation for the public good and social benefit, including decentralised voting, decentralised universal basic income (UBI) schemes and support of the decentralised supply of green energy by information systems</li>
        
        <li>Financial information systems decentralisation, including cryptocurrencies and community coins</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>January 15, 2024: Manuscript submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>April 19, 2024: First round reviews and decisions</li>
        
        <li>August 30, 2024: Second round (revision) submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>November 29, 2024: Second round reviews and decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 7, 2025: Final submission deadline for accepted manuscripts (subject to minor revisions)</li>
        
        <li>May 9, 2025: Final approval of manuscripts</li>
        
        <li>March 31, 2026: Online publication of special issue (anticipated date)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Roman Beck</strong>, IT University of Copenhagen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Erran Carmel</strong>, American University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada</li>
        
        <li><strong>Klitos Christodoulou</strong>, University of Nicosia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Raffaele Ciriello</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gilbert Fridgen</strong>, University of Luxembourg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rob Gleasure</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Robert Wayne Gregory</strong>, University of Miami Herbert Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hanna Halaburda</strong>, New York University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Niclas Kannengiesser</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Johann Kranz</strong>, Ludwig-Maximilians-University Munich</li>
        
        <li><strong>George Kuk</strong>, Nottingham Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gerhard Schwabe</strong>, University of Zurich</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carsten Sørensen</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alfred Taudes</strong>, Vienna University of Economics and Business</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jason Bennett Thatcher</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nils Urbach</strong>, Universität Bayreuth</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wenqian Wang</strong>, Perdue</li>
        
        <li><strong>Edgar Whitley</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>