<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | MIS Quarterly</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/journal/mis-quarterly</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers for MIS Quarterly.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 04:13:21 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | MIS Quarterly</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/journal/mis-quarterly</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ethics, Regulation, and Policy]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/misq-ethics-regulation-and-policy</link>
            <guid>misq-ethics-regulation-and-policy</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 03:16:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Stefan Seidel</strong>, University of Cologne</p>
        
        <p><strong>Nicholas Berente</strong>, University of Notre Dame</p>
        
        <p><strong>Hong Guo</strong>, Arizona State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Wonseok Oh</strong>, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Wave upon wave of digital technologies and the fast-advancing frontier of artificial intelligence (AI) are disrupting well-established, institutionalized ways of doing things, resulting in a host of ethical, regulatory, and policy challenges. The challenge involves addressing social, ecological, moral, and economic risks associated with technological advancements while, at the same time, encouraging competitiveness, innovation, and value generation from ubiquitous digital data. To address current ethical challenges and risks and anticipate future issues related to emerging technologies, governments are seeking to adjust regulations and set policy. Organizations are seeking to adapt their governance schemes to regulatory and ethical issues. This special issue seeks sociotechnical and information systems contributions to our thinking on ethics, regulation, and policy around digital technologies, data, and AI.</p>
    
    <p>Ethical tensions abound in relation to the pervasiveness of digital data and the widespread adoption of AI, including tensions between data privacy, fairness, and bias on the one hand, and business needs for using data for market and innovation purposes on the other. AI systems that increasingly replace cognitive tasks previously done by humans raise questions about deskilling and labor substitution and ultimately human dignity. While AI systems promise productivity gains and the potential to address key social and environmental issues, they also generate significant threats to sustainability and social challenges. Moreover, the responsibility of algorithms for the tasks they perform and the decisions they make is often not clear. The autonomy, interconnectedness, and increasing agency of digital technologies present challenges to established individualistic responsibility approaches since they make it difficult to attribute responsibility.</p>
    
    <p>The tension between addressing ethical risks and encouraging innovation requires balancing data privacy, fairness, and bias concerns with business needs for competitiveness and value generation from digital data and AI systems.</p>
    
    <p>Ethical challenges have inspired regulatory and policy action around digital technologies, particularly with respect to data and AI. The United States National Artificial Intelligence Act of 2020 sets forth programs and activities and highlights values like trustworthiness; at the same time, it aims at creating competitive advantage for the US economy by creating an innovation ecosystem or fostering public-private partnership mechanisms. The European Union&#39;s AI Act embeds fundamental values as it seeks to accomplish a high level of protection of health, safety, and fundamental rights and defines requirements for transparency monitoring, market surveillance, and governance that provide legitimacy for the use of AI systems. Regulatory responses involve institutional construction and ongoing institutional change, often requiring the deliberate coordination and action of change agents at different levels, including political, corporate, or non-governmental individuals and groups. Rapid changes in the sociotechnical context fueled by the decentralized and immaterial nature of digital technologies require frequent updates and often render conventional approaches to setting regulation and policy slow and ineffective.</p>
    
    <p>Digital technologies serve a dual role—they are both the source of ethical concerns triggering regulatory change and a tool for implementing, monitoring, and updating policies and regulations, distinguishing regulation of technology from regulation through technology. Such tools help regulatory institutions achieve legitimacy and stability, which marks the distinction between regulation of technology and regulation through technology. Ethical challenges as well as policy and regulatory change require organizational efforts to adopt and comply with new regulations and policies. This is challenging, since it requires organizational actors to make sense of and interpret the often-complex changes in the regulatory institutional environment and demands changes in organizational practices as well as technology architecture and implementation.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Technology/AI/data ethics</li>
        
        <li>Technology/AI/data regulation</li>
        
        <li>Technology/AI/data policy</li>
        
        <li>Institutions</li>
        
        <li>Governance</li>
        
        <li>Risk</li>
        
        <li>Digital</li>
        
        <li>Sociotechnical</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 13, 2026: Submission Deadline</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Alessandro Acquisti</strong>, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Benlian</strong>, Technical University of Darmstadt</li>
        
        <li><strong>Min Chen</strong>, George Mason University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aaron Cheng</strong>, The London School of Economics and Political Science</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ioanna Constantiou</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>John Dong</strong>, Nanyang Technological University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anna Essén</strong>, Stockholm School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Haiyang Feng</strong>, Tianjin University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stefan Feuerriegel</strong>, Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich</li>
        
        <li><strong>Uri Gal</strong>, The University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>James Gaskin</strong>, Brigham Young University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Goh Khim Yong</strong>, National University of Singapore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anand Gopal</strong>, Nanyang Technological University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Brad Greenwood</strong>, George Mason University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dominik Gutt</strong>, RWTH Aachen University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ola Henfridsson</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nina Huang</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jannis Kallinikos</strong>, The London School of Economics and Political Science</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gerald C (Jerry) Kane</strong>, University of Georgia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wolf Ketter</strong>, University of Cologne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Cameron Kormylo</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Natalia Levina</strong>, New York University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zhepeng (Lionel) Li</strong>, The University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kalle Lyytinen</strong>, Case Western Reserve University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Min-Seok Pang</strong>, University of Wisconsin-Madison</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hani Safadi</strong>, University of Georgia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nachiketa Sahoo</strong>, Boston University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Monash University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mari-Klara Stein</strong>, TalTech</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lai Wei</strong>, Shanghai Jiao Tong University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yi Yang</strong>, The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lior Zalmanson</strong>, Tel Aviv University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nan Zhang</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xia Zhao</strong>, University of Georgia</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>MIS Quarterly (MISQ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI-IA Nexus: The Future of Information Systems Security, Privacy, and Quality]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/misq-ai-ia-nexus</link>
            <guid>misq-ai-ia-nexus</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 05:11:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Rui Chen</strong>, Iowa State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Juan Feng</strong>, Tsinghua University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Miguel Godinho de Matos</strong>, Católica Lisbon School of Business &amp; Economics</p>
        
        <p><strong>Carol Hsu</strong>, University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>H. Raghav Rao</strong>, University of Texas at San Antonio</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Digital threats continue to impede information assurance. Many issues in information assurance have arisen in the last decade or two, including risk management, information quality, intellectual property, privacy protection, compliance with regulations, and continuity of operations. As a result, protecting information has become a global priority, and collaborative efforts are being made to prevent, detect, and react to threats to information quality, authenticity, integrity, confidentiality, and availability.</p>
    
    <p>As society steps into the age of generative AI (GenAI), fresh challenges and opportunities are arising in the realms of information security, privacy, and quality. Questions have emerged regarding the role and intended/unintended consequences of GenAI in information assurance. GenAI is believed to pose a paradox, serving as a dual-edged sword in the realm of information assurance.</p>
    
    <p>The emergence of GenAI is poised to exert a profound impact on assurance. On the one hand, GenAI has been recognized for its ability to bolster information assurance and has the potential to strengthen business defenses, accelerate security processes, and identify emerging threats as they arise. On the other hand, GenAI heightens the potency of existing threats, allows the fabrication of false information, fuels intellectual property theft, and poses challenges to governance and compliance. The 2024 February deepfake fraud incident in Hong Kong is a case in point.</p>
    
    <p>Tremendous new opportunities exist for information systems scholars to study information assurance issues within the context of GenAI, as traditional approaches may not work. This special issue seeks research that goes beyond simple applications of existing theories and methods from the cybersecurity literature in IS. We invite studies that explore the unique information assurance challenges in the realm of GenAI, calling for the development and application of new theories or methods.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Sophisticated human-deception attacks including vishing and deepfakes</li>
        
        <li>Hallucination and confabulation leading to misinformation</li>
        
        <li>Intellectual property theft from GenAI-generated content</li>
        
        <li>Regulation and compliance challenges with GenAI models</li>
        
        <li>Unreliable training data and its impact on LLMs</li>
        
        <li>Data poisoning risks in AI models</li>
        
        <li>Security leaks and inference attacks related to GenAI</li>
        
        <li>Prompt injections and their implications</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>January 20, 2025: Two-page abstracts due</li>
        
        <li>October 31, 2025: First-round paper submission</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2026: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2026: Workshop for authors with R&amp;R</li>
        
        <li>May 31, 2026: Second-round revisions due</li>
        
        <li>August 31, 2026: Second-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>November 30, 2026: Final revisions due</li>
        
        <li>February 28, 2027: Final revisions</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Panagiotis Adamopoulos</strong>, Emory University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jingjing Li</strong>, University of Virginia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rodrigo Belo</strong>, Nova School of Business and Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Huigang Liang</strong>, University of Memphis</li>
        
        <li><strong>Indranil Bose</strong>, NEOMA</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Maedche</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lemuria Carter</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ning Nan</strong>, University of British Columbia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Christy Cheung</strong>, Hong Kong Baptist University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jella Pfeiffer</strong>, University of Stuttgart</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rahul De&#39;</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Bangalore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dandan Qiao</strong>, National University of Singapore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Amany Elbanna</strong>, University of Sussex</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sagar Samtani</strong>, Indiana University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Uri Gal</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anastasia Sergeeva</strong>, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam</li>
        
        <li><strong>Weiyin Hong</strong>, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maha Shaikh</strong>, ESADE Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nina Huang</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Paolo Spagnoletti</strong>, Luiss Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hartmut Höhle</strong>, University of Mannheim</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rohit Valecha</strong>, University of Texas at San Antonio</li>
        
        <li><strong>Allen Johnston</strong>, University of Alabama</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jing Wang</strong>, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Arpan Kar</strong>, Indian Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jingguo Wang</strong>, University of Texas at Arlington</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juhee Kwon</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hong Xu</strong>, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Atanu Lahiri</strong>, University of Texas at Dallas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alvin Leung</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ting Li</strong>, Erasmus University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Heng Xu</strong>, University of Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Niam Yaraghi</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Cathy Liu Yang</strong>, HEC Paris</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yingjie Zhang</strong>, Peking University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>MIS Quarterly (MISQ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Institutional Press in the Digital Age]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/misq-the-institutional-press-in-the-digital-age</link>
            <guid>misq-the-institutional-press-in-the-digital-age</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 05:15:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Ahmed Abbasi</strong>, University of Notre Dame</p>
        
        <p><strong>Brad N. Greenwood</strong>, George Mason University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Melissa Mazmanian</strong>, University of California, Irvine</p>
        
        <p><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Robert Seamans</strong>, New York University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Over the last 20 years, ongoing waves of digitalization have decimated the traditional business model of the news and fundamentally changed how the news, or more formally, the &#39;institutional press&#39;, works. Indeed, ever since reserved frequencies were gifted to television broadcasters in the 1950s, on the condition that they inform the public of current events, the subsidy underpinning newspapers and other forms of institutional media has slowly eroded. Like many other industries, the internet has accelerated this phenomenon. Not only has the hyper-targeted advertising facilitated by social media and other platforms functionally eroded the subsidy model to its breaking point; but the costless transmission of data facilitated by the internet has increased geographic scope of dominant players, permitting them to reach beyond their original markets and squeeze content producers across the globe. Against this backdrop, it is hard to overstate the importance of this &#39;crisis of the institutional press&#39;. The news provides our primary means for understanding the world around us. Societies desperately need a well-functioning institutional press to tackle the many societal, economic, and environmental challenges we all face.</p>
    
    <p>Digital transformation has decimated traditional news business models through hyper-targeted advertising and costless data transmission, fundamentally threatening society&#39;s primary means for understanding the world and tackling critical challenges. The first day of core MIS undergraduate or MS/MBA classes usually begins with one of four motivating examples: the decline of incumbent sellers in favor of digital platforms, the increasing irrelevance of diseconomies of scale and the rise of digital monopolies, the rise of social media and user generated content, or the decline of the newspaper industry. Yet, as these classes continue to discuss the opportunities firms have in the digital age, the decline of institutional media often fades into the background.</p>
    
    <p>This phenomenon-driven special issue is motivated by the view that our students, colleagues, and society urgently need a better understanding of the causes and consequences of the changing nature of news in the digital era and potential solutions going forward. The special issue takes an interdisciplinary perspective, bringing together insights from across the broader information, managerial, and organizational sciences.</p>
    
    <p>This failure to discuss the implications of the decline of institutional news media is troubling. Not only has the Fourth Estate historically served to counterbalance institutions with a monopoly on force and morality, it has been a cornerstone of democratic republics for centuries. The claims regarding the influence of the press are not idle musings. News media outlets have been shown to influence many societal outcomes, from government agendas to public opinion to voting behavior. Yet, seismic changes have assaulted the free press as we understand it, notably with the increasing concentration in ownership of news outlets, leading to elevated reliance on advertising revenue that biased content. The recent history of the institutional press is interwoven with the history of digital technology, reshaping the roles and responsibilities of professional news organizations.</p>
    
    <p>Research has only begun to address the transformations occurring within the institutional press. The purpose of this Special Issue is to address this gap in scholarship and to inform stakeholders about how changes in institutional media are affecting society at the intersection of business, technology, and public policy. To this end, we invite scholarship that helps academia and society comprehend the major changes taking place within the institutional press, why those changes are occurring, and what the consequences of those changes are.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>The changing nature of the press, news media as an institution, and the consequences of those changes</li>
        
        <li>Re-envisioning the &#39;institutional&#39; nature of the evolving institutional press</li>
        
        <li>Spillovers from: the changing nature of governance, digital threats and/or violence against journalists, the decline of local news, the endangering of the local watchdog, and online/offline credibility</li>
        
        <li>The functioning of, and implications for, non-traditional digital era news sources</li>
        
        <li>Content characteristics (i.e., genres such as world news, politics, economy, tech, lifestyle/entertainment)</li>
        
        <li>Social media platforms and practices that legitimatize or delegitimatize institutional media</li>
        
        <li>The role of professional standards and gatekeeping in today&#39;s news media ecosystem and mechanisms to support them</li>
        
        <li>The news as a dynamic construct across time and space, and the consequent implications for content generation and consumption</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>April 30, 2024: Optional abstract submission due</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2024: Full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 15, 2025: First-round decisions expected</li>
        
        <li>May 30, 2025: Revision Plan Meeting with SI Editors (tentatively)</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2025: Second-round revisions due</li>
        
        <li>October 15, 2025: Second-round decisions expected</li>
        
        <li>February 15, 2026: Third and final revisions submissions due</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2026: Final decisions expected</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Mike Ananny</strong>, University of Southern California</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jens Foerderer</strong>, Technische Universität München</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anand Gopal</strong>, Nanyang Technological University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Brent Kitchens</strong>, University of Virginia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gene Moo Lee</strong>, UBC Sauder School of Business</li>
        
        <li><strong>Attila Marton</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jeffrey Nickerson</strong>, Stevens Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Christopher Parker</strong>, American University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Caitlin Petre</strong>, Rutgers University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Christian Peukert</strong>, HEC Lausanne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aleš Popovič</strong>, NEOMA Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jui Ramaprasad</strong>, University of Maryland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Imke Reimers</strong>, Cornell University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jie Ren</strong>, Fordham University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gaurav Sabnis</strong>, Stevens Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ananya Sen</strong>, Carnegie Mellon University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jananki Srinivasan</strong>, IIIT-Bangalore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xiao Xiao</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yi Yang</strong>, HKUST</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nan Zhang</strong>, University of Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aljona Zorina</strong>, IESEG</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>MIS Quarterly (MISQ)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>