<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/</link>
        <description>Calls for Papers shows you the latest calls for papers of academic journals in your discipline.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 03:20:21 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Critical National Infrastructure]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jmis-critical-national-infrastructure</link>
            <guid>jmis-critical-national-infrastructure</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 03:20:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Jason Chan</strong>, University of Minnesota</p>
        
        <p><strong>Alan Dennis</strong>, Indiana University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Daniel Gozman</strong>, The University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Kalle Lyytinen</strong>, Case Western Reserve University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Critical National Infrastructure (CNI) encompasses essential systems and services that are vital for societal stability, economic security, and national safety. The increasing digitalization of these infrastructures has introduced unprecedented efficiencies that have transformed economies, enabling faster service delivery, improved public safety, reduced corruption, and enhanced crisis response through data sharing and analytics.</p>
    
    <p>The United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) supports digital public infrastructure (DPI) as a driver for financial inclusion, social protection, and governance reforms. Digital advancements have also driven sustainability, with smart grids, environmental monitoring, and optimized resource management with potential for reducing carbon footprints and increasing resilience.</p>
    
    <p>Furthermore, technological innovation in financial services, transportation, and energy has the potential to stimulate economic growth through enabling new business models. While the increasing digitalization of Critical National Infrastructure has introduced efficiencies, it also created unprecedented vulnerabilities, including cyberattacks, cascading failures, and systemic interdependencies that amplify risks.</p>
    
    <p>Recognizing these challenges, governments in the UK, US, and Australia have developed regulatory frameworks such as the UK’s National Cyber Security Strategy, the US Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency (CISA) guidelines, and Australia’s Security of Critical Infrastructure Act (SOCI Act) to enhance resilience and mitigate emerging threats.</p>
    
    <p>CNI spans multiple critical sectors, each with unique security and operational challenges, including energy and utilities, telecommunications and information networks, financial services and payments, healthcare and public health, transportation and logistics, emergency services and law enforcement, and government and public sector infrastructure.</p>
    
    <p>As efforts to build CNIs have accelerated, issues around CNI security, resilience, and adaptability are becoming increasingly critical. At the same time significant research gaps remain in cybersecurity practices at the system level, governance, integration and management of emerging technologies such as Autonomous Driving Systems, and threat intelligence sharing.</p>
    
    <p>Addressing these gaps is essential for policymakers, businesses, and infrastructure operators to mitigate threats, optimize performance, and ensure long-term continuity.</p>
    
    <p>This Special Section aims to advance research on the design, adoption, and impact of digital solutions and services critical in building CNI to enhance governance, economic development, and public service delivery and safeguard CNI. We invite interdisciplinary contributions that explore how digital technologies and services can enhance CNI or impose new risks and challenges for the operation of CNIs. Papers that do not explicitly address or theorize about CNI design and operation and their digital components will be returned without review.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Emerging Technologies and Digital Transformation: Innovative technologies such as Artificial Intelligence, Digital Twins, Blockchain and IoT are transforming CNI, enabling predictive analytics, smart grids, and cyber-physical security enhancements.</li>
        
        <li>Cybersecurity, Resilience, and Risk Management: Cyber threats such as ransomware, insider attacks, and cyber-physical vulnerabilities continue to grow. Risk assessment frameworks and mitigation strategies are essential.</li>
        
        <li>Governance, Policy, and Public-Private Partnerships: CNI governance requires polycentric collaborative efforts between government agencies, private sector entities, and international stakeholders.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>June 1, 2025: Expression of Interest: one-page abstract, optional</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2026: Initial Submission Due</li>
        
        <li>May 31, 2026: Notification of First Round Decision</li>
        
        <li>September 30, 2026: 1st Resubmission Due</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2027: Notification of Second Round Decision</li>
        
        <li>April 30, 2027: 2nd Resubmission Due</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2027: Final Decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Management Information Systems (JMIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Futuring: ‘Digital’ Futures as a Novel Site of Inquiry and Imagination]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-futuring-digital-futures-as-a-novel-site-of-inquiry-and-imagination</link>
            <guid>jit-futuring-digital-futures-as-a-novel-site-of-inquiry-and-imagination</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 03:16:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Dirk S. Hovorka</strong>, The University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Benjamin Mueller</strong>, University of Bremen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Elizabeth Davidson</strong>, University of Hawaii - Manoa</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mike Chiasson</strong>, University of British Columbia</p>
        
    
    
    <p>What attention do we owe the future(s)? The Information Systems (IS) and adjacent research fields engage with the design, implementation, and evaluation of increasingly powerful digital technologies and with studies of their impact on work, knowledge, sustainability, and organizing. Given the rich and growing body of theories and findings from research on these wide and long-term impacts, the potential for researchers to help envision, inform, critique, and shape how these technologically-infused futures – &#39;digital futures&#39; – develop are immense.</p>
    
    <p>Despite this rich potential, most discussions of the future implications of digitalization in IS research are abstract and nominal, typically assuming a singular &#39;future&#39; will arise from the technological advances studied. Discourses on the future with digital technologies rarely bring the worlds and practices that emerge from, shape, and transform futures to the foreground for a close and critical examination. Similarly, whether or to what extent such worlds and practices will discernibly be digital to any meaningful degree is often just assumed, which focuses our attention on specific aspects that may no longer be salient in futures. As a result, researchers tend to cede these important discussions and considerations to visionaries, technology firms, and &#39;evangelists&#39; in business and consultancy.</p>
    
    <p>To the degree that IS research does consider the future, the implications of digital technologies in the discourse are often contradictory. On the one hand, an optimistic, instrumental view depicts the broad range of technologies as &#39;tools&#39; under social control, which can (and will) produce an economically, socially, and environmentally sustainable future. On the other hand, a substantive view of technology casts technology as dark, uncontrollable forces that (inevitably) result in personal, societal, and environmental distress. For instance, the dominating discussions of AI in research illustrate these contradictory &#39;hopes and fears&#39;. Neither view of technology sufficiently challenges researchers to engage actively with futuring – that is, the envisioning, informing, critiquing, and helping to shape possible futures systematically through research practices. Hence, the purpose and focus of this special issue is on futuring work – active, imaginary, forward-looking research work in IS or related fields that is informing or shaping our &#39;digital&#39; futures.</p>
    
    <p>Research approaches that address the worlds and practices that shape digital possibilities and the multiplicity of futures that could result are possible. These strategies can overcome nominal approaches to considering the future and build on the rich socio-technical positions already present in IS research. To do so, researchers need to consider new ways of futuring that go beyond simple extrapolations of current trends into the future or tacit acceptance of technology’s inevitable path. One way to do so is to loosen the grip of empiricism in IS research and broaden our relationship to futures, for instance, by engaging with speculation and imagination in research, creating speculative engagements with future possibilities, and deconstructing the narratives and expectations of the present. These and other approaches to futuring can be highly significant to what emerging phenomena can be observed, where present-day research interests and practices are directed, and ultimately, what future worlds are realized through the technologies we study.</p>
    
    <p>There is enormous potential for present-day research to consider the futures of lived social life, environmental conditions, and economies with digitalization and technological enactments. To foray into, conceptualize, and perform the variety of futuring approaches, we must take the theoretical, methodological, and philosophical implications of futures seriously in our research. Our goal in this special issue is to encourage researchers in the IS and adjacent managerial fields to do so. The intended types of contributions to this special issue follow the &#39;digital futures&#39; editorial referenced above and encourage submissions with novel contributions within (or across) three main categories: Engaging in Futuring, Envisioning Futures, and Conceptualizing Futures.  Submissions may examine our relationships with short-term events and technologies or with the long, slow shifts in social norms; moral reasoning; and the power, weight, and significance of institutions, practices, and technologies. We encourage consideration of the philosophical bases for connecting past-present-futures, new methods of futuring, and conceptions of the future as a site of inquiry. Traditional futures-studies approaches are welcome insofar as they contribute to the special issue’s goals. The special issue seeks to be inclusive in terms of diverse approaches to futuring and studying digital futures.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Researching futures to inform present theory and action.</li>
        
        <li>Anthropologic, ethnographic, or speculative design approaches.</li>
        
        <li>Ethical futures: what do we owe the future?</li>
        
        <li>Beyond trajectories of the digital: Anticipating and modelling future worlds.</li>
        
        <li>Precautionary principles: guardrails for dual-use technologies?</li>
        
        <li>Socio-technical construction of the future.</li>
        
        <li>Utopias, dystopias, and science fiction as forms of speculative science.</li>
        
        <li>Non-empirical approaches to knowledge.</li>
        
        <li>Bridging epistemic distance.</li>
        
        <li>Digital transformation in a digital world.</li>
        
        <li>Reconceptualizing the organization.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Invalid DateTime: Target publication date.</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2025: AOM workshop introducing special issue.</li>
        
        <li>August 15, 2025: Submit extended abstract for feedback and workshop admission, max 1500 words, via submission system</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2025: Abstracts invited for workshop.</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2025: Special Issue Workshop Hybrid at ICIS 2025 and online (recommended).</li>
        
        <li>February 15, 2026: First round submission deadline.</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2026: First round decision to authors.</li>
        
        <li>October 15, 2026: Second round submission deadline.</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2026: Second round decision to authors. Papers will be accepted or rejected after the second round of peer review.</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2027: Final revision due (if applicable).</li>
        
        <li>February 28, 2027: Final decision to authors.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Paper Development Workshop]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isj-isj-paper-development-workshop</link>
            <guid>isj-isj-paper-development-workshop</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2025 03:07:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ravi Patnayakuni</strong>, University of Alabama in Huntsville</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yingqin Zheng</strong>, University of Essex</p>
        
        <p><strong>Zhongyun (Phil) Zhou</strong>, Tongji University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Information Systems Journal, as part of its outreach efforts, will be holding a Paper Development Workshop along with the 2025 Pacific-Asia Conference on Information Systems in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. The half-day workshop will be held on Sunday, July 6, 2025, from 8:30 am to 12:30 pm as an in-person pre-conference workshop. ISJ welcomes research that spans across the diverse and interdisciplinary IS field.</p>
    
    <p>The paper development workshop aims to nurture scholarship across the broad spectrum of information systems researchers. We welcome work that examines both established and emerging areas within IS. The workshop aims to provide a supportive environment for researchers to develop their ideas and receive constructive feedback on their work from the journal’s editorial board members. We especially encourage submissions from author(s) planning to submit their work to ISJ’s forthcoming special issue on &#39;Theorising the Impacts of Generative Artificial Intelligence&#39;, which has a submission deadline of December 31, 2025, and any other special issues announced before the workshop deadline.</p>
    
    <p>The workshop welcomes papers at various stages of development, from early conceptual work to papers nearing completion. We encourage submissions that show potential for theoretical or practical contribution to the IS field, regardless of their current stage. The workshop particularly aims to support researchers who would benefit from early guidance and feedback on their work.</p>
    
    <p>Interested authors are invited to submit papers for possible inclusion in the workshop. Papers that have been accepted, under review, or under revision at other journals, workshops, or conferences should not be submitted. Please note that not all submissions received may be accepted. Papers that are not accepted will not receive feedback. The selected papers will be mentored by at least two members of the ISJ Editorial Board. Additionally, attending author(s) of accepted papers may be assigned manuscripts as discussants.</p>
    
    <p>Please note that the workshop is not associated with any publication. The goal is to offer feedback to the authors that can help enhance the quality of the paper as it is prepared for submission to a suitable journal. Authors do not have an obligation to submit the paper to ISJ but are encouraged to submit their completed papers for publication consideration to the journal in the future. Also, please note that participation in the workshop does not imply favorable consideration or outcome at ISJ.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Submissions from PACIS community</li>
        
        <li>Relationship between technology, business, economy, and society</li>
        
        <li>Examining established and emerging areas within Information Systems</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical or practical contribution to the IS field</li>
        
        <li>Support for early-stage researchers</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>May 12, 2025: Submission Begin</li>
        
        <li>May 19, 2025: Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>June 6, 2025: Decisions</li>
        
        <li>July 6, 2025: ISJ Trending Topics Workshop</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Journal (ISJ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Human - AI Collaboration, Emerging Digital Work Configurations and the Changing Nature of Work]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-human-ai-collaboration-emerging-digital-work-configurations-and-the-changing-nature-of-work</link>
            <guid>jit-human-ai-collaboration-emerging-digital-work-configurations-and-the-changing-nature-of-work</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 10:51:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Alexander Richter</strong>, Victoria University of Wellington</p>
        
        <p><strong>João Baptista</strong>, Lancaster University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ella Hafermalz</strong>, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mareike Möhlmann</strong>, Bentley University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Daniel Schlagwein</strong>, The University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mari-Klara Stein</strong>, Tallinn University of Technology</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Digital technologies, in particular artificial intelligence (AI), are reconfiguring how, where, and when work gets done, marking a shift from tools designed to support human tasks to agentic systems that collaborate with and even manage human workers. AI technologies are evolving to work autonomously or within hybrid collaboration systems of human and digital agents. Research on AI and human-AI collaboration has advanced from studying AI that supports human tasks to AI agents’ ability to make independent management decisions and regulate and manage human work. The future of working with AI is, however, still unknown and emergent, with both utopian and dystopian perspectives shaping our understanding of opportunities and challenges of their adoption and use in organizations, work, and other spheres of our lives.</p>
    
    <p>Prior research has helped make sense of and anticipate important side effects of AI-driven management, new forms of hidden and unrecognized ‘meta-work’ performed by employees, and the ‘ripple effects’ of introducing such technologies to the workplace. This includes the reconfiguration of spatial-temporal dimensions and ‘ways of seeing’ in the workplace, tensions between craft and mechanical work, and a wide range of unintended effects in work contexts such as loss of critical thinking and changes in how human work is coordinated as well as the authority and values that underpin it. New research is needed to develop relevant theories and methods to study human-AI collaboration and how this is reconfiguring work.</p>
    
    <p>This special issue invites submissions that critically examine the current and expected future effects of human-AI collaboration and other emerging digital work configurations. It seeks theoretical, empirical, and design-oriented contributions that study the transformative potential of digital-human collaboration, aiming to gather research that fosters ethical solutions and sustainable models for AI- and digitally-driven work, while informing future digital work scenarios. It encourages work that inspires innovative strategies and follows good research practice in the use of AI, but is also open to developing prospective scenarios and actively creating preferable futures.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Emerging Human - AI Work Configurations</li>
        
        <li>Effects of AI and Agentic Systems in the Workplace, Work, and Organizing</li>
        
        <li>Governance, Responsibility, and Ethics of AI Agents</li>
        
        <li>Adaptive Practices and Human - AI Dynamics</li>
        
        <li>Strategic and Organizational Implications of Human - AI Collaboration</li>
        
        <li>New Digital Work Configurations and Changing Nature of Work Beyond AI</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical and Methodological Advancements</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>August 15, 2025: Submissions due</li>
        
        <li>November 15, 2025: Notifications (submissions)</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2026: Revisions due</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2026: Notifications (revision 1)</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2026: Second revision due</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2026: Notifications (revision 2)</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2026: Target publication</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bright Internet through Secure and Responsible Artificial Intelligence]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/im-bright-internet-through-secure-and-responsible-artificial-intelligence</link>
            <guid>im-bright-internet-through-secure-and-responsible-artificial-intelligence</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 10:47:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Indranil Bose</strong>, NEOMA Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Amany Elbanna</strong>, The University of Sussex</p>
        
        <p><strong>Dan J. Kim</strong>, University of North Texas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Gene Moo Lee</strong>, University of British Columbia</p>
        
        <p><strong>Alvin Chung Man Leung</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The Bright Internet initiatives aim to transform the current Internet landscape into a more secure, trustworthy, and resilient environment. Originating from the recognition of growing cyber threats, data breaches, and the erosion of user trust, the concept of the Bright Internet was developed to address these pressing issues. It seeks to establish a framework where safety, privacy, and accountability are prioritized, ensuring that users can navigate the digital world without fear of malicious activities. The initiative focuses on implementing proactive security measures, fostering a culture of transparency, and promoting responsible behavior among all internet stakeholders. By leveraging advanced technologies and collaborative efforts, Bright Internet aspires to create a digital ecosystem where trust is restored, and the Internet&#39;s potential for positive societal impact is fully realized. Since 2017, the Bright Internet Global Symposium (BIGS) has been established as a forum for exchanging the vision of Bright Internet and discussing research outcomes and advancements surrounding Bright Internet issues. It fosters collaborations among researchers, companies, academic institutions, government bodies, and international organizations to achieve mutual benefits that transcend individual country capabilities.</p>
    
    <p>The Internet ecosystem is evolving rapidly in the Artificial Intelligence (AI) era. The evolution of AI started with supervised and unsupervised machine learning models in the 1950s and these models evolved into deep learning models in the 1990s (LeCun et al., 2015). Subsequently, with the adoption of Generative AI, content creation became extremely easy and fast. However, the veracity of this content is increasingly becoming a challenge to manage in the different open Internet ecosystems. Further traditional AI-based recommendation engines have also witnessed fast adoption in recent times, and sometimes these systems had many unintended consequences, across applications. Newer models of AI often do not have mechanisms to address unintended consequences surrounding responsible and ethical use.</p>
    
    <p>Digital platforms like social media and e-commerce use Internet-based infrastructure for facilitating social and economic interactions which create value across stakeholders who engage on these platforms. These platforms are heavily using AI in activities like content recommendation, dynamic pricing, product recommendations, friend recommendation, online campaign management, marketing automation through chatbots, fraudulent purchase prevention, inventory management, order fulfillment automation, product bundling, customer segmentation, and many more. Some of the applications still use traditional algorithms; many involve newer algorithms of AI like reinforcement learning, federated learning and large language models. We are interested in studies that look at emerging models of AI in different internet platforms, which are adopting them very fast and may have both utopian and dystopian outcomes surrounding information governance.</p>
    
    <p>With the fast adoption of AI, a plethora of challenges are emerging. For example, pricing discrimination happens from dynamic pricing strategies in e-commerce (Hinz et al., 2011). When AI facilitates this personalization, it has the potential to adversely impact specific communities inadvertently. For example, in sharing ride services, there were denial of services consistently to communities that needed extra support during service consumption. Further customers share a lot of demographic and psychographic information during their purchase and surfing behavior. AI applications have the potential to derive complex relationships from this information which can have strong privacy concerns. Fairness, Accountability, Transparency, and Ethics of AI implementation may not be addressed in many of these applications, which may negatively impact user experiences of these digital platforms.</p>
    
    <p>Further, in emerging business models like social commerce, there are many reports on how customers face challenges surrounding purchase fulfillment and service assurance (Zhang &amp; Benyoucef, 2016). There is evidence that online advertisements create content using AI and customers often feel a mismatch of expectations of what they see online versus what they receive as a product or service (Chaudhry, 2022). While internet ecosystems have become more open with time, content creation and recommendations based on AI in these open platforms often face veracity challenges. For example, Roumani (2024) highlights how social media platform features, technical features and vulnerability features affect the active exploitation of vulnerabilities. Similarly, recommendation engines in websites recommend content from other partnering websites through embedded links, which often have misinformation and disinformation (Abbasi et al., 2010). A lot of times, this misinformation is also often created and propagated using AI. Misinformation mixed with correct information sometimes makes detection difficult and adversely affects management decision-making (Lyytinen &amp; Grover, 2017). This may also impact the adoption and usage of these information systems due to different types of concerns (e.g. Chen et al., 2023). However, with AI, it is also possible to address these concerns as well on digital platforms and pave the path for Bright Internet. For example, Hu et al. (2023) highlight how large language models of Generative AI may be used to mine social media signals to detect drug trafficking.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Design of Bright Internet systems that can assist and aid governance of challenges</li>
        
        <li>How can we design systems using AI to address problems like fake websites, sources of misinformation, and propagators to create bright internet ecosystems?</li>
        
        <li>How would addressing these problems affect user experiences?</li>
        
        <li>Managing challenges to Bright Internet surrounding AI and cyber security</li>
        
        <li>What are the types of risks that AI may cause that infringe cybersecurity such as deep fakes?</li>
        
        <li>What should be the principles and technologies to prevent these risks?</li>
        
        <li>How can five principles of Bright Internet be applied to Bright AI: Origin Responsibility, Deliverer Responsibility, Identifiable anonymity, Privacy Protection, and Global Collaboration, but not intended to limit?</li>
        
        <li>Fair regulation of AI: policy and laws at present and in the future</li>
        
        <li>Critically evaluate AI to foster Bright Internet</li>
        
        <li>What is the limit with the perspective of architecture and data to pretrain? How can we manage hallucinations by Generative AI?</li>
        
        <li>How to integrate traditional Analytical AI and Generative AI to ensure truthfulness and optimization in the dialogue?</li>
        
        <li>Adequate mapping of AI solutions and problems to reduce unintended consequences</li>
        
        <li>Validation of the performance of AI application in practice: Cost-effectiveness, Time savings, productivity improvements, etc</li>
        
        <li>Learning to securely use, challenge, and live with AI under Bright Internet</li>
        
        <li>Ethical policies; Global collaboration efforts under associations</li>
        
        <li>Need of education on AI applications: Skilling, Future of Work debates</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>June 30, 2025: First Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>September 30, 2025: Notification of first-round reviews</li>
        
        <li>November 1, 2025: Revised manuscripts due</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2026: Notification of second round reviews</li>
        
        <li>April 30, 2026: Final manuscript due</li>
        
        <li>July 31, 2026: Last date for final acceptance</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information and Management (IM)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Understanding Resistance to Digital Transformation]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isj-understanding-resistance-to-digital-transformation</link>
            <guid>isj-understanding-resistance-to-digital-transformation</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 10:47:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Francesco Appio</strong>, Paris School of Business</p>
        
        <p><strong>Luca Gastaldi</strong>, Politecnico di Milano</p>
        
        <p><strong>Federico Iannacci</strong>, University of Sussex</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Digital transformation has become a major point of discussion in organizations and broader society, yet its overall desirability and consequences remain open to debate. While many practitioners and scholars see these initiatives as avenues for enhancing efficiency, competitiveness, and customer engagement, there is also growing recognition of the complexities, paradoxes, and unintended effects they may introduce. Indeed, the acceleration of digital projects—especially following the COVID-19 pandemic—can invite various forms of resistance, leading to stalled progress and disruptions.</p>
    
    <p>Importantly, digital transformation is increasingly recognized as an overarching and longitudinal process or strategic goal—rather than a one-time deployment of new technological tools—and requires shifts in both capabilities and institutional frameworks. Because this transformation unfolds over time, people may be resisting not only &#39;technology,&#39; but also the evolving cultural, structural, and strategic changes that accompany it. More precisely, resistance is not solely a matter of technical or budgetary constraints; it intersects with organizational culture, leadership approaches, and individual behaviors. The emergence of new technologies—such as Artificial Intelligence (AI), blockchain, the Internet of Things (IoT), and digital twins—can exacerbate concerns about data transparency, automation, &#39;black box&#39; processes, and ethical dilemmas. For some, these technologies prompt anxiety around potential job displacement or fears that advanced automation could undermine trust. In other situations, hurried or incomplete rollouts of new platforms—such as remote work tools—may create friction and lead employees to question their effectiveness.</p>
    
    <p>Studies also highlight the role of deeply held cultural assumptions and legacy mindsets in impeding organizational shifts. In particular, environments that do not support collaboration and experimentation can intensify pushback against change. Generational differences often add another layer of complexity, as digital-native employees may clash with colleagues who have limited exposure to or interest in new technologies. Approaches such as gamification and behavioral nudges show potential to lessen opposition, although their effectiveness remains an active area of inquiry. Additionally, collective pushback or digital boycotts—where groups of employees, consumers, or communities reject new platforms—underscore the importance of trust, data governance, and broader social considerations.</p>
    
    <p>Sustaining digital change over the long run often requires leadership that can manage both the technical and human dimensions of transformation, alongside an organizational culture geared toward continuous learning. Many organizations strive to integrate ongoing upskilling, transparent communication, and stakeholder engagement to reduce uncertainty and foster participation. By examining how and why employees, managers, or external stakeholders resist digital initiatives, researchers can illuminate strategies for balancing innovation with well-founded concerns and ensuring that transformations proceed in a manner consistent with ethical and social expectations.</p>
    
    <p>This special issue invites work that addresses a broad range of questions around resistance to digital transformation. Rather than framing such transformations as inherently beneficial, we encourage submissions that critically examine these processes, questioning when they should (or should not) be pursued and how resistance emerges in diverse contexts. Ultimately, we hope to generate richer insights into how organizations, policymakers, and societies can better navigate the opportunities and risks posed by digital change.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Cultural inertia and institutional friction</li>
        
        <li>Generational mismatches and skill gaps</li>
        
        <li>Augmentation vs. Automation</li>
        
        <li>Gamification and behavioral nudges</li>
        
        <li>Digital boycotts and collective pushback</li>
        
        <li>Organizational learning and adaptation</li>
        
        <li>Distinguishing digital transformation from general IS/IT resistance</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>July 31, 2025: Extended abstract submission for early feedback</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2025: Full paper submission deadline</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Martin Adam</strong>, Georg-August-Universität Göttingen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ravi Patnayakuni</strong>, University of Alabama in Huntsville</li>
        
        <li><strong>Andy Du</strong>, University of Massachusetts Boston</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dimitra Petrakaki</strong>, University of Sussex</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sven Laumer</strong>, Friedrich-Alexander-Universität</li>
        
        <li><strong>Luiz Antonio Joia</strong>, Brazilian School of Public and Business Administration at FGV</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shahla Ghobadi</strong>, University of Leeds</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Journal (ISJ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2027 Review Issue]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jsis-call-for-special-issue-review-articles</link>
            <guid>jsis-call-for-special-issue-review-articles</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 10:47:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rohit Nishant</strong>, Queen&#39;s Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Tuure Tuunanen</strong>, University of Jyväskylä</p>
        
        <p><strong>Wenyu (Derek) Du</strong>, Beihang University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The Journal of Strategic Information Systems dedicates an issue of JSIS each year to review articles in the realm of strategic information systems, broadly defined.</p>
    
    <p>We are now inviting authors to submit review articles for the 2027 Review Issue. We seek high‐impact scholarly surveys of important research literatures in the strategic information systems domain. Such articles will provide a synthesis of recent research and highlight important directions for future inquiries. The Review Issue is open to manuscripts concerning established and emerging topics in the field of strategic information systems, including those dealing with research methods relevant to our context.</p>
    
    <p>Submissions will be evaluated concerning the following criteria:</p>
    
    <p>Relevance. The proposed manuscript should thoroughly review a significant research area within the field of Information Systems that has strategic impact and relevance. We also welcome reviews of important research areas that have yet to make a major impact in the field of Information Systems, but argumentation can be made that the area is of strategic significance to the information systems field. Obviously, it is upon the authors to make a strong linkage of the research area to the IS system phenomena.</p>
    
    <p>Scope of Interest. While the review article must contribute to the strategic information systems literature and its developing agenda, they must speak to scholars in cognate IS domains and fields, including, for example: Strategic Management, Organization Studies and Knowledge Management. Ethical, policy and societal issues can form an important feature.</p>
    
    <p>Organization and Coherence. The review article should follow a logical structure, read clearly, and thoroughly and comprehensively represent extant research in the topic area concerned.</p>
    
    <p>Insight for Future Work. The review article should convey important implications for future research, both in the context of the chosen topic and for the strategic information systems domain more broadly.</p>
    
    <p>Timeliness/Contribution. The review article should normally be on topics for which no recent reviews exist, and it should clearly indicate its intended contribution to knowledge. If existing reviews exist, they need to be identified, and there needs to be compelling argumentation about how the proposed review will contribute to the literature beyond the existing reviews.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>High-impact scholarly surveys of important research literatures in the strategic information systems domain</li>
        
        <li>Synthesis of recent research</li>
        
        <li>Important directions for future inquiries</li>
        
        <li>Established and emerging topics in strategic information systems</li>
        
        <li>Research methods relevant to strategic information systems</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>September 1, 2025: Full draft of paper due</li>
        
        <li>September 1, 2027: Special issue published</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>The Journal of Strategic Information Systems (JSIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Theorising the Impacts of Generative Artificial Intelligence]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isj-theorising-the-impacts-of-generative-artificial-intelligence</link>
            <guid>isj-theorising-the-impacts-of-generative-artificial-intelligence</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 07:52:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Robert Davison</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</p>
        
        <p><strong>Antonio Díaz Andrade</strong>, University of Agder</p>
        
        <p><strong>Manuel Trenz</strong>, University of Gottingen</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Since 2022, we have witnessed an inexorable flood of information about Generative Artificial Intelligence (GAI) and its various components and manifestations. As hypes go, this one seems overdue for a cyclical correction; however, the enthusiasm for GAI across a wide range of contexts still rises. The euphoria permeates not just mainstream society and popular culture, but also business, politics, warfare and, of course, academia. The tone of inevitability about GAI and its benefits is fervent and the passion of many (notably academics, tech pundits and businesspeople) is abundant. This is not to say that there are no critical voices: there are, but their concerns risk being submerged by the tide of optimism and it may seem heretical to critique, let alone excoriate, the GAI phenomenon.</p>
    
    <p>For example, at some institutions, even measured critiques of GAI are viewed as misaligned with their forward-looking visions, creating an environment where scholars may feel pressured to conform to a predominantly positive narrative. Almost as soon as GAI was released and became a topic of discussion, we quickly saw a spate of opinions, accompanied by the wisdom of pundits and some speculative analyses of what the impact on a variety of societal and organizational functions might be. These early discussions lacked grounding in robust empirical or theoretical insights, instead reflecting speculative or overly generalized narratives. In many ways, these initial reactions paralleled the reactions to Artificial Intelligence almost forty years earlier (Sheil, 1987).</p>
    
    <p>Some academic publishers quickly outlawed the use of GAI by submitting authors and other notes of caution were expressed regarding the potential negative impacts. However, as the technology evolved, so in parallel did the restrictions on academic use, most of which were just as quickly retracted and replaced with more nuanced advisories. Academic institutions, journal publishers, and universities started to promulgate guidelines, essentially legitimizing GAI application, yet also unleashing peer and institutional pressure to take advantage of this new opportunity.</p>
    
    <p>In parallel to these academic perspectives, business organizations have expressed both enthusiasm for the technology and concerns about such issues as data protection, truth, trust, and errors, as well as how to train people to use GAI correctly. Today we see that AI-themed programmes and research centres are being created in profusion. This proliferation is worrisome not because of the exploration of GAI itself, but because it often lacks critical engagement with the potential harms and adverse consequences.</p>
    
    <p>At the ISJ, we have already seen both submissions and reviews where GAI appears to have played a role not so far from either co-author or some form of assistant. In response, we have published cautionary editorials (Davison et al., 2023, 2024). When it comes to AI-themed research submissions, our sense is that we are at the stage of the trickle before the deluge. Given the normative process of empirical (qualitative or quantitative) research, it is not surprising that few such AI-themed articles (e.g., Susarla et al., 2023; Grover, 2024) have been published. However, in a pre-GAI special issue (Mikalef et al., 2022), a more critical tone was adopted with an explicit focus on the dark side of AI.</p>
    
    <p>At the ISJ, the vast majority of GAI-themed submissions to date tend to emphasise the novelty of application area yet actually have little to do with IS and fail to engage with its broader sociotechnical axis. This reflects an ongoing challenge for IS scholars: how to meaningfully situate GAI research within the discipline’s core concerns. Nevertheless, this also presents an opportunity for IS researchers to engage critically with GAI through theoretical and methodological innovation and empirical rigor. What we also find to be absent from much of the GAI-related work done so far is either a more critical stance or attempts to engage in rigorous and novel theoretical development on the impacts of GAI.</p>
    
    <p>This is troubling because of the risks that GAI poses to individuals, organizations, society more broadly, and the natural environment. In fact, poorly vetted applications of GAI run the risk of such negative outcomes as violating privacy, facilitating research misconduct, insulting customers, and discriminating unfairly against specific groups. Given this backdrop, we argue that the time is now ripe for researchers to critically investigate the diverse impacts of GAI. Analyzing these impacts through a sociotechnical lens is essential to bridge the gap between technological advancements and their broader implications.</p>
    
    <p>We can expect that a wide variety of impacts may be experienced globally, some of which will be legal in one jurisdiction even as they are illegal elsewhere; this heightens concerns about widening digital and AI-related divides. To explain these phenomena and anticipate their future trajectories, researchers must employ appropriate theoretical frameworks and remain open to innovative forms of theorizing. GAI&#39;s emergence necessitates both the adaptation of existing theories and the development of new theoretical arguments that reflect its distinctive characteristics, such as its effects on human agency and the contextual nuances of its applications.</p>
    
    <p>We encourage the application of grounded research, given that GAI is still an emerging phenomenon. For example, theories of disruption, given the undeniably disruptive nature of GAI, may offer more fruitful opportunities for theoretical innovation, while critical design approaches rooted in theories of emancipation could illuminate issues of AI oppression. A robust theoretical foundation that explores the ‘dark side’ of GAI is indispensable for advancing sociotechnical research and addressing its complex, often adverse, societal impacts.</p>
    
    <p>In a positive sense, the research that we aim to publish in this special issue should contribute to our understanding of the potential negative impacts of GAI, with the hope that we can also mitigate them. In-depth ethnographic fieldwork, critical case studies, and grounded theory can help reveal and address the otherwise hidden aspects of GAI in practice. Action Researchers may go a step further to propose and even enact those mitigation strategies in particular contexts, thus subjecting their theoretical ideas to empirical tests.</p>
    
    <p>For this special issue, we specifically solicit research that draws on primary data. Primary data allows for a deeper understanding of GAI’s real-world impact and enables researchers to engage directly with stakeholders, such as individuals and organizations affected by GAI. We aim to foster research that is grounded in real-world experiences and produces theoretically innovative, methodologically rigorous work that can truly advance our understanding of GAI&#39;s sociotechnical consequences. We expect that authors will make a direct contribution to knowledge by developing a new theory or theorisations that acknowledge the unique characteristics of GAI. We welcome interdisciplinary work. We also welcome action research and design science studies if they empirically demonstrate how the negative impacts of GAI can be mitigated, and in addition develop theory.</p>
    
    <p>For this special issue, we do not accept the submission of stand-alone reviews of the technology, opinion papers and purely conceptual papers. Submissions to this special issue must align closely with the sociotechnical axis central to IS research. Specifically, we seek studies that explore the interplay between human, technological, environmental and organizational dimensions of GAI in real-world contexts. The range of topics and contexts that may be suitable is clearly extensive, and thus we only provide a partial list below. As we indicate above, we are particularly interested in the dark side of GAI.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Human - GAI Relationships and Collaboration (e.g., Anthropomorphism in AI and human identity; Dehumanized interactions; Relationships with robots or chatbots; Power dynamics in human - AI collaboration and hegemonic interactions)</li>
        
        <li>Human Agency, Creativity, and Cognition (e.g., Erosion of human agency and GAI dependency; Challenges to human creativity in the era of AI - driven pattern generation; Mediocrity as a new norm, and the struggle for excellence; Cognitive enhancement, deterioration, and dependence in GAI - mediated environments)</li>
        
        <li>Social Inequalities and Marginalization (e.g., Impacts on marginalized populations and inequality by design; Educational equity and impact on learning; Global and cultural distortions and digital exclusion; Data colonialism and global inequalities)</li>
        
        <li>Work and Organizational Shifts (e.g., Transformation, decline and disappearance of professions; Deskilling and disempowering of individuals; Disruptions to work, routines, and shifts in organizational dynamics)</li>
        
        <li>Governance and Policy (e.g., Implications of strong or absent governance frameworks; Regulation and policy development by governments and organizations; National policies and their differences; Environmental and societal trade-offs)</li>
        
        <li>Disinformation and Trust (Development &amp; dissemination of disinformation, misinformation, and conspiracy theories; Erosion of trust in human and organizational communication)</li>
        
        <li>Fundamental Risks (e.g., Systemic risk, resilience, and dependencies in AI - enhanced infrastructure; Vulnerabilities and data poisoning; Misuse of intellectual property; Warfare automation)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>June 30, 2025: Deadline for extended abstract submissions for early feedback</li>
        
        <li>December 31, 2025: Full paper submission deadline</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Angsana Techatassanasoontorn</strong>, AUT University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carla Bonina</strong>, University of Surrey</li>
        
        <li><strong>Christoph Breidbach</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dimitra Petrakaki</strong>, University of Sussex</li>
        
        <li><strong>Efpraxia Zamani</strong>, Durham University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gilbert Fridgen</strong>, University of Luxembourg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hameed Chughtai</strong>, University of Lancaster</li>
        
        <li><strong>Han-fen Hu</strong>, University of Nevada Las Vegas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Harminder Singh</strong>, AUT University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Johan Sæbo</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Luiz Joia</strong>, Getulio Vargas Foundation</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Martin Adam</strong>, University of Göttingen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maximilian Schreieck</strong>, University of Innsbruck</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mike Lee</strong>, University of Nevada Las Vegas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mira Slavova</strong>, Warwick Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mylene Struijk</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nancy Deng</strong>, California State University Dominguez Hills</li>
        
        <li><strong>Petros Chamakiotis</strong>, ESCP</li>
        
        <li><strong>Petter Nielsen</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Phil Zhou</strong>, Tongji University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pierre-Emmanuel Arduin</strong>, Paris Dauphine University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sven Laumer</strong>, Friedrich-Alexander University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tommy Chan</strong>, University of Manchester</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Journal (ISJ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Contemporary Innovation in Information Infrastructures]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-contemporary-innovation-in-information-infrastructures</link>
            <guid>jais-contemporary-innovation-in-information-infrastructures</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 12:55:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Margunn Aanestad</strong>, University of Oslo</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ahmed Abbasi</strong>, University of Notre Dame</p>
        
        <p><strong>Dubravka Cecez-Kecmanovic</strong>, UNSW Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Robert Gregory</strong>, University of Miami</p>
        
        <p><strong>Kalle Lyytinen</strong>, Case Western Reserve University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Annalisa Pelizza</strong>, University of Bologna</p>
        
        <p><strong>Joan Rodon</strong>, Esade Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Robin Williams</strong>, University of Edinburgh</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This call for a special issue focuses on contemporary innovation in information infrastructures, especially the emergence of new technological capabilities such as block-chain, big data, Artificial Intelligence (AI), and Internet of Things (IoT) technologies, and consequent emerging new (inter)organizational forms and processes encompassing contemporary infrastructuring.</p>
    
    <p>The special issue builds on and expands the earlier stream of studies on information infrastructures to garner a deeper understanding of the new, emerging forms of digitally enabled infrastructural formations and their design, growth patterns, and local, organizational, societal and institutional uses and impacts.</p>
    
    <p>We encourage multi-level analyses, studies of infrastructures in heterogeneous contexts, and analyses that give due consideration to both organizational and societal level relevance and significance, including double-edged effects that have often been missed in previous analyses of infrastructural formations. These effects include changes in social justice, climate change, immigration, and personal rights.</p>
    
    <p>We invite original papers that engage with, scrutinize and highlight contemporary developments in a world composed of increasingly pervasive and rapidly changing information infrastructures and their component systems integrated into daily routines and widely shared services provided across time and space.</p>
    
    <p>The expected contributions are not confined to any particular &#39;school&#39; or position of infrastructure studies and can take any feasible theoretical and methodological stance towards the subject matter. Our scope is highly inclusive: we wish to recruit all scholarly work showing an interest in building upon, extending, or modifying current streams of work focused on information infrastructures.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Infrastructuring of Platforms, Platformisation of Infrastructures: Studies of architectural strategies related to digital platforms and governance in data-intensive ecosystems.</li>
        
        <li>Governance of/by Information Infrastructures: Understanding the relationship between information infrastructures and governance in various institutions.</li>
        
        <li>Societal Challenges addressed through Information Infrastructures: Investigating how infrastructures facilitate coordination to tackle societal grand challenges such as climate or health.</li>
        
        <li>Approaches to Data &amp; AI Informed by Information Infrastructure Perspectives: Examining AI as an infrastructural assemblage and its implications for society.</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical Frames and Methodologies Salient to Infrastructure Studies: Debating theoretical and methodological concerns in infrastructure studies.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Invalid DateTime: Publication of the special issue</li>
        
        <li>July 30, 2025: Initial submissions</li>
        
        <li>November 30, 2025: 1st Round Decision on Submission</li>
        
        <li>May 30, 2026: Revised submission</li>
        
        <li>September 30, 2026: 2nd Round Decision</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2027: Revised Submission</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2027: Final decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Roberta Bernardi</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Claudio Coletta</strong>, University of Bologna</li>
        
        <li><strong>Morgan Currie</strong>, University of Edinburgh</li>
        
        <li><strong>Miria Grisot</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ole Hanseth</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ole Hendfridsson</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ola Michalec</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Eric Monteiro</strong>, Norwegian University of Science and Technology NTNU</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marko Niemimaa</strong>, University of Agder</li>
        
        <li><strong>David Ribes</strong>, University of Washington</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alain Sandoz</strong>, Université de Neuchâtel</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pankaj Setia</strong>, Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad</li>
        
        <li><strong>Franz Strich</strong>, Deakin University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maha Shaikh</strong>, Esade Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Antti Silvasti</strong>, LUT University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carsten Sorensen</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Léa Stiefel</strong>, University of Lausanne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stefan Tams</strong>, HEC Montréal</li>
        
        <li><strong>David Tilson</strong>, Rochester Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jonathan Wareham</strong>, Esade Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Will Venters</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Adrian Yeow Yong Kwang</strong>, Singapore University of Social Sciences</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aljona Zorina</strong>, IESEG School of Management</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Platform Partnerships]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jsis-platform-partnerships</link>
            <guid>jsis-platform-partnerships</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2024 12:48:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Thomas Huber</strong>, ESSEC Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Maximilian Schreieck</strong>, University of Innsbruck</p>
        
        <p><strong>Andreas Hein</strong>, University of St Gallen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ilan Oshri</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Over the last years platform partnerships between independent third-party developers (complementors) and providers of software platforms (platform owners) have become the prevailing model for developing and delivering software products and services. Platforms are strategic in enabling value co-creation through boundary resources—such as software development kits (SDKs) and application programming interfaces (APIs)—which provide complementors with the tools needed to seamlessly integrate their offerings into the core platform infrastructure.</p>
    
    <p>Novel and creative uses of technologies such as Artificial Intelligence (AI), Internet of Things (IoT), low-code/no-code platforms, and distributed ledger technologies (DLT) like blockchain are redefining how organizations interact, collaborate, and compete. AI and IoT enable real-time data analytics and predictive insights, allowing platforms to coordinate relationships and optimize sourcing decisions by anticipating demand, managing risks, and adjusting partnerships. IoT enhances this by providing continuous data streams from connected devices, enabling more responsive, data-driven collaborations in logistics and inventory management. Low-code/no-code platforms reduce entry barriers for participants, enabling organizations to develop solutions independently. Blockchain and smart contracts automate partnership agreements through self-executing code, reducing transaction costs and fostering trust, particularly in complex, cross-border environments.</p>
    
    <p>Together, these technologies have strategic implications on partnerships in platform ecosystems, potentially reshaping established practices in value co-creation and appropriation, and sourcing arrangements. While they offer complementors opportunities to innovate and gain leverage, they also equip platform owners with new tools to reinforce their dominance. Whether these new tools will benefit complementors or increase platform owners&#39; control remains an open question. For example, as decentralized, real-time decision-making becomes more common, will these technologies empower complementors to innovate and operate autonomously, or will they reinforce existing power imbalances, allowing platform owners to strengthen centralized control and dictate terms of value appropriation and collaboration?</p>
    
    <p>As dominant platform owners like Apple, Google, Amazon, and Microsoft in Western markets, and Alibaba, Tencent, and Baidu in China, continue to control key sectors of consumer and business markets, complementors face growing challenges in navigating the advantages of platform participation against the risks of dependency and lock-in, both undermining complementor autonomy. Meanwhile, the evolving regulatory landscape, such as the European Union’s (EU) Digital Markets Act, seeks to address these power imbalances by imposing restrictions on platform gatekeepers that reshape partner strategies and value co-creation.</p>
    
    <p>Indeed, platform partnerships are undergoing significant strategic transformations. Advancements in technologies such as AI, IoT, and blockchain, along with shifts in political and regulatory environments, are influencing how partnerships within platform ecosystems evolve. In this rapidly changing landscape, critical questions arise about the future dynamics of partnerships in platform ecosystems. How will the balance between value co-creation and value appropriation shift as AI, DLT, and IoT become more integrated into platform partnerships? Will these technologies empower complementors to innovate and capture a fair share of the value they create, or will they enable platform owners to centralize control, deepening dependencies and shifting value appropriation in their favor? And as platform ecosystems often nurture sourcing relationships, how and in what ways sourcing relationships between a platform owner and complementors affect the platform ecosystem? Ultimately, how can both platform owners and complementors strategically navigate these changes to ensure mutual benefit in an increasingly complex ecosystem?</p>
    
    <p>This call for papers invites research that explores how these strategic shifts are reshaping platform partnerships, including changes in the strategies and business models of platform owners and complementors, and the governance of these partnerships and ecosystems. We welcome empirical, conceptual, design, and simulation research. Any methodologies and theoretical perspectives are encouraged as long as they contribute to the theoretical understanding of platform partnerships, along with practical insights.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>The role of AI/machine learning and predictive analytics in managing platform partnerships.</li>
        
        <li>The impact of AI platforms&#39; unique characteristics, such as learning abilities and non-deterministic behaviors, on platform partnerships.</li>
        
        <li>The role of IoT in real-time coordination and dynamic management of platform partnerships.</li>
        
        <li>Effects of distributed ledger technologies on platform partnerships.</li>
        
        <li>Impact of low-code/no-code platforms on the role of complementors within these platforms.</li>
        
        <li>Strategies for complementors to manage power asymmetries within platform partnerships.</li>
        
        <li>The role of regulatory interventions in addressing the increasing power of platform owners.</li>
        
        <li>Strategies for complementors and platform owners to adapt to regulatory changes, such as new laws and antitrust decisions.</li>
        
        <li>Impact of emerging technologies on managing tensions in platform governance, such as control versus autonomy.</li>
        
        <li>The role of AI, real-time analytics, and DLTs in shaping sourcing strategies, decisions, and governance.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>December 5, 2024: Online information session</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2024: Informal meet the SI Editors, SIG digital sourcing, platforms and ecosystems (DSPE) Pre-ICIS workshop</li>
        
        <li>August 14, 2025: Informal meet the SE editors, SIG DSPE track - AMCIS 2025</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2025: Full paper submission</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2025: First round decisions</li>
        
        <li>March 15, 2026: Deadline to submit revised paper</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2026: Second round decisions</li>
        
        <li>September 1, 2026: Deadline to submit revised paper</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2026: Final decisions</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>The Journal of Strategic Information Systems (JSIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Future of Information Systems in the Enterprise]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-the-future-of-information-systems-in-the-enterprise</link>
            <guid>jit-the-future-of-information-systems-in-the-enterprise</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 03:00:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Robert Winter</strong>, University of St. Gallen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Karlheinz Kautz</strong>, RMIT University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Sabherval</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Leona Chandra Kruse</strong>, University of Agder</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The use of information systems in the enterprise is the backbone of digital transformation and digital business, acting as the binding force between technological, managerial, and organizational innovations. The design and use of information systems in the enterprise evolve alongside technological advancements, shifting managerial strategies, and changing organisational forms and needs (Kotusev, 2019).</p>
    
    <p>&quot;Enterprise information systems&quot; has been the key term for information systems that transcend narrow functions, processes, products, markets, or concerns (e.g., ERP, SCM, CRM) and integrate these elements, supporting end-to- end, creating synergy, and ensuring coherence in the enterprise context (Cao et al., 2022; Robey et al., 2002).</p>
    
    <p>Given the rapid pace of change and advancements in emerging technologies (e.g., artificial intelligence, edge computing), alternative approaches to information systems used in enterprises (e.g., shadow IT, cloud/as-a-service), and structures beyond single enterprises (e.g., platforms, ecosystems), this special issue is focused on the future of information systems in the enterprise context and deliberately uses this broader term to emphasise our interest in both conventional enterprise information systems and alternative IS/IT solutions used for similar enterprise-level issues.</p>
    
    <p>Information systems in the enterprise have undergone fundamental paradigm shifts in the past four decades. First, the integration scope of such systems has expanded to include customer activities, supply chains, and business ecosystems (Ignatiadis &amp; Nandhakumar, 2007; Sambhara et al., 2022). Second, technological innovations have fundamentally changed the characteristics and positioning of information systems in the enterprise. These innovations include, among others, transitioning from on-premises to cloud-based operations, shifting from traditional license to as-a-service models, incorporating analytic and execution functionalities, integrating with or evolving into digital platforms, adopting edge computing, and adding artificial intelligence functionalities (Dong et al., 2009; Flak et al., 2022). These developments set the stage for future challenges, such as how enterprises will further enhance agility and innovation through emerging technologies.</p>
    
    <p>Third, managerial innovations require greater flexibility from information systems in the enterprise. These include, among others, the rise of digital platforms and business ecosystems, end-to-end process integration, agile business organization, and continuous development and integration (Aral et al., 2024). Fourth, new types of enterprise systems and other information systems in the enterprise enhance value creation for old and new stakeholders, justifying significant investment while necessitating more sophisticated approaches for their design, development, governance, and operations (see further, Nah et al., 2001; Scott &amp; Vessey, 2002; Dong et al., 2009; Pang et al., 2014; Haki et al., 2020; Mikalef et al., 2020; Flak et al., 2022).</p>
    
    <p>The future of information systems in the enterprise is complex. IS practice must adapt to technological, managerial, and organizational innovations while IS research may need to integrate insights from work on enterprise systems, enterprise architecture, as well as IS governance, digital transformation, IS sourcing, and digital platforms. This special issue aims to address these challenges by inviting disciplinary and interdisciplinary submissions that provide important insights on the direction and future of information systems in the enterprise. Specifically, &quot;The Future of Information Systems in the Enterprise&quot; special issue seeks to generate new knowledge that addresses key practical or theoretical challenges.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Alternatives to traditional enterprise information systems such as digital platforms, shadow IT, no-code/low-code, and how the challenges they bring for coherent management, and our understanding of enterprise-level systems</li>
        
        <li>Designing future information systems in the enterprise with concerns for both business and societal values</li>
        
        <li>Exploring how technological or organizational innovations in the enterprise / enterprise-level context challenge and extend existing knowledge and theory</li>
        
        <li>Extending and adapting the body of knowledge to encompass specific contexts, such as strategies, industries, ecosystems, or specific organizational configurations</li>
        
        <li>Horizontal (cross-unit) and vertical (technology-to-business) integration through information systems in the enterprise</li>
        
        <li>Specific integration challenges of technology, organization, and humans in the enterprise / enterprise-level context</li>
        
        <li>Intersection of artificial intelligence and other emerging technologies in information systems in the enterprise</li>
        
        <li>Intersection/relation of enterprise and platform/ecosystem-level systems and technologies, and the corresponding challenges such as for organizational strategy</li>
        
        <li>Understanding and harnessing the complexity of enterprise computing</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 1, 2024: Extended abstract submissions via email to the corresponding special issue editor for early feedback and invitation to the special issue paper development workshop.</li>
        
        <li>November 15, 2024: Results are announced.</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2024: Special issue paper development workshop at ICIS 2024.</li>
        
        <li>April 1, 2025: First-round submissions.</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2025: First-round decisions.</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2025: Second-round submissions.</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2026: Second-round decisions (Papers are either acceptable with minor changes or rejected).</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2026: Final versions (Final decisions and online publication soon afterwards).</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Pär Ågerfalk</strong>, Uppsala University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rainer Alt</strong>, University of Leipzig</li>
        
        <li><strong>Vanessa Cooper</strong>, RMIT University Melbourne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rob Gleasure</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kazem Haki</strong>, HES Geneva</li>
        
        <li><strong>Taha Havakhor</strong>, McGill University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hartmut Hoehle</strong>, University of Mannheim</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sherah Kurnia</strong>, University of Melbourne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, UNSW</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jan Mendling</strong>, Humboldt-Universität</li>
        
        <li><strong>Annette Mills</strong>, University of Canterbury</li>
        
        <li><strong>Petter Nielsen</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ralf Plattfaut</strong>, University Duisburg-Essen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Matti Rossi</strong>, Aalto University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Helana Scheepers</strong>, Swinburne University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Priya Seetharaman</strong>, Indian Institute of Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pankaj Setia</strong>, Indian Institute of Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Matthias Söllner</strong>, University of Kassel</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zach Steelman</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tuure Tuunanen</strong>, University of Jyväskylä</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Artificial Intelligence-Information Assurance Nexus: The Future of Information Systems Security, Privacy, and Quality]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/misq-ai-ia-nexus</link>
            <guid>misq-ai-ia-nexus</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 05:11:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Rui Chen</strong>, Iowa State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Juan Feng</strong>, Tsinghua University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Miguel Godinho de Matos</strong>, Católica Lisbon School of Business &amp; Economics</p>
        
        <p><strong>Carol Hsu</strong>, University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>H. Raghav Rao</strong>, University of Texas at San Antonio</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Digital threats continue to impede information assurance. Many issues in information assurance have arisen in the last decade or two, including risk management, information quality, intellectual property, privacy protection, compliance with regulations, and continuity of operations. As a result, protecting information has become a global priority, and collaborative efforts are being made to prevent, detect, and react to threats to information quality, authenticity, integrity, confidentiality, and availability. As society steps into the age of generative AI (GenAI), fresh challenges and opportunities are arising in the realms of information security, privacy, and quality. Questions have emerged regarding the role and intended/unintended consequences of GenAI in information assurance. GenAI is believed to pose a paradox, serving as a dual-edged sword in the realm of information assurance. GenAI creates new content, whereas traditional AI mostly makes predictions and classifications based on existing datasets. GenAI is designed to reason and operate independently across various domains, whereas traditional AI focuses on narrow tasks (e.g., playing chess and translating languages by following specific rules). In addition, GenAI works with multiple data modalities (e.g., text, images, and videos), whereas traditional AI primarily functions in a single mode of data. These new capabilities of GenAI open new possibilities for its applications in a wide range of areas.</p>
    
    <p>The emergence of GenAI is poised to exert a profound impact on assurance. On the one hand, GenAI has been recognized for its ability to bolster information assurance. On the other hand, GenAI heightens the potency of existing threats, allows the fabrication of false information, fuels intellectual property theft, and poses challenges to governance and compliance.</p>
    
    <p>Another source of threats to information assurance stems from attacks that are designed to target the way GenAI systems are trained and expected to be used. Many of these attacks can be mitigated by explicitly integrating information assurance considerations when designing GenAI systems. Cisco found that 92% of organizations see GenAI as fundamentally different, requiring new techniques to manage data and risks. The relationship between GenAI and information assurance is depicted below. Numerous new opportunities exist for information systems (IS) scholars to study information assurance issues within the context of GenAI, as traditional approaches may not work. This special issue seeks research that goes beyond simple applications of existing theories and methods from the cybersecurity literature in IS. We invite studies that explore the unique information assurance challenges in the realm of GenAI, calling for the development and application of new theories or methods. By focusing on important research questions, this special issue will generate answers to address significant national and global research fronts.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>What factors influence individuals’ security and privacy behavior in the presence of GenAI tools?</li>
        
        <li>How can we predict, analyze, and counteract the emerging threats to GenAI models?</li>
        
        <li>How can economic analysis contribute to combating information assurance threats in GenAI?</li>
        
        <li>What are the managerial strategies and their effectiveness in addressing GenAI-induced issues on data security and privacy?</li>
        
        <li>What are the key principles in attributing accountability and responsibilities for the risks in GenAI model output?</li>
        
        <li>individual behaviors</li>
        
        <li>organizational practices</li>
        
        <li>societal impacts</li>
        
        <li>risk management</li>
        
        <li>investments in assurance</li>
        
        <li>market effects</li>
        
        <li>attacker analysis</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 15, 2024: Optional introductory workshops (virtual): informational sessions.</li>
        
        <li>January 20, 2025: Two-page abstracts submission deadline.</li>
        
        <li>March 31, 2025: Feedback on abstracts.</li>
        
        <li>July 11, 2025: Paper development workshop (virtual).</li>
        
        <li>October 31, 2025: First-round paper submission.</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2026: First-round decisions.</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2026: Workshop for authors with first-round revise-and-resubmit.</li>
        
        <li>May 31, 2026: Second-round revisions due.</li>
        
        <li>August 31, 2026: Second-round decisions.</li>
        
        <li>November 30, 2026: Final revisions due.</li>
        
        <li>February 28, 2027: Final revisions.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Panagiotis Adamopoulos</strong>, Emory University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jingjing Li</strong>, University of Virginia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rodrigo Belo</strong>, Nova School of Business and Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Huigang Liang</strong>, University of Memphis</li>
        
        <li><strong>Indranil Bose</strong>, NEOMA</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Maedche</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lemuria Carter</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ning Nan</strong>, University of British Columbia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Christy Cheung</strong>, Hong Kong Baptist University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jella Pfeiffer</strong>, University of Stuttgart</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rahul De’</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Bangalore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dandan Qiao</strong>, National University of Singapore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Amany Elbanna</strong>, University of Sussex</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sagar Samtani</strong>, Indiana University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Uri Gal</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anastasia Sergeeva</strong>, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam</li>
        
        <li><strong>Weiyin Hong</strong>, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maha Shaikh</strong>, ESADE Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nina Huang</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Paolo Spagnoletti</strong>, Luiss Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hartmut Höhle</strong>, University of Mannheim</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rohit Valecha</strong>, University of Texas at San Antonio</li>
        
        <li><strong>Allen Johnston</strong>, University of Alabama</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jing Wang</strong>, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Arpan Kar</strong>, Indian Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jingguo Wang</strong>, University of Texas at Arlington</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juhee Kwon</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hong Xu</strong>, Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Atanu Lahiri</strong>, University of Texas at Dallas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Heng Xu</strong>, University of Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alvin Leung</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Niam Yaraghi</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ting Li</strong>, Erasmus University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Cathy Liu Yang</strong>, HEC Paris</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yingjie Zhang</strong>, Peking University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>MIS Quarterly (MISQ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Designing for Digital Futures: Celebrating the Career and Intellectual Legacy of Professor Richard Boland Jr.]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/io-designing-for-digital-futures-celebrating-the-career-and-intellectual-legacy-of-professor-richard-boland-jr</link>
            <guid>io-designing-for-digital-futures-celebrating-the-career-and-intellectual-legacy-of-professor-richard-boland-jr</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 12:37:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Youngjin Yoo</strong>, Case Western Reserve University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Natalia N Levina</strong>, New York University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>_Information &amp; Organization_ invites submissions for a special issue celebrating the career and intellectual legacy of the journal’s founding editor, Professor Richard Boland Jr., on the occasion of his retirement.</p>
    
    <p>Throughout his distinguished career, Professor Boland is known for his innovative and unconventional approach to understanding the role of technology in organizations and society. He challenged traditional paradigms on technology and management, and urged scholars to embrace a more expansive, humanistic, and design-oriented perspective on information systems. Among other things, he is best known for his groundbreaking work on the role of design as a fundamental way of thinking about the future, contrasting design with traditional decision-making paradigms.</p>
    
    <p>This special issue seeks to honor Professor Boland’s legacy by inspiring submissions that not only build upon his seminal contributions but also push the boundaries of our understanding of technology’s role in shaping the future. Among others, we welcome especially forward-looking contributions that address the profound impact of emerging technologies, such as large language models, blockchain, and augmented reality, across various sectors, including healthcare, finance, manufacturing, sustainability, and education.</p>
    
    <p>In the spirit of Professor Boland’s commitment to active scholarship, we encourage submissions that position IS research as a world-shaping force, rather than merely a reflective lens on recent history. We seek contributions that embody Professor Boland’s spirit of critical inquiry, imaginative exploration, and commitment to human-centeredness. We encourage submissions that challenge dominant techno-centric narratives, propose alternative visions for the future of technology and organization, and engage with the ethical, philosophical, and societal implications of emerging technologies. We invite conceptual and empirical submissions that explore topics including, but not limited to:</p>
    
    <p>Envisioning alternative futures for technology and organization through speculative design and critical storytelling</p>
    
    <p>Exploring the role of technology in fostering human creativity, collaboration, and experiential learning in organizations</p>
    
    <p>Designing technologies that prioritize human autonomy, dignity, and well-being in the face of increasing automation and algorithmic decision-making</p>
    
    <p>Investigating the potential of participatory and co-design methodologies to democratize technology development and promote inclusive innovation</p>
    
    <p>Reimagining the relationship between technology, work, and leisure in the post-pandemic era</p>
    
    <p>Examining the implications of emerging technologies for organizational power dynamics, surveillance, and resistance</p>
    
    <p>Envisioning new forms of technological citizenship and digital activism in the age of platformization and datafication</p>
    
    <p>Exploring the role of technology in enabling sustainable, equitable, and resilient organizations and communities</p>
    
    <p>Proposing new methodological approaches and theoretical frameworks for studying the future of technology and organization, drawing inspiration from fields such as design, art, literature, and philosophy</p>
    
    <p>We welcome original research papers, theory development, conceptual papers, empirical studies, essays, and other innovative formats. In the spirit of Professor Boland’s openness to new ideas and his generosity towards junior scholars, we particularly encourage submissions from early-career researchers and doctoral students.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Challenge Techno-Centric Narratives: We seek papers that move beyond solution-oriented thinking, instead critically examining the assumptions and values embedded in emerging technologies (such as large language models, blockchain, and augmented reality).</li>
        
        <li>Center Human Values and Experiences: How can technology prioritize well-being, autonomy, and creativity? We encourage investigations into human-centered design approaches in the face of automation and algorithmic decision-making.</li>
        
        <li>Explore the Transformative Potential of Design: We invite speculative and participatory design methodologies to envision radically different futures where technology serves humanity, society, and the planet.</li>
        
        <li>Study how Diverse Perspectives Enable Innovation: How are perspective making and perspective taking combined in technological and technology-enabled innovation? How has digitization through online communities, crowdsourcing, and generative AI tools transformed innovation processes?</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>April 15, 2025: First-round submission due</li>
        
        <li>July 31, 2025: First-round decision expected</li>
        
        <li>December 31, 2025: Second-round submission due</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2026: Final decision due expected</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Ulrike Schultze</strong>, University of Groningen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michel Avital</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nick Berente</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aron Lindberg</strong>, Steven Institute of Technology</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information and Organization (IO)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Addressing Refugees and Migration Issues through Critical Information Systems Research]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isj-addressing-refugees-and-migration-issues-through-critical-information-systems</link>
            <guid>isj-addressing-refugees-and-migration-issues-through-critical-information-systems</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 10:34:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Safa’a AbuJarour</strong>, An-Najah National University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Hameed Chughtai</strong>, Lancaster University Management School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yingqin Zheng</strong>, University of Essex</p>
        
    
    
    <p>United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) reports that there are approximately 110 million forcibly displaced people worldwide, as of mid-2023, because of persecution, conflict, war, violence, human rights violations, or events seriously disturbing public order. These include 36.4 million refugees and 62.5 million internally displaced people (IDP), asylum seekers, and several other people in need of international protection. There is a strong history of research highlighting the issues faced by refugees, ranging from accounts of violence in the developing world, exploring the gendered experience of refugees, questioning racist thinking about immigration, case studies of asylum seekers, and philosophical inquiry into the fair treatment of refugees. The global refugee and forced migration crisis and the persistent challenges faced by these vulnerable communities call for an urgent need for innovative solutions that foster social inclusion and empower these populations.</p>
    
    <p>In our field, information systems (IS) researchers have been acutely aware of the refugee and migrant crises. Researchers have examined the critical issues related to social inclusion of refugees, social inclusion and activation of refugee agency, information and communication technology (ICT) enabled refugee integration, refugees and pedagogy, digitization and refugee settlement, refugee women and information-precarity, and migrant identity. Nonetheless, recent research in refugee studies has shown that critical areas at the intersection of technology, refugees, and broader migration crises have remained underexamined, for example, social media and device vetting, digitally mediated lived experiences of minority refugees, refugees and a sense of uncertainty in the digital age, refugee aid and digital capitalism, and networked refugees.</p>
    
    <p>We observe that despite some progress in our field, much remains underexplored in addressing these pressing issues, underscoring the need for rigorous research. This special issue aims to explore how IS research could contribute to illuminating the refugee crises and alleviating the deterioration of refugee and migrant social circumstances. These sensitive topics are situated within the broader debate on digital inclusion and empowerment and the discussions related to inequality and demarginalization and decolonization in our field.</p>
    
    <p>Exploring the critical research questions surrounding IS and migrant/refugee populations is essential for developing comprehensive and ‘good’ IS solutions and making the world a better place for all of us. We encourage submissions from diverse researchers with multidisciplinary perspectives, including experts in IS, social sciences, public policy, humanitarian studies, and other relevant fields. Such interdisciplinary collaborations will contribute to a holistic understanding of the problems and foster innovative solutions. We seek submissions that focus on real-world issues at the intersection of refugees and migrant crises and technology.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Critical analyses of the interrelated themes of identity, refugeeness, and belonging.</li>
        
        <li>Exploring the ethics of (forced) migration.</li>
        
        <li>Analysing the politics of responsibility and the integration of refugees and migrants in digital contexts.</li>
        
        <li>Technology, racial marginalization and refugees experience.</li>
        
        <li>Digital biopolitics, identities, and datafication of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Online activism and digital social movements in the context of refugees or migrants.</li>
        
        <li>Agency, resistance and coping mechanisms of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Examining the issues at the intersections of gender, technology, and migrants/refugees (including queering migration and issues of gender-based violence).</li>
        
        <li>Digitally-entangled lived experiences of minorities among refugee populations.</li>
        
        <li>Datafication of borders and algorithmic management of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Decolonial justice and /for migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Digital justice and human rights issues affecting migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Digital and data surveillance and control on migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Issues related to power and exploitation of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Critical narratives of displacement.</li>
        
        <li>Digital accounts and narratives of refugee experience.</li>
        
        <li>Technology and the political philosophy of migration and refuge.</li>
        
        <li>Novel theoretical lenses to study migration and refugee issues such as decolonial theory, spatial and temporal perspectives, Indigenous viewpoints, critical race theory, and feminist approaches.</li>
        
        <li>Novel methodological approaches to examine refugee issues such as visual ethnography, visual research, and digitally mediated bodily experiences.</li>
        
        <li>Application of novel technologies such as Blockchain and AI.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 30, 2024: Submission of extended abstract (optional)</li>
        
        <li>March 30, 2025: Submission of manuscript</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Petros Chamakiotis</strong>, ESCP Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Andrea Jimenez</strong>, University of Sheffield</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shirin Madon</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, University of New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Priyanka Panday</strong>, Kings College London</li>
        
        <li><strong>Israr Qureshi</strong>, Australian National University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maximilian Schreieck</strong>, University of Innsbruck</li>
        
        <li><strong>Devinder Thapa</strong>, University of Agder</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ranjan Vaidya</strong>, Auckland University of Technology</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Journal (ISJ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fostering the Design and Governance of the Metaverse]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jmis-fostering-the-design-and-governance-of-the-metaverse</link>
            <guid>jmis-fostering-the-design-and-governance-of-the-metaverse</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 12:25:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Paul Benjamin Lowry</strong>, Virginia Tech</p>
        
        <p><strong>Waifong Boh</strong>, Nanyang Technological University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Stacie Petter</strong>, Wake Forest University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jan Marco Leimeister</strong>, University of St. Gallen and University of Kassel</p>
        
    
    
    <p>JMIS, a top-tier scholarly journal, invites the best papers addressing the components of the potential emergence of the Metaverse as a complement to and a potential replacement for the current Web. The Metaverse is envisioned as a collection of technologies and initiatives intended to create a next-generation Internet (Web3) that is highly immersive, persistent, in 3D, and based on the latest developments in extended reality (XR)—an umbrella term for virtual reality (VR), mixed reality (MR), and augmented reality (AR)—as supplemented by artificial intelligence (AI), cloud computing, quantum computing, and other supporting technologies.</p>
    
    <p>Given the compelling and disruptive potential for the Metaverse to generate the Web3, several of the world’s leading technology companies are investing tens of billions of dollars on related software and hardware to foster this market, including Meta (famously renamed from “Facebook” as an all-in bet on the Metaverse), Microsoft, Snapchat, Amazon, NVIDIA, Epic Games, Apple, among others. This is an opportune time for researchers to examine what can be learned from the past failed efforts of AR/VR platforms such as Second Life and over-hyped failed AR technologies like Google Glass, and to examine the many more successes that are occurring, perhaps more quietly, with XR (i.e., VR, MR, AR) in education, manufacturing, gaming, branding, healthcare, retailing, logistics, aerospace and defense, architecture, advertising, and athletics.</p>
    
    <p>It is these successes and disruptive business models that are likely to form what will be known as the Metaverse. However, this is no minor feat, just as the Internet as we know it took decades to develop. To create a truly persistent 3D, virtual, and immersive Metaverse, there will need to be further advances in supporting hardware (goggles, headsets, sensors), and an exponential increase in computing power, storage, and memory. If the Metaverse is to succeed it must be based on making things better for people than the status quo, and thus must foster innovative business models that are profitable.</p>
    
    <p>This is the time for scientists to work with policy makers, companies, and not-for-profit organizations to break the current social media models and envision a Metaverse that can best serve collective global needs. Accordingly, we are pleased to announce a Special Issue (SI) on this subject at JMIS. Importantly, information systems (IS) researchers have long contributed to the foundational research that can serve as building blocks for the Metaverse, including but not limited to XR (i.e., VR, AR, MR), avatars, agents, gamification, and gaming. Meanwhile, IS researchers are presently leading key research on the Metaverse itself.</p>
    
    <p>Our strong preference is for contributions of original and rigorous theory-guided behavioral or empirical data around information systems artifacts that inform design, practice, research, and the products and foundations of theory of meaningful aspects of the Metaverse. We seek any methodological approaches that are legitimate and rigorous, and that can shed light on important phenomena related to the Metaverse. However, we are not seeking review papers or those that focus on discussions of further research alone.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Stages leading to the Metaverse: understanding the process and intermediate stages</li>
        
        <li>Applications of the Metaverse (i.e., meta-apps): serious applications driving innovation and implications</li>
        
        <li>Governance of the Metaverse (i.e., meta-governance): identity, ownership, accountability, and standards</li>
        
        <li>Challenges to security and privacy on the Metaverse (i.e., meta-cybersecurity): trust, cybercrime, and implications</li>
        
        <li>Dark unintended consequences of the Metaverse (i.e., meta-deviance): preventing deviant behaviors</li>
        
        <li>Designing immersive, interactive, and persistent 3D Metaverse applications (i.e., meta-interactivity): rethinking interactivity and immersion</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Invalid DateTime: Special issue publication</li>
        
        <li>June 30, 2023: First round submissions due date</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2023: First round decisions provided by</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2024: Second round submissions due date</li>
        
        <li>March 15, 2024: Second round decisions provided by</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2024: Third round submissions due date</li>
        
        <li>July 30, 2024: Final decisions on papers provided by</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Idris Adjerid</strong>, Virginia Tech</li>
        
        <li><strong>Christy Cheung</strong>, Hong Kong Baptist University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ersin Dincelli</strong>, University of Colorado Denver</li>
        
        <li><strong>James Gaskin</strong>, Brigham Young University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shuk Ying Ho</strong>, Australian National University</li>
        
        <li><strong>J. J. Hsieh</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tabitha James</strong>, Virginia Tech</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zhenhui Jiang</strong>, University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Allen Johnston</strong>, University of Alabama</li>
        
        <li><strong>Weiling Ke</strong>, Southern University of Science and Technology, China</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ajay Kumar</strong>, EMLYON Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>De Liu</strong>, University of Minnesota</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xin Luo</strong>, University of New Mexico</li>
        
        <li><strong>Greg Moody</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Fiona Nah</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Choon Ling Sia</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sebastian Schuetz</strong>, Florida International University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Isabella Seeber</strong>, Grenoble Ecole de Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mario Silic</strong>, Swiss School of Business and Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Monideepa Tarafdar</strong>, University of Massachusetts</li>
        
        <li><strong>Horst Treiblmaier</strong>, Modul University Vienna</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ofir Turel</strong>, University of Melbourne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Daniel Veit</strong>, University of Augsburg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lena Waizenegger</strong>, Auckland University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dezhi Wu</strong>, University of South Carolina</li>
        
        <li><strong>Fatemeh Mariam Zahedi</strong>, University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jun Zhang</strong>, Wuhan University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zhongyun Zhou</strong>, Tongji University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Management Information Systems (JMIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Information Technology to Foster Mental Health]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jmis-information-technology-to-foster-mental-health</link>
            <guid>jmis-information-technology-to-foster-mental-health</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 12:24:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Corey Angst</strong>, University of Notre Dame</p>
        
        <p><strong>Alan Dennis</strong>, Indiana University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Elena Karahanna</strong>, The University of Georgia</p>
        
        <p><strong>Gondy Leroy</strong>, University of Arizona</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Mental health issues such as depression, anxiety, and others are a growing epidemic facing modern society. The Mental Health America society estimated that nearly a fifth of the adult US population suffered a mental illness in 2019 - 2020 and that 94% of these individuals did not receive any treatment. Information Technology (IT) such as wearables, digital pills, cope notes, VR, and others have been proposed and used to help address the growing mental health crisis. However, the understanding of the design, development, adoption, use, and impact of such technologies for diagnosing and treating mental health illnesses remains nascent.</p>
    
    <p>Information Systems (IS) scholars are starting to study various aspects of mental health, including occupational stress, distress, and diagnosable mental health disorders. However, significant areas of opportunity remain for developing and evaluating digital technologies that could help identify or tackle anxiety disorders (e.g., generalized anxiety disorder, panic, social anxiety), mood disorders (e.g., depression, bipolar disorder), and addiction (e.g., substance abuse, chemical dependence). This Special Section seeks to expand research related to IT for mental health and spearhead an ongoing research agenda related to this subject in the IS discipline. We are specifically seeking contributions that improve our understanding of how IT could be leveraged to identify mental health conditions and improve mental health. We encourage a wide range of content, including theory, qualitative and quantitative approaches, and design science for mental health for this Special Section.</p>
    
    <p>Irrespective of the topic, the focus on how IT is being used or developed to identify mental health conditions or improve mental health should be evident (IT is a central theme of the paper). Research that examines the negative impacts of technology (e.g., antecedents to technostress) do not fit the theme. We welcome research that uses or employs various types of methods and analysis, including qualitative methods, quantitative methods, archival and observational research methods, mixed methods research, design science research, and Artificial Intelligence (AI)-enabled analytics methods, including machine learning, deep learning, text mining, and network science.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Impact of IT designed to prevent, diagnose, and treat mental health issues</li>
        
        <li>Design, development, and evaluation of new artifacts for identifying mental health conditions from social media</li>
        
        <li>Improving mental health with Metaverse-related technologies</li>
        
        <li>Internet of Medical Things (IoMT) and related sensor signal analysis-based approaches for identifying depressive behaviors</li>
        
        <li>AI systems to identify individuals in mental duress</li>
        
        <li>AI systems to recommend mental health interventions</li>
        
        <li>Automated identification of mental health progression</li>
        
        <li>Mental health intervention program development and deployment</li>
        
        <li>Adoption of mental health IT</li>
        
        <li>New theories around IT use and deployment for mental health</li>
        
        <li>Role of IT in improving mental health services</li>
        
        <li>Human-AI interfaces to support mental health decision-making processes</li>
        
        <li>IT for improving mental health for specific demographics or socioeconomic status</li>
        
        <li>Bias in IT for mental health</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>March 1, 2023: Expression of Interest (two-page abstract, single spaced, 12-point font)</li>
        
        <li>July 31, 2023: Initial Submission Due</li>
        
        <li>November 30, 2023: Notification of First Round Decision</li>
        
        <li>March 30, 2024: 1st Resubmission Due</li>
        
        <li>June 30, 2024: Notification of Second Round Decision</li>
        
        <li>September 30, 2024: 2nd Resubmission Due</li>
        
        <li>December 30, 2024: Final Decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Management Information Systems (JMIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Generative AI and its Transformative Value for Digital Platforms]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jmis-generative-ai-and-its-transformative-value-for-digital-platforms</link>
            <guid>jmis-generative-ai-and-its-transformative-value-for-digital-platforms</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 12:23:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Michael Wessel</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Martin Adam</strong>, Darmstadt University of Technology</p>
        
        <p><strong>Alexander Benlian</strong>, Darmstadt University of Technology</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ann Majchrzak</strong>, University of Southern California</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ferdinand Thies</strong>, Bern University of Applied Sciences</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Generative AI, which refers to artificial intelligence (AI) algorithms that generate original outputs based on prompt inputs, has the potential to fundamentally transform the way people create and consume content online. Unlike previous generations of AI systems, which were primarily designed to recognize patterns and make predictions, Generative AI synthesizes the data it has been trained on and creates content in the form of images, text, audio, video, and more that is similar to content created by human experts – but in much less time, at a fraction of the cost, and with amazing creativity. In this special issue, we focus on the opportunities and challenges that Generative AI poses for digital platforms. Over the past two decades, social media platforms such as Twitter and YouTube, mobile app platforms such as Apple’s App Store, e-commerce platforms such as Amazon, freelance platforms such as Upwork, and sharing economy platforms such as Airbnb and Uber have reshaped and disrupted entire industries.</p>
    
    <p>What these platform companies have in common is that they create value by facilitating interactions and the exchange of goods and services between two or more groups that would have been difficult or impossible to connect in the absence of the platform. Information systems (IS) scholars have made important contributions to the literature on digital platforms, much of which has been focused on the complex relationship between the triumvirate of users, complementors (i.e., those who contribute content to the platforms such as app developers or video creators), and the platform provider, which together form the platform ecosystem. In the context of digital platforms, all stakeholders, and their interactions with one another, can be transformed by Generative AI. For example, Generative AI can enable unprecedented forms of personalization (i.e., hyper-personalization), allowing complementors to instantly tailor their offerings to meet the preferences of each individual user. However, complementors in particular may also feel threatened by the technology’s disruptive potential. For instance, research has shown that the introduction of a Generative AI system on a crowdsourcing platform can motivate complementors to either leave the platform or shift their efforts to more complex contests to avoid competing directly with the new system.</p>
    
    <p>While all platform stakeholders can draw on Generative AI to save countless hours of human labor and enhance the user experience in various platform settings, we are only beginning to understand the transformative value of the technology for digital platforms. Especially since the introduction of ChatGPT 3 by OpenAI in 2022, Generative AI is experiencing rapid growth, with Gartner predicting that 30% of outbound messages will be synthetically generated by 2025. As a major paradigm shift, Generative AI will continue to revolutionize the way we use, govern, and understand digital platforms, creating a wealth of opportunities for individuals, teams, organizations, and society. However, there are also concerns that Generative AI will lead to job displacement, as the technology becomes capable of performing tasks that were previously done by humans.</p>
    
    <p>IS researchers have contributed important insights on fundamental questions regarding the implications of AI for business as well as how the technology could and should be managed. However, with the emergence of Generative AI, new research avenues are opening up, providing an opportunity for IS scholars to conduct leading research on the transformative and value-creating capacity of this fascinating technology, especially with regard to digital platforms. As a disruptive technology, Generative AI can enable truly innovative services and business models that engage all platform stakeholders in unprecedented ways. It could disrupt entire platform industries, sending them into a downward spiral while providing groundbreaking opportunities for others. Despite this promise as a game changer, the interplay between Generative AI’s inherent potential and its transformative value for digital platforms is poorly understood and requires further research. This is an area where IS scholars are well-equipped to contribute to the discussion through cutting-edge research.</p>
    
    <p>Rather than addressing the operational and tactical merits of Generative AI, this special issue provides a dedicated forum for IS and other scholars to engage in an important dialogue on its strategic and managerial implications. In particular, we are interested in the transformative value of Generative AI for digital platforms and the impact of Generative AI on the various stakeholders in a digital platform ecosystem, including complementors, users, and platform providers. Generative AI is changing the way complementors deliver products and services. Beyond being a more advanced personalization tool, the use of Generative AI in digital platforms raises questions about how it affects the role, strategies, and capabilities of complementors over time as well as the competition among them. For instance, the technology may lower barriers to entry by shortening development times and enabling even novice complementors without technical backgrounds to engage in tasks such as app development, potentially increasing competition among complementors. And more broadly, Generative AI can contribute to transforming entire business models.</p>
    
    <p>How will complementors differentiate themselves when all textual, visual, and audio content is created by Generative AI? What is the role of humans as value creators in this world? Generative AI can provide platform users with powerful creative tools that promise productivity gains in the creation of content. These are just three examples of highly extensible formats that Generative AI can drastically influence, with serious implications for how users organize and improve their platform activities. This will enable users to create high-quality content with minimal effort, making it easier for them to express themselves and share their ideas with others. In turn, this could further blur the lines between consumers and creators of content and services on digital platforms, as the skill barrier to create is significantly reduced. With easier entry to become a complementor, it can also be of interest to see how users react to products and services created using Generative AI. Will the perception of quality be altered by the disclosure of the usage of AI? What consequences with regard to competition and differentiation can be observed in platform markets?</p>
    
    <p>As Generative AI changes how users and complementors act and interact, so does the platform where the interaction happens. While Generative AI empowers users, the resulting dynamics and complexities in the complements and interactions need to be evaluated and considered, including business and ethical limitations (e.g., privacy, copyright, unethical applications, fraud detection). In the same vein, Generative AI may be used as a means to improve governance and orchestration of digital platforms. Despite these realities, we know little about how platform providers can manage and control the employment and use of Generative AI to create flourishing ecosystems, increase alignment between all stakeholders, and build (more or less open) value networks to integrate with upstream and downstream partners along future platform chains. The transformative value of Generative AI presents major opportunities, while also raising concerns about its broader societal and economic effects. For instance, the technology can stimulate innovation and aid the development of new products and services. However, it could also contribute to job displacement, as machines take over tasks previously done by humans. Additionally, Generative AI could exacerbate existing inequalities in society by favoring those who have access to the technology, leading to a new digital divide. There are also concerns about the ethical implications of using Generative AI, including issues related to data privacy, bias, and accountability. It is thus essential to study the societal and economic effects of Generative AI to ensure that its benefits are maximized while minimizing its potential harms. We therefore also explicitly invite research that considers humanistic outcome variables (e.g., emotional and mental well-being of individuals and society) rather than focusing strictly on efficiency and productivity perspectives. The focus of this special issue is to stimulate innovative investigation of the transformative value of Generative AI for digital platforms at or between all levels of analysis. Digital platforms should be the empirical setting. All lenses of inquiry into the disruptive nature and impact of Generative AI for digital platforms are encouraged, including strategic, organizational, behavioral, economic, and technical perspectives. We welcome theoretical, analytical, and empirical (including trace data from platforms, surveys, experiments, simulations, qualitative data, case studies, and secondary data from organizational, market, and regulatory sources) contributions to the special issue. Consistent with the policies of JMIS, the papers should aim to make a significant novel contribution to the IS field. Possible research areas include, but are not limited to:</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>The transformative value of Generative AI for complementors</li>
        
        <li>The transformative value of Generative AI for users</li>
        
        <li>The transformative value of Generative AI for platform providers</li>
        
        <li>The societal and economic effects of Generative AI</li>
        
        <li>Accessibility: The role of Generative AI in enhancing accessibility and inclusion on digital platforms</li>
        
        <li>Empowerment: Generative AI and its value for the democratization and empowerment of marginalized groups</li>
        
        <li>Automated content creation: Use of Generative AI to automate content creation on digital platforms</li>
        
        <li>Human engagement in Generative AI: Training and updating Generative AI to achieve better results</li>
        
        <li>Business model and value proposition: Generative AI can possibly alter a platform’s business model</li>
        
        <li>Generative AI as a platform: Many new Generative AI systems offer boundary resources</li>
        
        <li>Network effects: How can Generative AI help to kickstart and maintain network effects?</li>
        
        <li>Competition between digital platforms: Does Generative AI level the playing field between rival platforms?</li>
        
        <li>Platform governance and openness: How do boundary resources change to compensate for automatic content creation?</li>
        
        <li>Society and governments: What are the consequences of Generative AI beyond digital platforms?</li>
        
        <li>User experience: The impact of Generative AI on user engagement, satisfaction, and experience</li>
        
        <li>Humanistic outcomes: The role of Generative AI for the emotional and mental well-being of users</li>
        
        <li>Personalized content: The potential of Generative AI to create personalized content and enhance the relevance of recommendations</li>
        
        <li>Ethical considerations: The ethical implications of using Generative AI on digital platforms.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Invalid DateTime: Final decision</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2023: Optional extended abstract submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2024: Full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2024: First round of reviews completed</li>
        
        <li>August 15, 2024: Paper revisions due</li>
        
        <li>October 15, 2024: Second round of reviews completed</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2024: Second paper revisions due</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Ivo Blohm</strong>, University of St.Gallen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alec W. Cram</strong>, University of Waterloo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ben Eaton</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jens Förderer</strong>, Technical University Munich</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dominik Gutt</strong>, Rotterdam School of Management, Erasmus University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Thomas L. Huber</strong>, ESSEC Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Philipp Hukal</strong>, BI Norwegian Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Thomas Kude</strong>, University of Bamberg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Harris Kyriakou</strong>, ESSEC Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gene Moo Lee</strong>, UBC Sauder School of Business</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wietske Van Osch</strong>, HEC Montreal</li>
        
        <li><strong>Roopa Raman</strong>, University of Dayton</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mark de Reuver</strong>, Delft University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anne-Francoise Rutkowski</strong>, Tilburg University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stefan Seidel</strong>, University of Cologne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Markus Weinmann</strong>, University of Cologne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Martin Wiener</strong>, Technical University Dresden</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michael Andreas Zaggl</strong>, Aarhus University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Management Information Systems (JMIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unleashing the Power of Information Technology for Strategic Management of Disasters]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isr-unleashing-the-power-of-information-technology-for-strategic-management-of-disasters</link>
            <guid>isr-unleashing-the-power-of-information-technology-for-strategic-management-of-disasters</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:33:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Ahmed Abbasi</strong>, University of Notre Dame</p>
        
        <p><strong>Robin Dillon-Merrill</strong>, Georgetown University</p>
        
        <p><strong>H. Raghav Rao</strong>, University of Texas, San Antonio</p>
        
        <p><strong>Olivia Sheng</strong>, University of Utah</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The 21st Century has been termed “the century of disasters” (Achenbach 2011). These include natural and human-caused disasters. The former encompass geophysical (e.g., earthquakes), hydrological (e.g., floods), climatological (e.g., wildfires), meteorological (e.g., cyclones), or biological (e.g., disease epidemics such as COVID-19) disasters. The latter are caused by human-led events, such as conflicts, famine, terrorist attacks, cybersecurity incidents, and industrial accidents (IFRC 2010). A myriad of factors has contributed to a surge in disasters: technological innovation, population growth, climate change, demographic changes, and evolving social dynamics. When they happen, such disasters exact a devastating toll on civil and technical infrastructure and society as a whole (e.g., loss of human life, social and economic disturbances, and environmental damage).</p>
    
    <p>In extreme cases where natural and human-caused disasters join forces, the suffering of victims often increases exponentially. For example, the outbreak of COVID-19 has added a new threat to refugees and humanitarian resettlement programs (CDC 2020). The International Rescue Committee (2020) commented that “People in refugee camps in Syria, Greece and Bangladesh face a heightened risk of COVID-19 due to more densely populated conditions than even the Diamond Princess—the cruise ship where transmission of the virus was four times faster than in Wuhan.”</p>
    
    <p>Worldwide, government agencies, private sectors, and the public are in desperate search for new tools, practices, and strategies to safeguard society against the threat of disasters (Chen et al. 2013; Park et al. 2015). For policy makers, Information technology (IT) has been considered important in enabling and supporting efficient and effective disaster management. In recognition of the potential role of IT, as early as 2007, the United States Congress followed the E-government Act of 2002 to direct the National Research Council to study the application of IT to disaster management. Over the past decade, the world has seen an increasing level of IT use in modern disaster management (Beydoun et al. 2018). Examples include blockchain for disaster logistics, wearable technologies for rescue teams and victims, remote monitoring sensors for intelligence gathering, virtual reality for response preparedness and training, GIS for crisis mapping, social media for disaster information dissemination and extraction of real-time intelligence, and big data for impact assessment and forecasting. Such IT uses have been found across the globe.</p>
    
    <p>Management of disasters is challenging for its multi-phase, multi-hazard, multi-stakeholder, multi-task, multi-objective nature. First, disaster management follows multiple phases: mitigation, preparedness, response, and recovery. In the example of the preparedness phase, efforts are taken to develop a single- or all-hazard disaster plan, evaluate and modify the plan, exercise the plan (e.g., table-top exercises or drills), and stock inventory (e.g., water and food). These phases are interconnected as the performance of one response phase affects that of the next phase. Second, disaster management calls for different specialties and strategies in response to various disaster types, such as pandemics, terrorist attacks, mass shootings, earthquakes, tsunamis, wildfires, floods, hurricanes, and train derailments. For example, management of pandemic and terrorist attacks focus on responding to and containing a disaster after its appearance (i.e., reactionary), whereas floods and hurricanes necessitate proactive mitigation strategies in anticipation of the disaster. Third, disaster management involves a broad stakeholder approach, potentially encompassing international coalitions (e.g., the U.N.), local government, public safety and security (e.g., Fire, Police, and Hazmat), logistics providers, public health and medical services, humanitarian / social society organizations, military, transportation, utility and public works, donors, media, and business/civilian victims. While these stakeholders might agree on the general principle of social good, their exact goals and objectives might vary (Abbasi et al. 2019). Fourth, disaster management handles a wide range of operations, such as unified command, situational assessment, coordinated operations, risk assessment (Tinsley et al. 2011; Dillion and Tinsley 2008), impact analysis, resource allocation, victim assistance, supply chain and logistics, and financing. Fifth, disaster management works to achieve objectives such as preserving lives and properties, containing the impact, protecting the health and safety of response personnel, safeguarding the natural environment, sustaining business and civilian activities, protecting critical infrastructures, informing the public, and restoring and rebuilding affected communities. Finally, disaster management consists of mitigation of harm in the disaster context, which may include examination of harms and harm quantification, tracing the impact of harm and identifying susceptible population, and dissemination of harm.</p>
    
    <p>To help policy makers, IT can provide strategic support that addresses each aspect of disaster management. In the example of multi-stakeholder support, IT can be used to interconnect stakeholders for building response partnerships. In doing so, it is also important to avoid IT misuse which may create digital chaos and impede first responders and other offline disaster management activities; for instance, human- or bot-led propagation of false information on social media. The security and privacy issues of IT use surrounding disaster management is also an important consideration. Compared with other disciplines (e.g., Management Science), scholars in IS have been relatively silent about disaster management – new findings on the proper design, use, and management of IT can undoubtedly have a huge real-world impact. IS research in disaster management may be performed at multiple levels: individual, organizational, and social. Different methods, such as qualitative, quantitative, data science, and design science can all contribute to building a stronger body of knowledge.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Resolving interoperability barriers across governmental or industry entities</li>
        
        <li>Management of disaster information sharing across regions or countries</li>
        
        <li>Strategies and policies for disaster information privacy and security</li>
        
        <li>Building virtual disaster response command on demand</li>
        
        <li>IT enabled cross-agency collaboration and coordination</li>
        
        <li>Ethical, legal, cultural, and social issues (e.g., information privacy in tracking citizens who have contracted COVID-19)</li>
        
        <li>Social inequality, induced by digital divide and digital literacy, in the access and use of IT for disasters</li>
        
        <li>Knowledge sharing and coordination during and across the key response phases</li>
        
        <li>Disaster decision making and monitoring using low quality data and information</li>
        
        <li>Disaster decision making under urgency and risk (including mitigating harm from disasters)</li>
        
        <li>Optimization of disaster resource allocation (e.g., hospital utilization in mass shootings)</li>
        
        <li>Conflict resolution (e.g., blowing up a levee to save a town at the cost of drowning farmland)</li>
        
        <li>Organizational mindfulness, adaptation, and disaster resilience</li>
        
        <li>Strategies and tactics in engaging the public</li>
        
        <li>Community rebuilding using online communities, the crowd and apps</li>
        
        <li>Business continuity in the face of disasters</li>
        
        <li>Advanced ICT including AI, big data, IoT, and unmanned aerial vehicles for disaster response and recovery</li>
        
        <li>Disaster Management as a Service</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>June 30, 2021: Two-page Abstract</li>
        
        <li>July 30, 2021: Feedback on Abstracts</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2021: Five-page Extended Abstract</li>
        
        <li>October 9, 2021: UT San Antonio Workshop</li>
        
        <li>February 15, 2022: Full Paper Submission</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2022: First Round of Editorial Decisions</li>
        
        <li>June 30, 2022: Virtual Meeting with the SI Editors to Discuss Revision Plans</li>
        
        <li>August 30, 2022: Revisions Due</li>
        
        <li>November 30, 2022: Second Round of Editorial Decisions</li>
        
        <li>January 30, 2023: Final Revisions Due</li>
        
        <li>April 30, 2023: Final Editorial Decisions</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Ghasan Beydoun</strong>, University of Technology Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tanmoy Chakraborty</strong>, IIT Delhi</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rui Chen</strong>, Iowa State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tina Comes</strong>, Delft University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rahul De</strong>, IIM Bangalore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yogesh Dwivedi</strong>, Swansea University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xiao Fang</strong>, University of Delaware</li>
        
        <li><strong>Frank Fiedrich</strong>, Wuppertal University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Guodong (Gordon) Gao</strong>, University of Maryland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rajiv Garg</strong>, Emory University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hong Guo</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Han-fen Hu</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Paul Hu</strong>, University of Utah</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marijn Janssen</strong>, Delft University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>K.D. Joshi</strong>, University of Nevada, Reno</li>
        
        <li><strong>Raymond Y.K. Lau</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zhepeng (Lionel) Li</strong>, York University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xiaobai (Bob) Li</strong>, University of Massachusetts, Lowell</li>
        
        <li><strong>Onook Oh</strong>, University of Colorado Denver</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wonseok Oh</strong>, KAIST</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gautam Pant</strong>, University of Iowa</li>
        
        <li><strong>Insu Park</strong>, Dakota State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Raymond Patterson</strong>, University of Calgary</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alfonso Pedraza-Martinez</strong>, Indiana University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ram Sudha</strong>, University of Arizona</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Lancaster University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Chih-Ping Wei</strong>, National Taiwan University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Heng Xu</strong>, American University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Huimin Zhao</strong>, University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kang Zhao</strong>, University of Iowa</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Research (ISR)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Regulation in the Age of Digitalization]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-regulation-in-the-age-of-digitalization</link>
            <guid>jit-regulation-in-the-age-of-digitalization</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:32:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Daniel Gozman</strong>, University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Tom Butler</strong>, University College Cork</p>
        
        <p><strong>Kalle Lyytinen</strong>, Case Western Reserve University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The rise of information technology (IT) in organizations has been an inherent part of an agenda to increase and shape forms of social control. Despite the inherent link between uses of IT and social control, the topic of regulation has not received significant attention in the information system field – neither theoretically nor empirically. This special issue seeks to address this gap.</p>
    
    <p>The issue explores the growing and significant interplay between IT and regulation in the age of digitalization, where new challenges with social control with IT are emerging. In this special issue, we are interested in two broad domains of research related to regulation and IT: regulation through IT and regulation of IT.</p>
    
    <p>The first domain – regulation through IT – concerns new forms and arenas of regulation enacted through innovative IT solutions (often called “RegTech”). These technologies which are increasingly implicated in regulatory practices include new forms of real-time big data analytics, machine learning and other artificial intelligence (AI) techniques, use of blockchains and distributed ledgers, Internet of Things solutions or natural language processing techniques. These technologies change the ways organizations and industrial sectors respond to and comply with a growing number of regulatory obligations and needs. These technologies are also driving changes in the ways in which regulators seek to supervise and monitor firms and the ways in which firms comply with laws and regulations. Greater market and organizational transparency and enhanced supervision are now advocated as critical responses to organizational misconduct and associated risks. This has resulted in an increasing call for bureaucratization and (over-) regulation. Call for greater monitoring, supervision and sanctioning have been driven by concerns regarding the environment, health and safety risks, corporate fiscal and fiduciary scandals, financial failures leading to financial crisis in 2007-2008, or growing violations of data privacy that increased the “volume, velocity and variety” of laws and regulations that organizations must comply with and the range of novel IT based solutions they need to comply to such demands. Regulators have also shown a growing appetite to measure performance, to quantify financial, regulatory and operational risk and to improve compliance reporting through new technologies that assign accountability, enforce security and behavioural control, automate monitoring and enhance record keeping.</p>
    
    <p>The second domain – regulation of IT – is the wide range deployment and associated regulatory effects of new IT (especially concerns of security, privacy and/or safety). There is a notable gap in the field’s knowledge regarding new demands and ways of regulating IT (e.g., social media) given its scale, complexity and pervasive use. Concerns regarding the pervasive effects of platform businesses on privacy, competition and information veracity have invited calls to control and scrutinize technology vendors. Similar issues are likely to emerge in autonomous cars, user-based insurance, health policies and so on. There are consequently increased demands to regulate various IT solutions and to increase regulatory powers of governments related to IT uses, including through introducing entirely new regulatory bodies. If platform providers and vendors, or organizations offering extensive algorithmic solutions as parts of their related services, are subjected to new regulatory structures, then important questions arise regarding what degrees of transparency and reporting are appropriate and how related forms of supervision and sanctioning would function that need to regulate actual systems and their functioning and those who are implicated in their design.</p>
    
    <p>We invite empirical and theoretical research that contribute to our understanding and application how regulation is enacted through IT or how uses of IT can be regulated. We encourage submissions that use diverse epistemological and methodological approaches to focus on emerging and new regulatory solutions and practices. Submissions may engage in cross-disciplinary inquiries and should offer novel knowledge and fresh methodological, theoretical and empirical insights how regulation and IT evolve and are related. The papers will be evaluated for their interestingness, novelty and credibility of the contribution. If in doubt, interested authors should consult the special issue guest editors whether their papers fall within the scope of the special issue. To this end, authors are encouraged to submit an extended abstract to the editors for initial feedback.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Regulatory technologies for supervising and complying (regulation through IT)</li>
        
        <li>Regulation of social media technologies and platforms</li>
        
        <li>Regulation of IT solutions and related solutions during design, implementation and use</li>
        
        <li>Regulation of AI</li>
        
        <li>How to bridge the gap between ethics and policy (e.g., for AI)</li>
        
        <li>Strategic implications of regulating technologies for nations, industries and firms</li>
        
        <li>Solutions for data privacy, protection, governance and &quot;fake news&quot;</li>
        
        <li>Cybersecurity obligations and mitigating related risks at the organizational level</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>January 31, 2021: First round submission</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2021: Round 1 decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2021: Second round submission</li>
        
        <li>September 1, 2021: Second round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>November 1, 2021: Third and Final Round submissions</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2021: Final decision to authors</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Barney Tan</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Chris Parker</strong>, American University</li>
        
        <li><strong>David Tilson</strong>, University of Rochester</li>
        
        <li><strong>Eric Lim</strong>, University New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>Francois de Vaujany</strong>, Université Paris - Dauphine</li>
        
        <li><strong>Frantz Rowe</strong>, Université de Nantes</li>
        
        <li><strong>Heiko Gewald</strong>, Neu - Ulm University of Applied Science</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jonas Hedman</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>M. Lynne Markus</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Markos Zachariadis</strong>, University of Warwick</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michael zur Muehlen</strong>, Stevens Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michel Avital</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mikhail Oet</strong>, Northeastern University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nicholas Berente</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pierangelo Rosati</strong>, Dublin City University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Roman Beck</strong>, IT University of Copenhagen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shazia Sadiq</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Silvia Masiero</strong>, Loughborough University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stefan Haefliger</strong>, City University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Theo Lynn</strong>, Dublin City University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Uri Gal</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Vladislav Fomin</strong>, University of Vilnius</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Emerging Technologies and IS Sourcing]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-emerging-technologies-and-is-sourcing</link>
            <guid>jit-emerging-technologies-and-is-sourcing</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:31:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ilan Oshri</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Oliver Krancher</strong>, IT University of Copenhagen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Sabherwal</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The last decade has seen a significant proliferation of new technologies. These include robotic process automation, big data, machine/deep learning and artificial intelligence, blockchain, and other &quot;emerging technologies&quot;. Consulting and market research companies have consistently predicted that the current wave of technologies will transform both front and back office operations, requiring firms to rethink their business models and strategies.</p>
    
    <p>While evidence suggests that firms will continue to invest in emerging technologies, there has so far been little evidence about the involvement of service providers and advisory in the selection, design, and adoption of such emerging technologies. IS sourcing research has conventionally accounted for three main areas of interest: sourcing decision, contractual structures, and relationship management. Emerging technologies challenge these traditional conventions in the IS sourcing literature. Particular challenges include but are not limited to: greater dependency on data in emerging technologies, which triggers clients to source data science services; the actual implementation of emerging technology often happens through platforms that involve multiple players and services; the asset transfer model has become less relevant and yet client firms are still expected to reduce their headcount; there is greater emphasis on the redesign of the value chain as services have become digitized and decisions are now driven by smart algorithms; emerging technologies are viewed as a black box, posing a skills and expertise challenge to client firms to ensure acquiring and retaining knowledge of the technology.</p>
    
    <p>Further, the IS sourcing literature which has traditionally relied on three main reference theories, namely, transaction cost economics, resource dependency, and social exchange. Emerging technologies emphasize the need to expand this theoretical base and accommodate new paradigms of capturing and analyzing data in IS sourcing research. Taking into account the above observations, the IS sourcing literature thus begs for the re-examination of client-supplier-advisory relationships by challenging core concepts of sourcing decision, contractual structure, and relationship management as offering new theoretical landscapes that accommodate the sourcing phenomenon in a digital age.</p>
    
    <p>This special issue seeks to facilitate an empirical and theoretical re-examination of &quot;IS sourcing&quot; in the light of the current wave of emerging technologies. We invite research papers that investigate issues relating to emerging technologies and IS sourcing, particularly focusing on robotic process automation, big data, machine/deep learning and artificial intelligence, and blockchain. Other technologies are less of interest for this special issue.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Governance and control structures between client-supplier-advisory in emerging technology settings</li>
        
        <li>Sourcing decision making in emerging technology settings</li>
        
        <li>Ecosystem and platforms in emerging technology sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Contract management in emerging technology sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Full data lifecycle in emerging technologies and its implications for sourcing management</li>
        
        <li>Skills and capability development and retention in emerging technology sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Implications for innovations within the client-supplier-advisory eco-system</li>
        
        <li>Ethical and societal implications deriving from such sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Impact of emerging technologies on client’s, supplier’s and advisory’s strategies, business models and capabilities</li>
        
        <li>Implications of crowdsourcing, big data, analytics as well as machine/deep learning and artificial intelligence for the contemporary IS outsourcing</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>April 15, 2021: First round submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>July 25, 2021: First round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>October 25, 2021: Second round submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>January 28, 2022: Second round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2022: Third and final round submissions deadline</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2022: Final decision to authors</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ethical Issues and Unintended Consequences of Digitalization and Platformization]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-ethical-issues-and-unintended-consequences-of-digitalization-and-platformization</link>
            <guid>jit-ethical-issues-and-unintended-consequences-of-digitalization-and-platformization</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:30:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Matti Rossi</strong>, Aalto University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Christy M. K. Cheung</strong>, Hong Kong Baptist University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Supratek Sarker</strong>, University of Virginia</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jason B. Thatcher</strong>, Temple University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Disruptive digital innovations do not come without pain – the disorder that they introduce can create negative externalities and unintended consequences for people, communities, industries and economies. In the worst case, there is disruption with little innovation. This can lead to job losses for individuals, loss of human dignity, negative health impacts, lost revenue for communities, obsolescence of industries and loss of the traditional values that underpin modern societies.</p>
    
    <p>Sarker et al. (2019) note that “humanistic concerns arising from the curtailing of human freedom and development, and from racism, sexism and commodification of the human body are overlooked for the apparent benefits that systems, including widely used search engines and medical databases, promise to deliver (Noble 2018; Wachter-Boettcher 2017). Indeed, there is a rising need for a thorough ethical interrogation of algorithms (O’Neil 2016) that underlie systems mediating many critical human activities, so as not to marginalize certain stakeholders, especially those ‘who are already in the margin’ (Noble 2018, p. 171).</p>
    
    <p>In this special issue, we take this critical, yet constructive view of technological and social changes associated with “digital transformation” (Zuboff 2015, Wood et al. 2019, Larsson and Teigland 2020). We are interested in contrarian papers that reject the taken-for-granted assumptions of positive impacts of technology, as in cases of digital platforms, telework enabled by mobility, growth of the gig economy, fintech/blockchain, and so on, and investigate relatively unexamined platform externalities as a means to identify ways to resolve paradoxes, discontinuities and challenges posed by technology and the unintended consequences of technology applications.</p>
    
    <p>We also seek papers that shed light on the problems of information technology (IT)-enabled phenomena such as the implications of winner-takes-all platform economics; highlight the social, environmental and economic implications of blockchain and similar innovative digital technologies; or propose solutions that mitigate negative societal impacts of innovation (e.g., through leveraging the power social networks to disseminate information and strengthen democratic discourse).</p>
    
    <p>We encourage the submission of manuscripts taking either of two stances: 1) Submissions considering a critical or dystopian view of the social, technological and moral implications of digitization and digital transformation. Here, “the dark side” – ethical issues, unintended digitalization and other problematic aspects – of digitalization and platformization are front and centre the argument. An example may be Zuboff’s (2015, 2019) recent work on surveillance capitalism and her analyses of large-scale digitization “gone wrong”. 2) Submissions seeking to balance or reconcile “the dark side” and “the bright side” of digitalization and platformization. Here, analyses, exemplars and theoretical frameworks considered ethical issues and negative consequences explicitly, in addition to intended benefits of digitalization too often exclusively focused on. An example may be social media research: initial writings trumpeted the benefits of social media for building relationships, with later work highlighting problematic behaviours such as cyberbullying or doxxing.</p>
    
    <p>In this special issue, we are open to all forms of inquiry, including surveys, experiments, case studies, design science projects and conceptual work that probe “the dark side”, ethical issues and unintended consequences of digitization, platformization and the rapid diffusion of digital infrastructures and digital work models based thereon.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Digital Taylorism and the race to the bottom for workers</li>
        
        <li>Destruction of jobs by “botization”</li>
        
        <li>Risks for society from fast-spreading false information</li>
        
        <li>Systemic risks and vulnerability of digital platforms</li>
        
        <li>Management incompetence in digital transformation</li>
        
        <li>Risks of IoT and blockchain</li>
        
        <li>Dark side and ethics of sharing economy and gig economy</li>
        
        <li>Digital privacy and surveillance capitalism</li>
        
        <li>Bias in algorithms and artificial intelligence</li>
        
        <li>Digital inequity and digital divide between “the North” and “the South”</li>
        
        <li>Fake news, misinformation, and disinformation in social media</li>
        
        <li>Fake and biased online reviews and co-creation on digital platforms</li>
        
        <li>The emergence of deep web/dark net marketplaces</li>
        
        <li>Subjective well-being (e.g., FOMO and social media fatigue)</li>
        
        <li>Cyberharassment, cyberbullying and cyberstalking</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>June 1, 2021: First round submission</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2021: First round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2022: Second round submission</li>
        
        <li>April 1, 2022: Second round decision to authors (reject or accept with minor revision)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Margunn Aanestad</strong>, Agder University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Benlian</strong>, TU Darmstadt</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michelle Carter</strong>, Washington State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tommy Chan</strong>, Northumbria University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mike Dinger</strong>, University of South Carolina - Upstate</li>
        
        <li><strong>Taha Havakor</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>J. J. Po - An Hsieh</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hanna Krasnova</strong>, University of Potsdam</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, UNSW Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alvin Leung</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juho Lindman</strong>, University of Gothenburg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jani Merikivi</strong>, Grenoble Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Daniel Pienta</strong>, Baylor University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marten Risius</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Markus Salo</strong>, University of Jyvaskyla</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sebastian Schuetz</strong>, Florida International University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carsten Sorensen</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ali Sunyaev</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Lancaster University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Manuel Trenz</strong>, University of Göttingen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xiao Xiao</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Products of Theorizing: Towards Native Theories of Emerging IT]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-products-of-theorizing-towards-native-theories-of-emerging-it</link>
            <guid>jit-products-of-theorizing-towards-native-theories-of-emerging-it</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:29:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Nik Hassan</strong>, University of Minnesota Duluth</p>
        
        <p><strong>Suzanne Rivard</strong>, HEC Montreal</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ulrike Schultze</strong>, Southern Methodist University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Leslie Willcocks</strong>, London School of Economics and Political Science</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Theorizing is one of the defining aspects of academic research. Articulating insights generated from situated empirical observations into relatively stable abstractions (e.g., concepts, propositions, models) that elucidate, explain or predict events occurring at another time and place is the hallmark of knowledge generation (King 2021). Of late, much attention has been paid to theory development in the Information Systems (IS) field. For example, the MIS Quarterly (MISQ) special issue on &#39;Next-Generation Information Systems Theorizing&#39; reflects a sense of urgency felt within the IS field to make sense of an increasingly unruly and complex reality given the increasing pace of technological innovation (Burton-Jones et al. 2021). In similar vein, two 2021 Journal of Information Technology (JIT) debates sections focused on &#39;IS Research and Science&#39; (Siponen and Klaavuniemi 2020, and commentaries) and &#39;Theorising as Craft&#39; (Rivard 2021, and commentaries) and a recent Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS) special issue focused on &#39;Envisioning Digital Transformation – Advancing Theoretical Diversity&#39;. New and native IS theories ensure that the IS field remains vibrant, diverse, academically and socially relevant and influential (Hassan 2011; Hassan and Willcocks 2021; Lowry et al. 2020; Markus and Saunders 2007). Researchers, however, often set the bar too high for theory delivered within individual research contributions by viewing theory as a comprehensive and detailed explanation of a phenomenon (Rivard 2021), an object that Weick (1995) refers to as a &#39;theory that sweeps away all others&#39; (p. 386). This mindset may lead IS researchers to adopt theories from other fields as a foundation rather than creatively developing new and native theories from empirical observations (Grover and Lyytinen 2015).</p>
    
    <p>To maintain the long-term growth and vitality of the IS field, a definition of theory that encourages cumulative and novel theorizing over time is needed (Hassan and Willcocks 2021; King 2021). One way of achieving this is by advancing a &#39;products of theorizing&#39; perspective (Weick 1995). The theorizing perspective celebrates both the final outcomes and the &#39;interim struggles&#39; that characterize theory generation (Weick 1995). It holds the promise that interim conceptual artifacts of theorizing such as metaphors, frameworks and concepts (Lowry et al. 2020) are valuable to the discipline as they can be leveraged and exploited further in subsequent research. In this way, a discipline might inch its way towards native theories over time. The goal of this special issue is to solicit and showcase exemplars from the &#39;products of theorizing&#39; approach. We are looking for articles that go beyond verification dimensions of the natural-science approach to IS research (Schlagwein 2021) and push the envelope of theorizing towards native products of theorizing (Hassan et al. forthcoming): theory frame devices (i.e., questions, paradigms, laws and frameworks), theory generators (i.e., myths, analogies, metaphors and models) and theory components (i.e., concepts, constructs, statements and hypotheses).</p>
    
    <p>The time is ripe to embark upon the development of native theories in the IS field, as IT has leaped into the consciousness of the public in unprecedented ways. Big data and AI applications are part of consumers’ and workers’ everyday lives, either enhancing them or increasing their visibility (Aral 2020; Benbya et al. 2021; Zuboff 2019); firms increasingly deploy robotic process automation and cognitive automation, aiming to achieve benefits for themselves, their employees and their customers (Lacity and Willcocks 2021); and governments rely on new forms of data collection about citizens (e.g., blood samples, vaccination data, fingerprints, iris-recognition systems) in support of the services they provide (Kolas et al. 2021). To take advantage of the theorizing opportunities that these emergent information technology (IT) phenomena provide, the goal of this special issue is to encourage research that generates products of theorizing derived from and related to IT phenomena. We are seeking contributions that develop products of theorizing, that is, interim constructions, that are useful as precursors to strong native IS theory. To increase the likelihood of a theorizing product’s value, we are particularly interested in research that tackles phenomena that are core to the IS discipline. Given the multifaceted nature of the IS discipline, we do not expect agreement on what constitutes a core IS phenomenon. We therefore encourage authors to make the case that the products of theorizing they develop are valuable for articulating native theories that are defining of the field of IS or are substantially valuable for their specific area.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Use of theory generators (e.g., analogies, myths, models and metaphors) for understanding and guiding research of emergent phenomena such as surveillance capitalism, fake news, social media, or the performativity of big data and AI.</li>
        
        <li>Constructing or formulating novel frameworks derived from or relevant to emerging technologies.</li>
        
        <li>Adopting a genealogical lens to uncover the products of theorizing that have been instrumental in the theories that have become popular in the IS discipline (e.g., socio-technical, sociomateriality, imbrication).</li>
        
        <li>Reviewing and analysing the foundations of core concepts of the IS field such as that of &#39;information,&#39; &#39;system&#39; and &#39;technology&#39;.</li>
        
        <li>Re-theorizing areas or subfields within IS (e.g., design science, data analytics, big data, AI) where native products of theorizing are sparse.</li>
        
        <li>Problematizing the IS field (i.e., going beyond gap-spotting and borrowing theory from reference disciplines) to identify questions and challenges that the field of IS is uniquely qualified to address.</li>
        
        <li>Inventing native original concepts in the IS field that will serve as foundations for the scientific IS research method and declare to the world, the field’s core concerns.</li>
        
        <li>Exploring the role of scientific laws in IS research as a product of theorizing with relevance to emerging phenomena.</li>
        
        <li>Unpacking products of theorizing (e.g., questions, models and frameworks) that uncover deep-seated assumptions about contemporary IS phenomena (e.g., symbols of value, solidarity, social structure, conflict and contradictions within a technology-driven society) that are especially relevant to emerging technologies.</li>
        
        <li>Distinguishing between non-observable constructs from more observable concepts that are rarely discussed in IS research but form the mainstay of scientific studies.</li>
        
        <li>Aggregating the statements, claims and propositions that have been made by a stream of IS literature and that are deemed most impactful on and relevant for contemporary users, organizations and society, to set the stage for the further progress towards native IS theory.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>October 24, 2021: Extended abstracts (for workshop and feedback) due</li>
        
        <li>December 12, 2021: Workshop at ICIS 2021 SIG PHIL</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2022: First-round submissions version due</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2022: First-round reviews returned</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2022: Second-round submissions due</li>
        
        <li>August 30, 2022: Second-round reviews returned</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2022: Final versions due</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2022: Final decisions and publication online</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Transformation as Geo-Political, Organizational and Technological Nexus]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-digital-transformation-as-geo-political-organizational-and-technological-nexus</link>
            <guid>jit-digital-transformation-as-geo-political-organizational-and-technological-nexus</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:28:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Wendy L. Currie</strong>, Audencia Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Carol Hsu</strong>, The University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ben Van Vliet</strong>, Illinois Institute of Technology</p>
        
        <p><strong>Vishanth Weerakkody</strong>, University of Bradford</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue focuses on the currently ongoing – and recently COVID-19 -accelerated – digital transformation(s) of economy and society. That is, how industry sectors and societal domains are reshaped by the geo-political, organizational and technological nexus that is &#39;digital transformation&#39;. The literature on digital transformation is interdisciplinary, spanning fields such as information systems (Vial, 2019), management (Hanelt et al., 2021) and other business disciplines (Verhoef et al., 2021). However, this work&#39;s broad range and somewhat incoherent framings show a lack of consensus of &#39;digital transformation&#39; as both a theoretical concept and an empirical field (Warner and Wager, 2019).</p>
    
    <p>Thus far, most digital transformation studies have focused on the organization as the unit of analysis. Why a single definition of digital transformation may be elusive, the digital transformation seems most often used to as a just a shorthand for IT-enabled organizational transformation (Besson and Rowe, 2012; Wessel et al, 2020), an organization-centric approach. Digital transformation processes increasingly take place at wider scales, beyond individual organizations and their business processes. Digital transformation(s) affect financial markets (Currie et al., 2018), healthcare (Pouloudi et al., 2016) or government (Weerakkody et al., 2016). Digital transformation(s) hence often have disruptive effects in relation to industry structures, corporate strategy, consumer experiences, policies and overall economic and societal trajectories (Legner et al., 2017; Zuboff, 2015; Vial, 2019).</p>
    
    <p>In this special issue, we invite especially that a) study digital transformation as a process (preferred over simplistic &#39;cause-and-effect&#39; hypotheses), and b) understand digital transformation in a broad sense, that is, in relation to industries, governments, economies and societies (preferred over organization-centric approaches).</p>
    
    <p>We are interested in work that understands digital transformation as a process. Studies of interest may use process theories, process analyses and/or process data to provide explanations (Langley, 1999). Process studies offer a means of conceptualizing events and identifying patterns (Gehman et al., 2018). These aspects have often been neglected in IS studies in favour of simplistic variance models (Karpovsky and Galliers 2015). Approaching digital transformation fundamentally as a process promises to produce theoretical accounts with nuanced explanations of change (Weick and Quinn, 1999). Variance models (and other types of models) are also welcomed to the special issue. Still, they will be expected to pay attention to digital transformation as a process and not to neglect the relevant processual patterns or temporal order.</p>
    
    <p>We are interested in work that studies digital transformation in a broad sense. Such work may see digital transformation as a nexus of technological, organizational, industrial, economic, governmental, societal and geo-political changes. This nexus invites theoretical and empirical studies which extend organization-centric views to understanding wider processes in which digital IT plays a key role. Emerging IT (artificial intelligence and machine learning, robotics and automation, blockchains and cryptocurrencies, meta- verses, remote working technologies, etc.) may generate specific opportunities for such research. Digital transformations come with significant challenges for businesses and societies, governments, and regulators across jurisdictions. Organization-centric approaches are welcomed to the special issue but must pay attention to wider developments and contexts and argue why the organization is the best locus of study.</p>
    
    <p>In preparing papers for this special issue, authors are expected to engage with the concept of digital transformation as a process and provide critical theoretical and/or empirical analysis extending beyond IT-driven change of isolated business processes.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Study digital transformation as a process</li>
        
        <li>Understand digital transformation in a broad sense, in relation to industries, governments, economies and societies</li>
        
        <li>Digital transformation of industry sectors (e.g., health, finance, retail)</li>
        
        <li>Digital transformation driven by ecosystems and platforms</li>
        
        <li>Regulation and governance of digital transformation</li>
        
        <li>Process studies on digital transformation identifying episodic and/or continuous changes</li>
        
        <li>Revealing unintended consequences of digital transformation or the corresponding policies, strategies, and operations</li>
        
        <li>Multi-disciplinary studies on digital transformation, especially if leading to novel theoretical perspectives</li>
        
        <li>Extreme or revealing digital transformation cases or scenarios</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>April 15, 2022: Abstracts submissions (optional; authors are invited to submit extended abstracts of papers for early reactions)</li>
        
        <li>August 15, 2022: First-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>October 20, 2022: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2023: Second-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2023: Second-round decisions (papers are either acceptable with minor changes or rejected at this stage)</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2023: Final versions due (final decisions and online publication soon afterwards)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Next-Generation Information Systems Research Methods]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-next-generation-information-systems-research-methods</link>
            <guid>jit-next-generation-information-systems-research-methods</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:27:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Ivo Blohm</strong>, University of St. Gallen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Susanna Ho</strong>, Australian National University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Oklahoma</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jan Marco Leimeister</strong>, University of St. Gallen</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue is interested in &#39;next-generation&#39; research methods for studying information technology (IT) phenomena – particularly in the information system (IS) research field. So far, IS researchers have applied a range of quantitative, qualitative and engaged methods to study IT-related phenomena. Quantitative IS research has often followed a positivist approach of hypothesis testing, with sometimes &#39;first-generation&#39; regression models distinguished from &#39;second-generation&#39; structural equation models (Gerow et al. 2011). Data used in such methods stems from surveys, experiments, panel studies, etc. The primary objective of this research stream typically is theory testing. Qualitative IS research has ranged from positivist to interpretivist, seeking rich situated insights via case studies, grounded theory or ethnographies. One objective of this research stream is theory construction. Critical and emancipatory IS research adds a strong value orientation and theoretical basis to qualitative research. Another type of IS research seeks to generate new knowledge with &#39;engaged&#39; methods like design science or action research. The objective of this stream that differentiates it from the first two is the focus on solving important individual, organizational or societal challenges; or extending the boundaries of human and organizational capabilities by creating new and innovative artifacts (Baskerville and Wood-Harper 1996; Hevner et al. 2004).</p>
    
    <p>In recent years, the scope of and possibilities for IS research have tremendously widened. Digital IT have become mainstream at the individual, organizational and societal levels (Burton-Jones et al. 2021). Digital IT is key to innovation in various domains from medicine to education, from psychology to the arts. Hence, these domains have become of interest and relevance to IS researchers, yet also overlap with other fields and are hence interdisciplinary in nature. These innovations are increasing the volume and variety of trace data available to researchers but necessitate a shift in our research practices (Johnson et al. 2019). Further, big data, machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI) technologies provide a plethora of powerful approaches for collecting and analysing data at a scale not possible before such that we might need to adapt our research methods and tools to make this data actionable and to generate novel knowledge. These ML technologies are being applied not only to theory testing but also to theory construction – in conjunction with or independent of qualitative methods (Miranda et al. 2022).</p>
    
    <p>This special issue focuses on the next generation of research methods to study IT – new methods relevant to the IS research field that account for a) the interdisciplinary nature and wider scope of IT phenomena, and/or b) the novel capacities afforded by new technologies/techniques (e.g., ML/AI). The way that novel technologies and techniques afford new possibilities is quite apparent in quantitative IS research. In contrast to &#39;first-generation&#39; regression-based approaches and &#39;second-generation&#39; structural equation modelling, a new generation of research methods including the predictive analytics (Shmueli and Koppius 2011), data mining (Smith 2020), ML (Shrestha et al. 2020) or explainable AI (Gunning et al. 2019) come with substantial new opportunities and challenges. For instance, these methods potentially allow for more fine-grained measurements and analyses to extend our knowledge of existing phenomena and may help us study novel phenomena including those that were, methodologically speaking, &#39;out of reach&#39; (George et al. 2016). These technological advancements enable us to progress our research toolkit and inform new ways of generating knowledge and theorizing (Burton-Jones et al. 2021; Shrestha et al. 2020). Increased recognition of abduction as a counterpart to deductive and inductive reasoning (Behfar and Okhuysen 2018; Sætre and Van de Ven 2021) pits concerns about practices such as HARKing (Kerr 1998) – hypothesizing after the results are known (aka p-hacking) – believed to lead to logically and scientifically flawed hypotheses, against concerns about stifling the advancement of knowledge (Pratt et al. 2019). ML/AI techniques are now so powerful that they can test millions of models on large data sets to find the &#39;best-matching&#39; model (of all possible) for what needs to be explained. This is a fundamental gear change in what can be done with quantitative data sets, the promise and validity of which are hotly debated (Kitchin 2014; Smith 2020).</p>
    
    <p>In terms of changes to the nature of the IS domains, qualitative-interpretative researchers seek to find new methods suitable for the wider, interdisciplinary scope of IS research. This is done via finding or developing analytical new grounds and looking at digital IT differently (e.g. via sociomaterial or affordances perspectives), seeking additional foundations in other fields (e.g., Zuboff’s (2015) political economy informed analysis of surveillance capitalism and &#39;Big Tech&#39;) or via the modification of methods to suit digital environments (e.g., virtual ethnographies or computational grounded theory). Other forms of qualitative research such as meta-synthesis, qualitative comparative analysis and discourse analysis also seem promising and relevant but are seldomly used in IS research. Digital IT (e.g., social media, digital platforms, AI/ML) has increasing and substantial impacts on society (e.g., mental health, trust in science, misinformation and polarization, monopolization and industry disruption). Hence, ethical, critical, value-based and political-economy questions are increasingly and necessarily asked about digital IT. Similarly, today’s pace of innovation may also warrant novel approaches to engaged scholarship and design science. For instance, researchers are calling for methods that can accumulate and update evidence more effectively (Lacity et al. 2021) and better ensure the generalizability of prescriptive knowledge (Brendel et al. 2021; Iivari et al. 2021).</p>
    
    <p>This special issue invites contributions that propose, introduce, debate or critique novel quantitative, qualitative or design-oriented methods research, with a focus on the &#39;how&#39; (i.e., origins, processes, steps of the method) and the &#39;why&#39; (e.g., &#39;rigour vs relevance&#39; and &#39;it is new, but is it better&#39; questions) these approaches should be used in IS research. The goal of the special issue is to provide a space for introducing and discussing innovative &#39;next-generation&#39; methods for studying IT-related phenomena, relative to the IS research field.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Critical reflection of research methods used in IS.</li>
        
        <li>Introducing new qualitative, quantitative or design research methods.</li>
        
        <li>Transferability of non-IS research methods such as from other fields or praxis.</li>
        
        <li>Novel combinations of research methods such as cross-disciplinary or mixed-method approaches.</li>
        
        <li>Innovative approaches to analyze big data.</li>
        
        <li>Approaches dealing with special types of unstructured data.</li>
        
        <li>Problems of null hypothesis testing via big data and AI/ML.</li>
        
        <li>AI, ML and explainable AI for knowledge creation and theory generation.</li>
        
        <li>Transparent, robust and replicable research designs and methodologies.</li>
        
        <li>Transferability and generalizability of insights generated with specific methods.</li>
        
        <li>Approaches to evaluating and communicating practical relevance of findings.</li>
        
        <li>Critical assessment of novel approaches on practical, conceptual, ethical or philosophical grounds.</li>
        
        <li>Philosophy of science-based proposals for or critiques of methods.</li>
        
        <li>Culture and values-driven proposals for or critiques of methods.</li>
        
        <li>Methods to study the past, the present and/or the future.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 20, 2022: Abstract submissions: (optional; authors are invited to submit extended abstracts of papers for early reactions)</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2023: First-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2023: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2023: Second-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>February 15, 2024: Second-round decisions: (papers are either acceptable with minor changes or rejected at this stage)</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2024: Final versions due: (final decisions and online publication soon afterwards)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Decentralised Information Systems: New Thinking and New Paradigms]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-decentralised-information-systems-new-thinking-and-new-paradigms</link>
            <guid>jit-decentralised-information-systems-new-thinking-and-new-paradigms</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:26:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Ali Sunyaev</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mary Lacity</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Michel Avital</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue seeks to explore and extend the conceptualisation, design, development, implementation and governance of contemporary “decentralised” information systems. “Decentralised” information systems are often seen as an important anti-thesis to “centralised” such systems. Modern societies and economies rely more highly on data, information systems, and technologies than ever. Pioneering organisations brought forth major milestones in developing and providing information technologies (e.g., TCP/IP and the Internet). However, with the significance of information technology increasing over the past decades, a small number of organisations have emerged as “tech giants” (e.g., Alphabet/Google or Meta/Facebook). Those organisations offer digital services and infrastructures for data processing that gained large-scale adoption by individuals, organisations, governments and society at large. As a result, societies, economies and technical systems became strongly dependent on services from a handful of organisations. The increase of the resulting dependencies leads to a centralisation of information systems. Highly-centralised information systems can result in global organisations and central social actors that abuse their power and pursue their own interests at the expense of others (e.g., by manipulation), exclude participation from social actors who disagree with them (e.g., by censorship) or invade their privacy through monitoring (e.g., by tracking actions of individuals on the internet). Highly-centralised information systems can also pose several further risks. For example, governance rights – such as rights of access, validation, software updates, data policies, and data overrides – may be centralised with few social actors in control. From a technical perspective, successful attacks on and crashes of central computing devices for network message propagation can interrupt communication in computing systems and even bring about system failures.</p>
    
    <p>To avert risks of over-centralization, the purposeful decentralisation of information systems has become a prominent topic of public discourse, for example, around Internet search, cloud computing, social media and financial systems. An information system’s degree of decentralisation refers to the degree to which the information system is independent of central actors and technical constructs. Several attempts have been made to design decentralised information systems to improve collaboration between actors while reducing dependencies on central authorities. Such endeavours include the development of decentralised token economies based on distributed ledger technology, decentralised identity management systems and distributed collaborative machine learning systems (e.g., federated learning systems). Although information systems decentralisation may resolve several of the above issues of over-centralisation, it also comes with its own challenges. For example, maintaining decentralised information systems can become difficult when multiple social actors need to update their technical components independently. Extensive data replication across technical components in decentralised information systems (e.g., in blockchain systems) can facilitate detecting and exploiting software vulnerabilities. If too many social actors have opposing ideas, decentralised governance risks never reaching an agreement. When only a few social actors participate in governance, information systems envisioned to be decentralised may de facto centralise.</p>
    
    <p>To purposefully achieve the benefits of information system decentralisation, we need to consider both the design of information systems as such and the behaviour of the social actors involved. Information systems decentralisation is driven by interdependent economic, political, social and technical factors. As an example of technical factors, the innovation of blockchain technology supports the decentralisation of asset ownership management. Changes to corporate information system designs, corporate ecosystems, and regulatory refinements are required to facilitate the development and adoption of such technical innovations. Such changes can lead to the centralisation of information systems in other aspects, such as their organisational structures. The entanglement of interdisciplinary factors tightly makes information systems decentralisation an interdisciplinary topic, relevant to several research fields, including computer science, organisational studies and information systems. The interdependence between information system designs and the influence of interdisciplinary factors makes the purposeful decentralisation of information systems an important yet complex undertaking that this special issue seeks new knowledge about.</p>
    
    <p>The complexity of information system decentralisation leads to various open questions, such as “how to achieve and sustain appropriate degrees of decentralisation of information systems so that individuals, organisations, and entire business ecosystems can benefit”, “how decentralised enterprise information systems need to be designed”, and “what technical know-how and involvement is required from actors to decentralise information systems appropriately”? This special issue seeks to improve the understanding of how the various factors affect the decentralisation of information systems used in business and other societal contexts, how different degrees of decentralisation of such information systems emerge over time, and how different degrees of decentralisation of information systems can affect business ecosystems, business processes, and societies overall. We invite applied, empirical, and theoretical research works that investigate information system decentralisation in a way that acknowledges its interdisciplinary nature and significantly contributes to understanding information system decentralisation, its manifestations, antecedents, and its impact on individuals and organisations, ecosystems and societies. We welcome and encourage submissions from researchers using diverse epistemological and methodological approaches. The manuscripts will be evaluated for the interestingness and novelty of their contributions.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Decentralised information systems for enterprises (e.g., information systems design and implementation for enterprises)</li>
        
        <li>Decentralised organisations and information systems decentralisation, including decentralised autonomous organizations (DAOs), decentralised platforms, token-driven governance and work practices</li>
        
        <li>Asset monetisation and similar information systems decentralisation, including web3, non-fungible tokens (NFTs) and digital assets</li>
        
        <li>Consumer privacy and information systems decentralisation, including self-sovereignty vs. self-responsibility</li>
        
        <li>The token economy, including tokenomics business models, effects of regulation and standardisation on decentralised token economies</li>
        
        <li>Digital resilience and information systems decentralisation, including critical information infrastructures</li>
        
        <li>Information systems decentralisation for the public good and social benefit, including decentralised voting, decentralised universal basic income (UBI) schemes and support of the decentralised supply of green energy by information systems</li>
        
        <li>Financial information systems decentralisation, including cryptocurrencies and community coins</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>January 15, 2024: Manuscript submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>April 19, 2024: First round reviews and decisions</li>
        
        <li>August 30, 2024: Second round (revision) submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>November 29, 2024: Second round reviews and decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 7, 2025: Final submission deadline for accepted manuscripts (subject to minor revisions)</li>
        
        <li>May 9, 2025: Final approval of manuscripts</li>
        
        <li>March 31, 2026: Online publication of special issue (anticipated date)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Roman Beck</strong>, IT University of Copenhagen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Erran Carmel</strong>, American University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada</li>
        
        <li><strong>Klitos Christodoulou</strong>, University of Nicosia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Raffaele Ciriello</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gilbert Fridgen</strong>, University of Luxembourg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rob Gleasure</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Robert Wayne Gregory</strong>, University of Miami Herbert Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hanna Halaburda</strong>, New York University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Niclas Kannengiesser</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Johann Kranz</strong>, Ludwig-Maximilians-University Munich</li>
        
        <li><strong>George Kuk</strong>, Nottingham Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gerhard Schwabe</strong>, University of Zurich</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carsten Sørensen</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alfred Taudes</strong>, Vienna University of Economics and Business</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jason Bennett Thatcher</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nils Urbach</strong>, Universität Bayreuth</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wenqian Wang</strong>, Perdue</li>
        
        <li><strong>Edgar Whitley</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Theory and Practice of Informational Transitions]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jasist-the-theory-and-practice-of-informational-transitions</link>
            <guid>jasist-the-theory-and-practice-of-informational-transitions</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:25:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Jenny Bronstein</strong>, Bar-Ilan University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Alison Hicks</strong>, University College London</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jette Hyldegård</strong>, University of Copenhagen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Pam McKenzie</strong>, The University of Western Ontario</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ian Ruthven</strong>, University of Strathclyde</p>
        
        <p><strong>Gunilla Widén</strong>, Åbo Akademi</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Life transitions forms a rich area of scholarship for Information Science research. The last five years have seen a steady growth in the publication of empirical studies related to transition, including PhD work and longitudinal studies, in a variety of areas including health, social, academic and employment contexts. At the same time, emerging conceptual work has also started to re-examine transition through a historical lens, including how change and adjustment has been treated in historical Information Science scholarship. This adds significant scope for complex conceptual work. The breadth of interest further means that transition has the potential to unify various related fields of study, including information behaviour, practice, and literacy research as well as various disciplinary fields. This Special Issue will provide a platform for the exploration of life transitions from an information behaviour, information practice, or information literacy perspective.</p>
    
    <p>Transitions are a natural state in everyday life. In a broader sense, individuals could be said to be in a constant state of transition, or &#39;transitioning&#39; with every passage in life. According to the Oxford English Dictionary, transition is defined both as a noun and adverb: &#39;A passing or passage from one condition, action, or (rarely) place, to another; change&#39; and, &#39;To make or undergo a transition (from one state, system, etc. to or into another); to change over or switch.&#39; From a research perspective, transition is a complex topic that has been variously conceptualised and defined. Transitions can be personal (changes due to changes in life cycle), situational (changes in circumstances in personal or professional life), or environmental (changes in the organisational environment impacting individuals). These emphases mean that transition has been most comprehensively explored to date within the field of Education and Nursing.</p>
    
    <p>Conceptual work in these areas has focused on the process through which people in transition move beyond a disrupted reality to construct a new reality. Information has been found to be a strong trigger in the transition process. Transitions fracture the individual’s information landscapes and require them to learn new &#39;ways of knowing&#39;, a process that often requires both seeking and avoiding information as a coping mechanism to reduce uncertainty.</p>
    
    <p>Although transitions are permeated with information practices of many kinds, information behaviour/practices/literacy research has engaged only peripherally with ideas of transition and the concept remains underexplored. Consequently, the aim of this special issue is to extend these initial explorations of transition through an information lens. We invite empirical, conceptual or methodological submissions for this special issue that address one or more of these questions:</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>How should transition be conceptualised, studied, evaluated within the field of information behaviour, information practice or information literacy?</li>
        
        <li>What is the role of information and information activities, including information avoidance, in a transition?</li>
        
        <li>What models, theories and concepts from Information Science and beyond are useful for studying transitions?</li>
        
        <li>What research methods/methodologies can we use to study transition?</li>
        
        <li>What types of life transitions exist and how can they be conceptualised in information behaviour, information practice or information literacy?</li>
        
        <li>What informational strategies might support transitions?</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>September 13, 2023: Paper development workshop</li>
        
        <li>June 13, 2024: Submissions due</li>
        
        <li>September 11, 2024: Decisions after first round of reviews</li>
        
        <li>November 1, 2025: Special Issue to be published</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology (JASIST)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Re-orientating Search Engine Research in Information Science]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jasist-re-orientating-search-engine-research-in-information-science</link>
            <guid>jasist-re-orientating-search-engine-research-in-information-science</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:24:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Dirk Lewandowski</strong>, Hamburg University of Applied Sciences</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jutta Haider</strong>, Swedish School of Library and Information Science, University of Borås</p>
        
        <p><strong>Olof Sundin</strong>, Department of Arts and Cultural Sciences, Lund University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>General web search engines are an essential part of today&#39;s information infrastructure. They have made it possible to find almost anything on the Internet by typing a few keywords into an empty search box. In fact, search engines have become so integrated into devices and practices that you can get an answer before you even knew how to phrase the question. Search engines shape our lives and at the same time shape the society and culture we live in. We use them at work, in school, in research, in planning our vacations, in finding products, and in politics – just to name a few important areas.</p>
    
    <p>The search engine market is dominated by a few companies that have divided the market into regions: Baidu in China, Yandex in Russia and Google in much of the Western world. More competition between search engines is often called for, but is very difficult to achieve. On the other side, we find the content providers doing everything they can by employing various types of search engine optimization (SEO) to achieve the highest rank in the search engine results page when people search for information.</p>
    
    <p>In information science, search engines have been studied mainly in the subfield of information retrieval and information behaviour. The study of search engines has thus been a core task of information science since the discipline&#39;s beginnings in the 1960s and even before (Saracevic, 2009). With concepts such as relevance or precision and recall, the evaluation of effectiveness has often been the focus of research.</p>
    
    <p>While general web search engines play an extremely important role in today&#39;s information infrastructure - economically, culturally, politically, technically, etc. - and have become an integral part of daily life at many levels, information science has only partially embraced the role of general web search engines in society. Research is fragmented into different subfields of information science and these fields do not always communicate well with each other.</p>
    
    <p>In this special issue, we call on information science researchers to join us in the investigation of general web search engines, also from outside Information Retrieval. Why information science? Information science can look back on a long and rich tradition of studying search and search systems. Relevance, one of the most central concepts for even contemporary search engines, has its origin in the field (Saracevic, 1975). Still, there are some blind spots, especially what role different types of relevance play when it comes to search engines (cf. Sundin, Lewandowski &amp; Haider, 2021).</p>
    
    <p>These search engines index a plethora of content and have a very low quality threshold when it comes to including documents in their indexes. Therefore, ranking results in a way that benefits users and at the same time provides societal relevance is paramount. From a technical viewpoint, information retrieval research has contributed to search engines by developing indexing methods (e.g., Sparck Jones, 1972) and ranking algorithms, with link-based algorithms being based on central ideas from information science, namely citation analysis (Garfield, 1979).</p>
    
    <p>Evaluation campaigns such as TREC (Haarman &amp; Voorhees, 2006) and CLEF (Ferro &amp; Peters, 2019) have developed solid methods and procedures to thoroughly test search engines. On the user side, information science research has contributed to the development and understanding of search engines through developing information-seeking models (e.g., Bates, 1989; Kuhlthau, 2003; Belkin, Oddy &amp; Brooks, 1982) that are used in system development (White, 2016).</p>
    
    <p>Information behaviour research has also produced a large body of empirical work on people&#39;s behaviour when looking for and using information. Information science, with its rich tradition of studying these topics, provides a good starting point for investigating today&#39;s search engines (Haider &amp; Sundin, 2019; Lewandowski, Sünkler &amp; Schultheiß, 2020; Lewandowski et al., 2021). As the field is interdisciplinary, it can also can serve as a hub for integrating research from other fields.</p>
    
    <p>Search engines and their use (search) are studied in different disciplines and from different theoretical perspectives. In addition to information science, information studies, and LIS, the topic has been addressed in disciplines as diverse as science and technology studies (STS), media and communication studies, political science, economics, education, psychology, HCI, or informatics, to name a few. Media-centred and device-centered research exists alongside people-centred studies and research that focuses on society, economics, or politics.</p>
    
    <p>While some focus on search engine use in general (e.g., Halavais 2018), others examine specific commercial search engines such as Google (e.g., Hillis et al. 2012), as well as Yandex, Baidu, or various regional services (e.g., Zavadski &amp; Toepfl 2019). Some studies focus on specific groups such as teenagers (e.g., Andersson 2017) or the elderly (Sanchiz et al. 2017), settings, or professions (e.g., Gudmundsdottir and Hartlevik 2020), and others focus on search engine use in relation to other platforms such as social media (e.g., Delmastro &amp; Splendore 2021).</p>
    
    <p>More recently, with the emergence of critical algorithm studies and critical AI, the focus has been on the various ways in which Google in particular may be implicated in society&#39;s information disorders and problems with misinformation and algorithmic biases that reinforce prejudice and injustice (e.g., Noble, 2018; Puschmann 2019). Another angle has been the central role of Google in capitalism (Bilić 2018; Mager, 2012), while others have examined the role of commercial search engines in reinforcing confirmation biases, partisanship, or hostile media effects (e.g., Tripodi 2018).</p>
    
    <p>Although search engines have been studied from many different angles and for a relatively long time, the field is extremely scattered. Not only is there little awareness of each other&#39;s work across disciplines, but even across subfields there are few connections. Different disciplinary investigations run in parallel and rarely meet in a productive way. Furthermore, the more commercial search engines fade into the background, the more difficult it becomes to perceive and study them. Moreover, their functioning is largely opaque and beyond the control of society, which in many cases means that the data available for research remains speculative. This may require creative approaches to data collection and methodology, as well as research designs that are open to new influences and experimental tactics.</p>
    
    <p>This Call for Papers is based on the premise that different approaches need to benefit from each other. We are looking for contributions that broaden the respective disciplinary, methodological, or empirical perspectives to identify and explore commercial search engines and their use and role in society from new angles, or that bring together different approaches in original ways. In particular, we would like to encourage information science/information studies, broadly understood, to reposition themselves and contribute the discipline&#39;s expertise to shed light on the ever more powerful role of commercial search engines in almost all areas of society and everyday life, influencing not only how we know and what we know, but increasingly also how knowledge and information are created and communicated, to begin with. The guest-editors welcome papers representing a variety of approaches. Papers can be theoretical, conceptual or empirical or combinations thereof.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Social and cultural aspects of relevance</li>
        
        <li>Epistemic implications of search-engine use</li>
        
        <li>Search engine bias (e.g., in terms of race, gender, class) and marginalization</li>
        
        <li>Fair search</li>
        
        <li>Search engine providers’ responsibility and accountability</li>
        
        <li>Search engines as multi-sided platforms</li>
        
        <li>History of web search and web search engines</li>
        
        <li>Ethical considerations related to search engines</li>
        
        <li>Affect and emotional aspects of search engine use</li>
        
        <li>Information literacy related to search engines</li>
        
        <li>Search engines and specific groups (children, elderly,...)</li>
        
        <li>Search engines and studies of ignorance and information avoidance</li>
        
        <li>Search engines in everyday life and in social practices</li>
        
        <li>Search engines in educational settings</li>
        
        <li>Alternative approaches to concepts of indexing in search engines</li>
        
        <li>Search engines and the role of data voids</li>
        
        <li>Negotiations of search results (search engine optimization, paid search advertising)</li>
        
        <li>Search engine comparisons (e.g., comparing results tailored to different locations, comparing results from different search engines)</li>
        
        <li>Methods for search engine research</li>
        
        <li>Data collection for search engine studies</li>
        
        <li>Approaches to &#39;opening the Black Box of search engine rankings&#39;</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 30, 2022: Submissions due</li>
        
        <li>February 28, 2023: Decision after first round of reviews</li>
        
        <li>September 1, 2023: Special Issue to be published</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology (JASIST)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Healthier Information Ecosystems]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jasist-healthier-information-ecosystems</link>
            <guid>jasist-healthier-information-ecosystems</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:23:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Josh Introne</strong>, Syracuse University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Charisse L’Pree Corsbie-Massay</strong>, Syracuse University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Brian McKernan</strong>, Syracuse University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Deana Rohlinger</strong>, Florida State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Olof Sundin</strong>, Lund University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Francesa Tripodi</strong>, UNC - Chapel Hill</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue, &quot;Healthier Information Ecosystems,&quot; will focus on the interconnected nature of online pathologies, draw attention to the socio-technical aspects of information technology, and animate interdisciplinary approaches to addressing these problems. Similar to Buckminster Fuller’s mission of “World Game,” we want to aid in developing a wide variety of solutions (including but not limited to technical, political, social, and educational) to the wicked problems of our time to make “the world work for 100% of humanity, in the shortest period of time… without ecological offense or the disadvantage of anyone.”</p>
    
    <p>We invite contributions that address the socio-cultural embeddedness of the problems plaguing information ecosystems and provide new ways of thinking about and strategies to achieve a healthier global information environment. We are actively seeking a broad approach to issues of healthier information ecosystems, including both theoretical and applied, qualitative and quantitative, as well as inside and outside the discipline of information science and technology.</p>
    
    <p>As Rong Tang (Tang et al., 2021) and colleagues mentioned in their 2021 JASIST piece, information science is experiencing a paradigm shift and the need to better understand the socio-technical side of information technology is central to this change. There is no shortage of research examining the pathological aspects of our modern information ecosystems, covering a broad spectrum of socio-technical phenomena including (but not limited to) misinformation, toxicity, polarization, and extremism. Together, these phenomena might be considered to be a sign of an “unhealthy” information ecosystem. However, our collective understanding of the problem remains fragmented and incomplete, impeding our ability to identify and implement successful solutions.</p>
    
    <p>For this special issue, we seek papers that take an interdisciplinary approach to expanding our understanding of information ecosystems by answering such vital questions as: What does it mean to live in an unhealthy information ecosystem, is it possible to envision a healthier one, and how do we get from here to there?</p>
    
    <p>Papers should speak to the information science community, but do so in an interdisciplinary manner that centers on the interplay of information, technology, and society. We are eager to receive contributions from disciplines that might lend new perspectives, including (but not limited to) statistical physics, complex systems, biology, environmental science, economics, management science, organization science, communication, psychology, anthropology, sociology, and philosophy. All contributions should clarify how they can be used to help our information ecosystems work for the betterment of society at large, developing an inclusive and thus “healthy” ecosystem.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Definitions of healthy ecosystems</li>
        
        <li>Ethical models for evaluating the health of online information ecosystems</li>
        
        <li>Multilevel metrics for evaluating the health of online information ecosystems</li>
        
        <li>Strategies for creating healthy ecosystems</li>
        
        <li>Design and collective human dynamics</li>
        
        <li>Disrupting systems of mis- and dis-information in politics and democracy, including national, state, and local politics</li>
        
        <li>Educational interventions</li>
        
        <li>Information as a social, political, economic, and cultural phenomenon</li>
        
        <li>Interdisciplinary perspectives and approaches to information and media</li>
        
        <li>The role of information ecosystems in conspiracy theories</li>
        
        <li>Interactions between online and offline decision making and behavior</li>
        
        <li>Information architecture, interface design and psychological biases of information consumers</li>
        
        <li>Engaging with systems of power; who is advantaged and who is disadvantaged from current or future systems</li>
        
        <li>Complex dynamics of information, social interaction and cognition</li>
        
        <li>Social dynamics and digital media ecosystems</li>
        
        <li>How policy, economic, and market forces shape algorithm design and development</li>
        
        <li>Big data, open science, and their socio-cultural impacts</li>
        
        <li>Hijacking of user-generated content and/or AI-generated content</li>
        
        <li>Mis- and dis-information transference during the COVID-19 pandemic</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>May 15, 2023: Deadline Extended for submissions</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2023: Decisions after first round of reviews</li>
        
        <li>January 1, 2024: Special Issue to be published</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology (JASIST)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Analytical Creativity]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isr</link>
            <guid>isr</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 12:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Min Ding</strong>, Penn State</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ram Gopal</strong>, University of Warwick</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ulrike Schultze</strong>, University of Groningen</p>
        
        <p><strong>D. J. Wu</strong>, Georgia Institute of Technology</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Creativity is typically defined as the capacity to produce something – either abstract or physical -- that is (1) new; and (2) valuable. Recent rapid advances in generative models such as GPT-4 by OpenAI, which is capable of generating unlimited new output (e.g., writing, image) that are arguably indistinguishable from human creative output, have surprised many. This new class of technology is also energizing the scholarly interest in creativity.</p>
    
    <p>Kaufman and Beghetto (2009) proposed a Four C model for creativity, mini-c (transformative learning), little-c (everyday creativity), Pro-c (professional expertise), and Big-C (eminent creative contributions). While human creativity has led to tremendous progress in science, technology, and society, the performance of creativity is nevertheless treated as a black box by both academics and practitioners. We know about environments and activities that are conducive to creative tasks – ranging from brainstorming to going for a run -- but we do not know precisely how human creativity works. This makes it challenging to enact it reliably and at scale.</p>
    
    <p>But algorithmic creativity performed by generative large language models such as Chat GPT and other AI applications is just as impenetrable. While these algorithms can produce exceptional new ideas and outputs (e.g., the Dreamcatcher chair), their designers (e.g., OpenAI) do not fully understand how these models work.</p>
    
    <p>Nevertheless, recent advances in neuroscience and computer science point to a form of creativity – namely analytical creativity – that can potentially yield creative outcomes in a replicable manner. Analytical creativity conceptualizes the creative task as a search problem whose purpose is to find the most desirable outcome, which is defined in terms of newness/originality and value, within a vast theoretical space, and to do so optimally (low search cost). Its goal is to uncover the process behind human or machine creativity. Using an analogy: the traditional conception of creativity is similar to a magician’s performance as viewed from the audience’s perspective. To the average viewer, the acts are beyond explanation and thus magical. But in reality, every magician’s performance is achieved by following a carefully designed recipe of action, which includes slights of hand that capitalize on human’s perceptual weaknesses.</p>
    
    <p>What if creativity is not so much a stroke of genius or ‘divine inspiration,’ but a rather mundane process that, once understood, can be automated? Evidence is mounting that this might indeed be the case. Using brain image and computational models, neuroscience provides a more structured understanding of how our brains process a creative task in a systematic way. Recent developments in deep learning research have led to interpretable models that can identify new game-playing strategies, generate visual art, and compose songs (e.g., large language models).</p>
    
    <p>Such deep learning models are beginning to unmask the complex steps involved in human creativity. For example, the process of how protein folds, which is a significant component of how the creative process is performed by the brain, has been broken down into 3D structures (Eisenstein 2021). Together with the research on neuroscience, this evidence has coalesced into a stream of creativity research that posits that the creative process shares commonality across domains, and that it can be learned, practiced, and performed with consistent results. Examples of this stream of research on analytical creativity include Altshuller’s (1984) theory of inventive problem solving (TRIZ) and Ding’s (2020) logical creativity theory.</p>
    
    <p>Analytical creativity is a more general concept than computational creativity, an emerging multidisciplinary domain that seeks to ‘model, simulate or replicate creativity using a computer, to achieve one of several ends: construct a program or computer capable of human-level creativity to better understand human creativity and to formulate an algorithmic perspective on creative behavior in humans; to design programs that can enhance human creativity without necessarily being creative themselves. This special issue seeks to encourage research that questions, evaluates, and advances analytical creativity. We welcome philosophical, theoretical, empirical, and design-science contributions. We encourage multi-disciplinary studies that integrate fields such as information systems, management/organization science, computer science, neuroscience, philosophy, and mathematics, as well as psychology and sociology.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Changing meanings/definitions of creativity</li>
        
        <li>Accountability of computer creativity</li>
        
        <li>Creativity as an (efficient) search problem</li>
        
        <li>Approaches to analytical creativity</li>
        
        <li>Human-Algorithm collaboration in creative tasks</li>
        
        <li>Human replicable artificial creative intelligence</li>
        
        <li>Role of neuroscience in creativity research</li>
        
        <li>Levels of analysis</li>
        
        <li>Institutional level creativity</li>
        
        <li>Application of creativity</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>January 2, 2024: Submissions will be accepted beginning</li>
        
        <li>February 29, 2024: Full Paper Submission</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2024: First Round of Editorial Decisions</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2024: Workshop at University of Warwick</li>
        
        <li>October 30, 2024: Revisions Due</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2025: Second Round of Editorial Decisions</li>
        
        <li>March 28, 2025: Final Revisions Due</li>
        
        <li>May 30, 2025: Final Editorial Decisions</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Yifan Dou</strong>, Fudan University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Fred Feinberg</strong>, University of Michigan</li>
        
        <li><strong>Guodong Gao</strong>, Johns Hopkins University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Natalia Levina</strong>, New York University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mingfeng Lin</strong>, Georgia Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aron Lindberg</strong>, Stevens Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Vincent Mak</strong>, University of Cambridge</li>
        
        <li><strong>Oded Netzer</strong>, Columbia University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Susan Scott</strong>, London School of Economics and Political Science</li>
        
        <li><strong>Inbal Yahav Shenberger</strong>, Tel Aviv University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anjana Susarla</strong>, Michigan State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Demetrios Vakratsas</strong>, McGill University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Harry Wang</strong>, University of Delaware</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lior Zalmanson</strong>, Tel Aviv University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Research (ISR)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Institutional Press in the Digital Age]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/misq-the-institutional-press-in-the-digital-age</link>
            <guid>misq-the-institutional-press-in-the-digital-age</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 05:15:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Ahmed Abbasi</strong>, University of Notre Dame</p>
        
        <p><strong>Brad N. Greenwood</strong>, George Mason University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Melissa Mazmanian</strong>, University of California, Irvine</p>
        
        <p><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Robert Seamans</strong>, New York University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Over the last 20 years, ongoing waves of digitalization have decimated the traditional business model of the news and fundamentally changed how the news, or more formally, the ‘institutional press’, works. Indeed, ever since reserved frequencies were gifted to television broadcasters in the 1950s, on the condition that they inform the public of current events, the subsidy underpinning newspapers and other forms of institutional media has slowly eroded. Like many other industries, the internet has accelerated this phenomenon. Not only has the hyper-targeted advertising facilitated by social media and other platforms functionally eroded the subsidy model to its breaking point; but the costless transmission of data facilitated by the internet has increased geographic scope of dominant players, permitting them to reach beyond their original markets and squeeze content producers across the globe. Against this backdrop, it is hard to overstate the importance of this &#39;crisis of the institutional press&#39;. The news provides our primary means for understanding the world around us. Societies desperately need a well-functioning institutional press to tackle the many societal, economic, and environmental challenges we all face.</p>
    
    <p>The first day of core courses usually begins with one of four motivating examples: the decline of incumbent sellers in favor of digital platforms, the increasing irrelevance of diseconomies of scale and the rise of digital monopolies, the rise of social media and user-generated content, or the decline of the newspaper industry. Yet, as these classes continue to discuss the opportunities firms have in the digital age and teach students to implement advanced analytics to more effectively mine business value from data, the decline of institutional media often fades into the background.</p>
    
    <p>This phenomenon-driven special issue is motivated by the view that our students, colleagues, and society urgently need a better understanding of the causes and consequences of the changing nature of news in the digital era and potential solutions going forward. The special issue takes an interdisciplinary perspective, bringing together insights from across the broader information, managerial, and organizational sciences.</p>
    
    <p>This failure to discuss the implications of the decline of institutional news media is troubling. Not only has the Fourth Estate historically served to counterbalance institutions with a monopoly on force and morality, it has been a cornerstone of democratic republics for centuries. These claims are not idle musings. News media outlets have been shown to influence many societal outcomes, from government agendas to public opinion to voting behavior. The Fourth Estate mediates the attention granted to social movements and can influence the strategic management of organizations. Institutional media can also prompt changes in corporate governance: it can shape the valuation of firms at IPO, influence firm founding, confer legitimacy on industries, and even elevate de novo technological innovations in the public consciousness.</p>
    
    <p>Yet, seismic changes have assaulted the free press as we understand it. The late 20th century witnessed an increasing concentration in ownership of news outlets, leading to elevated reliance on advertising revenue that biased content. The recent history of the institutional press is interwoven with the history of digital technology. Initially, the World Wide Web served largely as a vehicle for the dissemination of news produced by professional news organizations, extending their reach. In time, the ensuing competition for reader attention shifted the gatekeeping function from professional news organizations to online content curators. Contemporary media coverage became more selective and influenced by market actors. With the advent of social media, user-generated content further usurped the gatekeeping role of professional news organizations. Moreover, public subsidy for the Fourth Estate was undermined by social media, accelerating the control of dominant players on public discourse and hollowing the local publishing industry. At the same time, social media has afforded citizen journalists the ability to counter-balance the biases of professional news organizations.</p>
    
    <p>Even more recently, society has witnessed a demonstrable shift towards the &#39;post-truth era,&#39; in which populist, tribalist, and anti-&#39;mainstream media&#39; rhetoric proliferates. While the blockchain has been heralded as a way of remaking the institutional press in the digital era, we have little systematic understanding of its efficacy. All the while, the process of news construction and dissemination is being disrupted by algorithms, machine learning, and artificial intelligence. The long-term implications of these AI tools on the institutional press are unknown. Indeed, we are witnessing intersections of the evolutionary paths of technology and the institutional press in ways that are fundamentally changing the &#39;freedom of the press&#39; and the complex network that includes journalists, software engineers, relational databases, and social media platforms which form it; along with prevailing norms, values, and institutional logics of a particular sociotechnical moment.</p>
    
    <p>Research has only begun to address these changes. The purpose of this Special Issue is to address this gap in scholarship head on and to inform stakeholders about how changes in institutional media are affecting society at the intersection of business, technology, and public policy. To this end, we invite scholarship that helps academia and society comprehend the major changes taking place within the institutional press, why those changes are occurring, and what the consequences of those changes are; and work together toward a more positive future for the institutional press.</p>
    
    <p>We encourage an equally diverse breadth of scholars to submit their work to this special issue.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>The changing nature of the press, news media as an institution, and the consequences of those changes.</li>
        
        <li>The functioning of, and implications for, non-traditional digital era news sources.</li>
        
        <li>What constitutes news in the digital era?</li>
        
        <li>The interaction of social and institutional media.</li>
        
        <li>The role of professional standards and gatekeeping in today’s news media ecosystem and mechanisms to support them.</li>
        
        <li>Sociotechnical approaches to understanding the intersections and dependencies between technologies, institutional forces, values, and norms in relation to freedom of the press.</li>
        
        <li>Designing and assessing IT artifacts (e.g., generative AI, algorithms and computational methods, blockchain) towards an aspirational institutional press.</li>
        
        <li>The news as a dynamic construct across time and space, and the consequent implications for content generation and consumption.</li>
        
        <li>The news as a societal information system.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>April 30, 2024: Optional abstract submission due</li>
        
        <li>May 30, 2024: Optional abstract feedback via email</li>
        
        <li>August 5, 2024: Invited five-page abstract for AOM Workshop due</li>
        
        <li>August 9, 2024: Paper Development Workshop at AOM</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2024: Full Paper Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 15, 2025: First-round decisions expected</li>
        
        <li>May 30, 2025: Revision Plan Meeting with SI Editors</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2025: Second-round revisions due</li>
        
        <li>October 15, 2025: Second-round decisions expected</li>
        
        <li>February 15, 2026: Third- and final revisions submissions due</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2026: Final decisions expected</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Mike Annay</strong>, University of Southern California</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jens Foerderer</strong>, Technische Universität München</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anand Gopal</strong>, National Technical University of Singapore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Brent Kitchens</strong>, University of Virginia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gene Moo Lee</strong>, UBC Sauder School of Business</li>
        
        <li><strong>Attila Marton</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jeffrey Nickerson</strong>, Stevens Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Christopher Parker</strong>, American University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Caitlin Petre</strong>, Rutgers University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Christian Peukert</strong>, HEC Lausanne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aleš Popovič</strong>, NEOMA Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jui Ramaprasad</strong>, University of Maryland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Imke Reimers</strong>, Cornell University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jie Ren</strong>, Fordham University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gaurav Sabnis</strong>, Stevens Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ananya Sen</strong>, Carnegie Mellon University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jananki Srinivasan</strong>, IIIT-Bangalore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xiao Xiao</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yi Yang</strong>, HKUST</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nan Zhang</strong>, University of Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aljona Zorina</strong>, IESEG</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>MIS Quarterly (MISQ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ethical and DEI Implications of the Future of Work: The Role of Immersive Platforms]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jsis-ethical-and-dei-implications-of-the-future-of-work-the-role-of-immersive-platforms</link>
            <guid>jsis-ethical-and-dei-implications-of-the-future-of-work-the-role-of-immersive-platforms</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 12:38:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Sue Newell</strong>, Warwick Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Manju Ahuja</strong>, University of Louisville</p>
        
        <p><strong>Bob Galliers</strong>, Bentley University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>In this call for papers, we seek manuscripts that explore the future of work with respect to immersive platforms enabling innovative work practices and ask prospective authors specifically to consider the potential pitfalls (i.e., concerning ethics and DEI) of all this.</p>
    
    <p>In the spring of 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic triggered the operations of most companies worldwide to move online. The education systems along with several other services for citizens, including public administration, healthcare etc. followed suit. In a sense, the COVID-19 pandemic served as an unintended natural experiment, testing the extent to which current technologies are able to support remote/virtual interactions via immersive platforms. At the same time, the pandemic also exposed limitations of these arrangements, setting the groundwork for novel ways (and technologies) to promote further such interactions in the future.</p>
    
    <p>Overall, we welcome empirical, theoretical, review and perspective/position papers. While we are inclined to recommend that papers with empirical data are preferred, we understand that we are discussing a phenomenon in its becoming. Yet, papers with primary data or those that systematically analyze secondary data on organizations using novel technologies for remotization are strongly encouraged. JSIS is inclusive as to the use of methods of any kind. Qualitative, quantitative, archival/historical analyses, mixed method papers, and experiments are all welcome, as long as rigor leads the collection of data and its analysis. Importantly, conclusions, critical reflections and impacts should result. Strong theoretical contributions are required for empirical and theoretical papers. Perspective/position papers should also contribute to theory, by developing a research agenda, with implications for practice also being highlighted.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>People analytics in organizations, leveraging virtual realities with a focus on privacy/discriminations</li>
        
        <li>The present and future of telehealth with the support of immersive platforms</li>
        
        <li>The present and future of higher education with the support of immersive platforms</li>
        
        <li>Predictive policing using behavioral data stemming from immersive platforms</li>
        
        <li>Immersive platforms and academic conferences</li>
        
        <li>Laws and regulations landscape concerning DEI and immersive platforms (and challenges for companies)</li>
        
        <li>Immersive platforms and the environment</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>January 31, 2024: Submission of extended abstracts (~1,000 words including references)</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2024: Deadline for full papers submission</li>
        
        <li>November 15, 2024: Feedback to authors (reject, revisions)</li>
        
        <li>February 28, 2025: Resubmission deadline for paper granted a revision</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2025: Feedback to authors (reject, conditional acceptance)</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2025: Resubmission deadline for papers granted conditional acceptance (camera ready)</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2025: Accepted papers published online</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Anjana Susarla</strong>, Michigan State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, UNSW Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carolina Salge</strong>, University of Georgia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Cristina Alaimo</strong>, Luiss University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dubravka Cecez-Kecmanovic</strong>, UNSW Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ghiyoung Im</strong>, Louisville University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mareike Mohlmann</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maric Boudreau</strong>, University of Georgia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Martin Wiener</strong>, TU Dresden</li>
        
        <li><strong>Massimo Magni</strong>, Bocconi University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Romilla Syed</strong>, University of Massachusetts, Boston</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sepideh Ebrahimi</strong>, University of Waterloo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Silvia Masiero</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stella Pachidi</strong>, University of Cambridge</li>
        
        <li><strong>Virpi Kristiina Tuunainen</strong>, Aalto University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>The Journal of Strategic Information Systems (JSIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Sustainability and Information Systems Research: New challenges and theoretical perspectives]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-digital-sustainability-and-information-systems-research</link>
            <guid>jais-digital-sustainability-and-information-systems-research</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 12:54:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jacqueline Corbett</strong>, Université Laval</p>
        
        <p><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Monash University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Thomas Kude</strong>, University of Bamberg</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yenni Tim</strong>, University of New South Wales</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Sustainability is a moral and existential imperative of our time. As Information Systems (IS) scholars, we are aware of the immense impact of digital technologies on efforts and initiatives towards sustainable practice happening locally and globally. Furthermore, because digital phenomena lie at the heart of our discipline, IS researchers are well positioned to join these efforts. This Special Issue aims to champion new digital sustainability research programs targeting the planet’s most pressing sustainability challenges from the past decade. We hope it will contribute towards building novel collective knowledge and help shape digital sustainability research in IS.</p>
    
    <p>Human society is approaching the edge of a dangerous precipice. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change’s (IPCC) Sixth Assessment Report unequivocally confirms that human activities have caused global warming, predicting that even with current commitments and mitigation efforts, it will be difficult to limit warming below the critical threshold of 2 o C. The planet’s air, land, and water continue to be threatened on several fronts, with research suggesting that the safe operating zone for six of the nine planetary boundaries has already been breached. Over the past decade, extreme weather events such as droughts, floods, fires and heatwaves have not only increased in frequency but also in magnitude. In addition to causing environmental impacts, these events have a significant impact on society, further complicating the pursuit of social and economic sustainability.</p>
    
    <p>In 2020, about 724 million people were living in conditions of extreme poverty, with almost 30% of the world’s population suffering from some level of food insecurity. Equality for women and other marginalized groups continues to lag. The World Bank reports that 2.4 billion women globally do not have the same economic rights as men, and despite the adoption of the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples in 2007, Indigenous Peoples around the world continue to suffer the intergenerational trauma of colonization. The trend towards urbanization endures, with cities struggling to ensure inclusive, resilient, and sustainable living environments for all residents. On top of all these challenges, violent conflicts have led to the forced migration of millions of people and the deaths of thousands of civilians. These alarming circumstances highlight the lack of progress towards the United Nation’s Sustainable Development Goals.</p>
    
    <p>As argued in a recent JAIS editorial on digital sustainability, the IS research community has a strong foundation to draw upon, ranging from research into Green IS to studies addressing significant societal challenges. The poor cannot eat technology, but the mindful design and use of technology can contribute to innovative solutions and positive impacts. In particular, we consider that the recent shift in the way IS research approaches digital phenomena offers new perspectives on the relationship between digital technologies and sustainability. Building on a contention that the classical view of an information system as representing and reflecting physical reality has become obsolete, there exists an opportunity for the IS community to drive a more inclusive agenda on digital sustainability, one that encompasses phenomena in which the impact of digital technologies and macro-level environmental, social, and economic objectives converge.</p>
    
    <p>Accordingly, this Special Issue seeks contributions that delve into digital sustainability and encompass the development, deployment, and utilization of digital resources and artifacts toward improving the environment, society, and economic welfare.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Design and development considerations</li>
        
        <li>Research that investigates the processes, principles, resources or capabilities required for the design and development of digital sustainability artefacts</li>
        
        <li>Intervention-based research that engages directly in enhancing sustainability practices within organizations or communities through effective leveraging of digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>Studies examining how the different inter- and intra-organizational actors involved in digital sustainability projects engage and interact as they develop, deploy, and govern digital solutions for macro-level sustainability agenda</li>
        
        <li>Explorations of the relationships between digital objects and the physical reality they shape/create in the context of social and environmental sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Use considerations</li>
        
        <li>Research examining how digital technologies support key organizational activities in the management of macro-level sustainability challenges</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical and/or empirical investigations of the interplay between sustainability initiatives and other digital agendas</li>
        
        <li>Studies of ‘computed human experiences’ with respect to sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Research on the challenges and opportunities for reclaiming and rejuvenating Indigenous cultures and knowledge through decolonized digital artefacts</li>
        
        <li>Management and governance considerations</li>
        
        <li>Studies exploring the governance of digital sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Research on the role of different actors in the digital sustainability ecosystem</li>
        
        <li>Studies on the sustainability agenda at the community and societal levels</li>
        
        <li>Policy implications related to digital sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Outcomes and consequences</li>
        
        <li>Studies that incorporate multiple aspects of digital sustainability performance</li>
        
        <li>Case studies of real-world impacts of digital sustainability on vulnerable or marginalized communities</li>
        
        <li>Research investigating alternative ways of measuring progress toward long-term sustainability objectives</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>February 20, 2024: Online information session (we invite potential authors to send us specific questions to address during this session)</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2024: Deadline for paper submission</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2025: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>June 1, 2025: Deadline to submit revised papers</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2025: Second-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2026: Deadline to submit revised papers</li>
        
        <li>June 1, 2026: Provisional/Final decisions</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2026: Deadline to submit final paper (if minor revision is required)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Managing the Individual, Organizational, and Societal Challenges of Generative AI: Utopian, Dystopian, Neutropian Perspectives]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-managing-the-individual-organizational-and-societal-challenges-of-generative-ai-utopian-dystopian-neutropian-perspectives</link>
            <guid>jais-managing-the-individual-organizational-and-societal-challenges-of-generative-ai-utopian-dystopian-neutropian-perspectives</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 12:46:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Varun Grover</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Arpan Kumar Kar</strong>, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Sabherwal</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Spyros Angelopoulos</strong>, Durham University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Hartmut Hoehle</strong>, University of Mannheim</p>
        
        <p><strong>Anik Mukherjee</strong>, Indian Institute of Management</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The origins of generative AI (GAI) can be traced back to the 1950s, when Alan Turing proposed a test to determine whether a machine could be perceived as intelligent enough to generate responses to questions in a way indistinguishable from a human. Later, in the 1970s, researchers developed more advanced models capable of producing more realistic and coherent outcomes. Contemporary GAI models are based on state-of-the-art neural network architectures. They combine such architectures to develop large models that outperform existing benchmarked ones. Contemporary GAI solutions can produce large amounts of contextual outputs on any specific topic. They are highly trained and sophisticated, enabling users to produce various types of AI-generated content. Although GAI has been around for a while, recent developments have brought the potential of such solutions to the forefront. In particular, LLMs have the potential to transform the way we develop textual content and communicate with one another.</p>
    
    <p>The ongoing discourse on GAI seems to extol the promises of AI and the dangers. Our goal for this Special Issue is to offer a careful examination of the challenges faced in managing this powerful set of technologies for individuals, organizations, and society. Many of the challenges around GAI concern data. As per a Forbes report, over 90% of internet data will be produced by GAI models, triggering serious concerns about harmful and abusive content generation. Most current GAI-triggered use involves chat-based digital assistants. While the outcome of GAI in these digital assistant-based applications is indeed remarkable, their effectiveness depends on the level of task specificity and the need for information synthesis.</p>
    
    <p>At the individual level, a number of challenges exist on how to effectively use GAI to augment individual productivity. For instance, how can GAI-based interactions positively or negatively affect customer experiences, how can GAI augment (vs. replace) human skills, and broader questions of how over-reliance on GAI systems may adversely impact the cognitive inability of users and learners. At the organizational level, there are many challenges around governance. For instance, how can we govern the quality of content by GAI, how can the adoption of GAI lead to disruption, how do we set up appropriate governance structures to manage GAI projects, and how can we avoid unintended consequences of GAI adoption in firms? At the societal level, there are extensive challenges around misinformation, bias, and privacy. Our broad goal for the special issue is to attract papers that articulate the challenges theoretically and study them empirically, while making a strong contribution to the theory and practice in the deployment of GAI.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Challenges in managing GAI for individuals, organizations, and society</li>
        
        <li>Impact of GAI on individual productivity and customer experiences</li>
        
        <li>Governance challenges related to content quality generated by GAI</li>
        
        <li>Misinformation and privacy issues at the societal level</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>August 31, 2024: Article Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>November 30, 2024: First Review</li>
        
        <li>July 31, 2026: Article Final Decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Shahriar Akter</strong>, University of Wollongong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hillol Bala</strong>, Indiana University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kevin Bauer</strong>, University of Mannheim</li>
        
        <li><strong>Roberta Bernardi</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michael Chau</strong>, The University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alain Chong</strong>, University of Nottingham Ningbo China</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kieran Conboy</strong>, National University of Ireland Galway</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yogesh Dwivedi</strong>, Swansea University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Amany Elbanna</strong>, Royal Holloway University of London</li>
        
        <li><strong>Weiguo (Patrick) Fan</strong>, University of Iowa</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sumeet Gupta</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Raipur</li>
        
        <li><strong>Karlheinz Kautz</strong>, RMIT University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stan Karaniosis</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yeongin Kim</strong>, Virginia Commonwealth</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ajay Kumar</strong>, EM Lyon</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marijn Janssen</strong>, TU Delft</li>
        
        <li><strong>Agam Gupta</strong>, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shivam Gupta</strong>, NEOMA Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Taha Havakhor</strong>, McGill University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mary Lacity</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xin (Robert) Luo</strong>, University of New Mexico</li>
        
        <li><strong>Patrick Mikalef</strong>, Norwegian University of Science &amp; Tech</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ilias O Pappas</strong>, University of Agder</li>
        
        <li><strong>Uthaysankar Sivarajah</strong>, University of Bradford</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kai Spohrer</strong>, Frankfurt School of Finance and Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sujeet Sharma</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Nagpur</li>
        
        <li><strong>Samuel Fosso Wamba</strong>, Toulouse Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Amber Young</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Health Analytics and IS Theorizing]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-health-analytics-and-theorizing</link>
            <guid>jais-health-analytics-and-theorizing</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 12:50:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Aaron Baird</strong>, Georgia State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yusen Xia</strong>, Georgia State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Kohli</strong>, William &amp; Mary</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The objective of this special issue is to showcase how health analytics can be used to enhance theorizing in the field of IS. In addition to its contribution to deep analysis, the power of health analytics research lies in theory development that leverages the unique context of health care. Specifically, the special issue aims to foster research that addresses the question: How can the application and design of analytics methods identify insights from health data and extend IS theory?</p>
    
    <p>This special issue places analytics at the forefront of IS research so that health care researchers can make a theoretical contribution to IS research. Through this special issue, we hope to provide an opportunity for emerging and innovative health analytics research to be published that will showcase how new forms and combinations of theoretical reasoning, methods, and data can contribute to theory building. Our hope is that this special issue will contribute to deeper descriptions, explanations, and predictions of emerging health phenomena relevant to IS scholars as well as demonstrate to clinicians and patients opportunities that will enrich health care management and delivery. We welcome research at the intersection of traditional and emerging approaches, exploratory research, phenomenon-based research, novel methods, and data from any relevant source (with IRB approval, as needed). While we are open to discoveries of all kinds, we expect application of rigorous methods, presentation of persuasive reasoning, and inclusion of strong evidence.</p>
    
    <p>Health analytics can be generally described as generating insights from health data through analysis. Significant and impactful work in health analytics is emerging in the IS literature, but there are also significant opportunities to leverage health analytics research to contribute to theorizing in IS. For instance, while interesting findings within IS have been presented in the context of health analytics use in hospitals and clinical diagnostics or care, many health analytics research contexts have yet to be exploited in IS research. The diversity of data and contexts within which to conduct health analytics research is substantial and such diversity is currently underrepresented in IS journals. We propose that health analytics research can advance beyond presentation of context specific models and methods. We see considerable promise in applying such innovative approaches to the enhancement of IS theory, particularly in explaining IS-enabled mechanisms, through research conducted in the health analytics context.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Heterogenous treatment effects in areas such as health care performance, social determinants of health, use of patient generated health data, and offering or pricing of health care, pharmaceutical, medical device, or insurance products.</li>
        
        <li>AI/ML based tools that can reduce information asymmetry, improve decision-making, or optimize information flows.</li>
        
        <li>Unstructured data analysis, such as of digital trace data, images, or user-generated content, that yields insights about topical or trend dynamics.</li>
        
        <li>Impact of, or disparities in, health analytic capabilities or investments by hospitals, clinics, or less frequently considered entities such as laboratories, pharmacies, medical device manufacturers, public health agencies, or charitable organizations.</li>
        
        <li>Integration of personal device data to analyze trends, identify public health issues, and efficacy of treatments.</li>
        
        <li>Any interesting or creative area we have yet to research in-depth in IS, such as topics in genomics, signal processing/telemetry, clinical trials, or epidemiology.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>February 1, 2023: Extended abstract submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2023: Extended abstract decision</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2023: 1st round full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2023: 1st round full paper decision</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2024: 2nd round full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2024: 2nd round full paper decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Corey Angst</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hilal Atasoy</strong>, Rutgers University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sezgin Ayabakan</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ofir Ben Assuli</strong>, Tel Aviv University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sangeeta Shah Bharadwaj</strong>, Management Development Institute</li>
        
        <li><strong>Langtao Chen</strong>, Missouri University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yichen Cheng</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anton Ivanov</strong>, University of Illinois</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juhee Kwon</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nakyung Kyung</strong>, National University of Singapore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Oklahoma</li>
        
        <li><strong>Abhay Mishra</strong>, Iowa State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sunil Mithas</strong>, University of South Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Min-Seok Pang</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sujeet Sharma</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Tiruchirappalli</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sriram Somanchi</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Junbo Son</strong>, University of Delaware</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ankita Srivastava</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Monica Tremblay</strong>, William &amp; Mary</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hongyi Zhu</strong>, The University of Texas at San Antonio</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Registered Reports]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/misq-registered-reports</link>
            <guid>misq-registered-reports</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 05:15:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Shuk Ying Ho</strong>, Australian National University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jan Recker</strong>, University of Hamburg</p>
        
        <p><strong>Chee-Wee Tan</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Anthony Vance</strong>, Virginia Tech</p>
        
        <p><strong>Han Zhang</strong>, Georgia Tech</p>
        
    
    
    <p>An irony of science is that, despite our devotion to evidence, there is little evidence underpinning many aspects of the journal review process. As part of our commitment to continually improving our review processes at MIS Quarterly, this special issue aims to obtain evidence regarding the merits of a recent innovation in the review process—registered reports.</p>
    
    <p>While the registered report model is relatively new, it has been adopted by over 200 journals across the sciences. Business and Information Systems Engineering was the first (and so far, lone) IS journal to adopt this model. Other early adopters across the business fields include Journal of Accounting Research, Academy of Management Discoveries, and Leadership Quarterly.</p>
    
    <p>Our goal in this special issue is to learn if the registered report model should be available as an ongoing model for MISQ, as a supplement to our existing options. While we see a lot of promise in the model, we plan to test it first to learn if/how it can best suit our journal.</p>
    
    <p>The registered report model involves a 2-stage ‘acceptance’ process: a conditional acceptance before data collection, followed by an acceptance if the authors follow the agreed plan. Compared to a normal review process, there are two main differences: Pre/pilot data may (or may not) have been collected before conditional acceptance, but the main data will not have been collected prior to the conditional acceptance being offered. The paper cannot be rejected due to its results.</p>
    
    <p>Early tests of the registered report model across the sciences are yielding positive results, especially on the dimensions of bias reduction and investment motivation.</p>
    
    <p>Submissions to this special issue will be reviewed in a three-step process focusing on different criteria. Step 1 involves examining the submission proposals for suitability. Step 2 is the Stage 1 Review based on criteria for conditional acceptance. Step 3 is the Stage 2 Review based on criteria for final acceptance, where the actual results will be considered but will not affect acceptance as long as the agreed processes were followed.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Registered report model</li>
        
        <li>Evidence in journal review process</li>
        
        <li>Bias reduction in peer review</li>
        
        <li>Investment motivation in research</li>
        
        <li>Hypothesized models and empirical testing in IS research</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Invalid DateTime: Stage 2 submissions due within 9 months of Stage 1 decision</li>
        
        <li>Invalid DateTime: Special Issue Publication, Editorial, and Showcase Event</li>
        
        <li>February 20, 2023: Introductory workshop (optional)</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2023: Proposal Deadline</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2023: Stage 1 Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2023: Stage 1 initial decisions expected</li>
        
        <li>January 1, 2024: Special Issue workshop for Stage 1 authors</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2024: Stage 1 submissions must receive a conditional acceptance no later than this date</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>MIS Quarterly (MISQ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Blockchain Technology and Applications]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/dss-blockchain-technology-and-applications</link>
            <guid>dss-blockchain-technology-and-applications</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 06:37:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Shaokun Fan</strong>, Oregon State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Noyan Ilk</strong>, Florida State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Akhil Kumar</strong>, Penn State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>J. Leon Zhao</strong>, Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shenzhen</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Blockchain technology has received enormous attention since Bitcoin was launched in 2009 and has become the frontier of technology advancements and application innovations in recent years. In particular, blockchain is now recognized as a critical part of the new ABCD of modern technology, that is, Artificial intelligence, Blockchain, Cloud computing, and big Data. However, many research challenges and opportunities remain to be tackled and surmounted in areas such as blockchain infrastructure decentralization, blockchain network governance, blockchain security and privacy, and the nature of machine trust in blockchain-based systems. Because blockchain is an integral part of automated business processes, the implementation of this technology can vary greatly between organizations across different industries.</p>
    
    <p>The aim of this special issue is to highlight novel and high-quality research in blockchain technology and applications, and to examine the current and future impact of blockchain systems, and related technologies including data verification before block confirmation, authentication of data ownership, and dataflow across blockchain systems. Considering the decision-making focus of DSS publications that bridge the gap between managerial and technical perspectives, this special issue is open to all manuscripts that make a significant research contribution to blockchain systems and applications in business sectors such as finance, insurance, healthcare, manufacturing, supply chain, education, and government.</p>
    
    <p>In terms of research paradigm, we invite manuscripts with system-based implications that draw on various analytical, empirical, and technical methodologies including, but not limited to, system development, econometrics, decision theory, operations management, experimentation, and engineering. We strongly encourage submissions that follow a design science research perspective, which aims to develop cutting-edge IT artifacts. That is, all technical and quantitative research methods that are helpful in tackling real-world challenges confronted by managers, engineers, and researchers via blockchain technology are welcome.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Process-aware blockchain design and management</li>
        
        <li>Blockchain applications in metaverse platforms</li>
        
        <li>Design and implementation issues in the transition from PoW to PoS</li>
        
        <li>Data management issues on the blockchain</li>
        
        <li>Security and privacy issues on the blockchain</li>
        
        <li>Design and implementation issues of Metaverse systems</li>
        
        <li>Integration of blockchain into existing business infrastructure</li>
        
        <li>Modeling, design and implementation of trust mechanisms in blockchain-based systems</li>
        
        <li>New and faster consensus algorithms for blockchain implementation</li>
        
        <li>NFT analysis and design paradigms in various business sectors</li>
        
        <li>Blockchain-based NFT casting models and mechanisms</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>October 15, 2022: Submissions System opens</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2023: Paper Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>January 30, 2023: Initial Screening of Submissions</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2023: First Review Decisions</li>
        
        <li>June 30, 2023: Revision Due</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2023: Acceptance Decisions</li>
        
        <li>November 15, 2023: Final Manuscript Due</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Michael Adams</strong>, Queensland University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Arthur Carvalho</strong>, Miami University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Daning Hu</strong>, South University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Qiqi Jiang</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jiewu Leng</strong>, Guangdong University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rong Liu</strong>, Stevens Institute</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xin Luo</strong>, The University of New Mexico</li>
        
        <li><strong>Chih-Hung Peng</strong>, National Chengchi University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zhe Shan</strong>, Miami University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hemang Subramanian</strong>, Florida International University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yinliang Tan</strong>, University of Houston</li>
        
        <li><strong>Chih-Ping Wei</strong>, National Taiwan University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ling Xue</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wenping Zhang</strong>, Remin University of China</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xi Zhao</strong>, Xi&#39;an Jiaotong University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Decision Support Systems (DSS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Responsibility: Social, Ethical, and Ecological Implications of IS]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-digital-responsibility-social-ethical-and-ecological-implications-of-is</link>
            <guid>jais-digital-responsibility-social-ethical-and-ecological-implications-of-is</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 06:37:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Jan Recker</strong>, Universität Hamburg</p>
        
        <p><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Janina Sundermeier</strong>, Freie Universität Berlin</p>
        
        <p><strong>Monideepa Tarafdar</strong>, University of Massachusetts Amherst</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Pervasive digitalization has influenced practically all aspects of the human experience and our institutions in business, society, and government. Diverse areas such as organizational management and strategy, urban affairs and city planning, healthcare, entertainment, safety, politics, and transportation have all been inexorably shaped by digital technologies. Such technologies have created non-trivial and non-reversible changes to our individual and collective behaviors, our institutions and organizations, as well as to human society and our planet at large. But with great power also comes great responsibility. The transformational changes from digitalization are neither unequivocally positive nor negative; more often than not, they are laden with ethical tensions between the contrasting outcomes they engender. For example, personal data digitalization can help individuals live longer and heal their lives, but it also challenges individual rights, obligations, and our sense of dignity. Social media allows us greater connectivity and access, upholding the democratic principle of collective voice, but also becomes a vehicle for manipulating public opinion and spreading fake news and falsehood. Emerging technologies such as shared electric vehicles are coining a revolution in the mobility and energy sector, but also increase fears of labor substitution. The datafication of everyday behaviors has led to new healthcare opportunities but also increased surveillance. The wide embracement of Artificial Intelligence (AI) propels new opportunities for automation and decision-making, but also raises thorny ethical issues in terms of accountability, privacy, fairness, discrimination, and further biases. These observations surface the fact that digital technologies invoke competing narratives: the transformational and innovative powers of digital technologies often contrast dysfunctional outcomes of digitalization, such as social endangerment or loss of human voice and autonomy. While digital technologies promise an exciting future, we have been cautioned that “the journey to the fully pervasive digitized world is also likely to be perilous” and “as much as the potential benefits of digital technology are real, so too are the risks and complexity that ride with them.” Therefore, the key question that we must ask is: how can we positively leverage the transformational powers of digital technologies without falling prey to their possible dysfunctional outcomes? We believe that the answer to this complex question partly lies in the consideration of an important construct: responsibility. Responsibility allows us to evaluate transformational digital technologies in a balanced manner, by factoring in both harmful and positive outcomes from the engagement with such artifacts. Responsibility has become a salient term in this digital age, inspiring new streams of research such as corporate digital responsibility and responsible innovation. Forcing us to engage in meta-ethical reflection, responsibility is crucial to addressing some of the dysfunctional outcomes associated with the rapid proliferation of digital technologies – thus allowing for normative action consistent with human values and ethical defensibility. As information systems researchers, it must be on us to better understand the concept of responsibility as it pertains to the enablement of positive outcomes of the ongoing digitalization of our everyday lives while safeguarding the human experience against possible negative consequences of the same. We term this concept “digital responsibility”, which we believe can serve as an organizing construct of research that aims to inform the balancing of ethical and humanistic tensions pertaining to the rapid proliferation of digital technologies. Notably, focusing on digital responsibility allows us to challenge the often-embraced utopic narrative of digitalization – thus problematizing our vision for this special issue. Digital responsibility is antithetical to “mindlessness” in designing and implementing digital technologies, which is often associated with the inability “to cope gracefully with changing, complex situations characteristic of high-risk domains.” The lens of digital responsibility necessitates that we embark upon rigorously analyzing, explaining, predicting, as well as influencing, the potential costs, duties, and obligations of decisions that relate to the development, implementation, and use of digital information and communication technologies. Following such observations, unpacking the phenomenon of “digital responsibility” should be of utmost concern to IS researchers – and this is the central theme of this special issue.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Designing and using digital technologies for and with responsibility</li>
        
        <li>Considerations of accountability, liability, fairness, and/or responsibility for digital technology design, implementation, and use</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical perspectives and/or empirical insights on the (un)intended social, ethical, and ecological consequences of digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical underpinnings of the concept of digital responsibility, such as from an ethical theory perspective</li>
        
        <li>Design of digital technology to address social, ethical, and/or ecological challenges</li>
        
        <li>Individual, organizational, institutional, or societal strategies for leveraging IS for social, ethical, and/or ecological challenges and innovations</li>
        
        <li>The role of digital technology in promoting social, ethical, and ecological advancements</li>
        
        <li>Applications of emerging digital technologies (e.g., AI) to social, ethical, and/or ecological realms</li>
        
        <li>Societal, ethical, and ecological consequences of emerging digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>(Un-)ethical issues of IS and the data they generate</li>
        
        <li>Dignity, respect, and moral behavior in a digital world</li>
        
        <li>Social support and inclusion enabled by or embodied in digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>The balance of contradicting implications of IS (e.g., IS as a means for social change vs. IS for manipulating public opinion)</li>
        
        <li>The affordances of existing and emerging digital technologies for enacting digital responsibility</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 3, 2023: Deadline for paper submissions</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2024: First-round review decisions</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2024: Hybrid Paper development workshop</li>
        
        <li>July 11, 2024: Deadline for submission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2024: Second-round review decisions</li>
        
        <li>December 8, 2024: Deadline for submission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2025: Provisional decision and final round of comments</li>
        
        <li>February 27, 2025: Deadline for submission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2025: Notification of final decisions</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Jose Benitez</strong>, EDHEC Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Benlian</strong>, TU Darmstadt</li>
        
        <li><strong>Roberta Bernardi</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michelle Carter</strong>, Washington State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dubravka Cecez-Kecmanovic</strong>, University of New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>John D&#39;Arcy</strong>, University of Delaware</li>
        
        <li><strong>James Gaskin</strong>, Brigham Young University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Oliver Laasch</strong>, ESCP Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shan Pan</strong>, University of New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hannes Rothe</strong>, University of Duisburg-Essen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Saonee Sarker</strong>, Lund University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Olgerta Tona</strong>, University of Gothenburg</li>
        
        <li><strong>John Tripp</strong>, Clemson University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tuure Tuunanen</strong>, University Jyväskylä</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Technologies and Social Justice]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/misq-digital-technologies-and-social-justice</link>
            <guid>misq-digital-technologies-and-social-justice</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 05:15:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
    
    
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>MIS Quarterly (MISQ)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>