<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/</link>
        <description>Calls for Papers shows you the latest calls for papers of academic journals in your discipline.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 04:35:43 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Transformative AI in Online Markets: Development, Impact, and the Road Ahead]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/im-transformative-ai-in-online-markets-development-impact-and-the-road-ahead</link>
            <guid>im-transformative-ai-in-online-markets-development-impact-and-the-road-ahead</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 03:21:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Hillol Bala</strong>, Indiana University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yue (Katherine) Feng</strong>, Hong Kong Polytechnic University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Xin Li</strong>, Hong Kong Polytechnic University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>With the proliferation of the internet and mobile technology in the past two decades (Chen et al. 2002), online markets and platforms have experienced exponential growth and become a cornerstone of modern commerce, transforming how businesses operate and how consumers engage with products and services (Phan and Vogel 2010). The development of the online market attracted significant attention from academia.</p>
    
    <p>Meanwhile, driven by advances in models (including machine learning, deep learning, and large models) and computational power, artificial Intelligence (AI) has emerged as a transformative force, reshaping organizations and innovations (Fügener et al. 2021; Lee et al. 2023). The importance of AI goes beyond the improvement in operational performance, such as in personalization, recommendation, and data processing, and lies in the potential to solve complex problems with significant impacts (Wei et al. 2025). The term “transformative AI” was coined to refer to such potential of AI to change society, economy, or even humans (Banafa 2023; Trammell and Korinek 2023; Wessel et al. 2025).</p>
    
    <p>In particular, we posit that AI will bring transformative power to revolutionize the online market — a foundation of the digital economy. As AI technologies continue to evolve, they promise to unlock new opportunities, foster innovation, and address global challenges (Mikalef and Gupta 2021). With AI’s further integration into online markets, it may create a more dynamic, efficient, and customer-centric digital shopping experience (Deng et al. 2023; Rai et al. 2019; Wang et al. 2025).</p>
    
    <p>In light of this potential, this special issue invites efforts from information systems scholars to study the design, use, impact, and management of AI that may transform online markets for exchanging products, services, innovations, and algorithms, among other things. This special issue encourages research using technical, empirical, or behavioral methods performed at individual, group, organizational, or societal levels. We particularly welcome the studies that can bring insights into the future of AI in online markets.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Models and algorithms that can bring a transformative impact on online markets</li>
        
        <li>Challenges &amp; solutions for online markets in the AI era</li>
        
        <li>Human-AI interaction in online markets</li>
        
        <li>Operational optimization in online markets with AI</li>
        
        <li>Impact of AI on consumer behavior and platform design</li>
        
        <li>Social, psychological, or economic implications of AI adoption in digital commerce</li>
        
        <li>Personalization and recommendation systems driven by AI</li>
        
        <li>Generative AI for content creation and presentation in e-commerce</li>
        
        <li>AI-enabled decision-making for consumers, sellers, and platform operators</li>
        
        <li>Business model innovations in AI-integrated online markets</li>
        
        <li>Ethical issues related to the implementation and use of AI in online markets</li>
        
        <li>Responsible and explainable AI in online market platforms</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 23, 2025: Call for papers announcement date for the special issue.</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2026: Submission system open.</li>
        
        <li>June 1, 2026: Submission deadline for full papers.</li>
        
        <li>September 1, 2026: First-round authors notification.</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2027: First-round revisions deadline.</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2027: Second round authors notification.</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2027: Second round revision deadline.</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2027: Final author notification.</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2027: Projected publication date.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Yanzhen Chen</strong>, HK University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ashish Gupta</strong>, Auburn University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wei Hu</strong>, Tongji University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Araz Jabbari</strong>, Laval University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rain Kan</strong>, Indiana University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Satish Krishnan</strong>, IIM Kozhikode</li>
        
        <li><strong>Akshat Lakhiwal</strong>, University of Georgia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mengxiang Li</strong>, Hong Kong Baptist University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Guangrui (Kayla) Li</strong>, York University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yijing Li</strong>, Hong Kong Polytechnic University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ben Liu</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Chewei Liu</strong>, Arizona State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Fei Liu</strong>, Hong Kong Polytechnic University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xiao Liu</strong>, Arizona State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yidi Liu</strong>, Chinese University of Hong Kong (SZ)</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shengjun Mao</strong>, University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Boris Ng</strong>, Hong Kong Polytechnic University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Agrim Sachdeva</strong>, University of Arizona</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pankaj Setia</strong>, IIM Ahmedabad</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yani Shi</strong>, Southeast University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anuragini Shirish</strong>, Institute Mines-Télécom</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nichalin Summerfield</strong>, Umass Lowell</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jianshan Sun</strong>, Hefei University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xue (Jane) Tan</strong>, Southern Methodist University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ching-I Teng</strong>, Chang Gung University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yu Tong</strong>, Zhejiang University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mochen Yang</strong>, University of Minnesota</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lei Wang</strong>, Indiana University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Samuel Fosso Wamba</strong>, Toulouse Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tracy Yang</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Niam Yaraghi</strong>, Miami University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dezhi (Denny) Yin</strong>, University of South Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mi Zhou</strong>, University of British Columbia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sijia Zhou</strong>, Southeast University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information and Management (IM)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Generative AI as Driver of Change in Media]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jmis-generative-ai-as-driver-of-change-in-media</link>
            <guid>jmis-generative-ai-as-driver-of-change-in-media</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 03:12:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Thomas Hess</strong>, University of Munich (LMU)</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ioanna Constantiou</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Niki Panteli</strong>, Lancaster University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Generative AI (GenAI) has rapidly become a general-purpose technology that reshapes how information is created, curated, and consumed. GenAI broadly refers to a class of AI models that generate seemingly new content in the form of text, images, audio, or video. In the media context, where value is built around the provision and use of content, GenAI has attracted particular attention. For instance, it enables the near-instant creation of journalistic articles, marketing texts, or audiovisual material, and it supports personalization by dynamically adapting media offerings to individual user preferences. The advent of the Internet had already marked a profound transformation in the delivery and consumption of content. It made user-generated content possible, catalyzed multi-sided platforms, and enabled unprecedented personalization. This transformation brought new players into the media sector, as technology companies entered the market and traditional media firms were forced to develop significant digital competencies for the first time.</p>
    
    <p>GenAI is expected to have an equally profound impact on the media industry by expanding complementary innovation, lowering barriers for content creation, and altering the economics of matching and recommendation at scale. Despite recent advances, our knowledge is still limited. Existing research has begun to shed light on the impact of GenAI on textual news app users’ willingness to pay, yet it is unknown whether similar effects extend to audiovisual content. Moreover, there are initial indications of how journalists’ productivity may change with the use of GenAI. At the same time, the potential for entirely new GenAI-based products remains largely unexplored. In particular, little is known about the extent to which audience discussions can be moderated and managed, or about the new forms of public media provision that GenAI might enable. These questions are especially pressing given the central role of media in shaping public opinion and broader societal developments, including political attitudes.</p>
    
    <p>The aim of this special issue is to advance IS research on this emerging field. We invite contributions that examine the role of GenAI in the provision and use of media offerings. Analyses may focus on individuals, organizations, or industries. Studies may address GenAI on the level of systems, their effects, or their management. Submissions should be firmly grounded in the technology itself and its implications for media ecosystems. This special issue aims to stimulate innovative investigations of the transformative role of GenAI in the provisioning and use of public media. In contrast to closed settings, such as private messaging services, the recipients of public communication cannot be predetermined or exhaustively specified in advance. Accordingly, the domain of interest spans both online media, including digital platforms and social media, and traditional media such as print and television. We welcome qualitative and quantitative empirical studies as well as design-oriented research. Submissions should provide a clear academic contribution by advancing theory and knowledge in the Information Systems discipline. While practical relevance and managerial implications are highly valued, they are not sufficient on their own; academic advancement is essential.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Provision of Content for the Media</li>
        
        <li>Use of Content provided by the Media</li>
        
        <li>Embedding of the Media in Society</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>December 1, 2025: Full paper submission opens</li>
        
        <li>April 30, 2026: Full paper submission closes</li>
        
        <li>June 30, 2026: Desk check</li>
        
        <li>September 30, 2026: Feedback on the first version</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2027: Submission revision 1</li>
        
        <li>April 30, 2027: Feedback on revision 1</li>
        
        <li>June 30, 2027: Submission revision 2</li>
        
        <li>July 31, 2027: Final decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Management Information Systems (JMIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[India at the Intersection: Reconfiguring Commerce, Capabilities and Culture in Age of Technological Acceleration]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jsis-india-at-the-intersection-reconfiguring-commerce-capabilities-and-culture-in-age-of-technological-acceleration</link>
            <guid>jsis-india-at-the-intersection-reconfiguring-commerce-capabilities-and-culture-in-age-of-technological-acceleration</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 03:16:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Pankaj Setia</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Ahmedabad</p>
        
        <p><strong>Priya Seetharaman</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Calcutta</p>
        
        <p><strong>Abhishek Kathuria</strong>, Deakin University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Contemporary Information Systems (IS) are marked by transformations at the intersection of technology, people and organizations (Setia 2024). These are shaped by, and are shaping how firms, communities, and societies evolve. As researchers unravel these dynamics, India presents a compelling context. Rooted in millennia of cultural and commercial history, India is now rapidly being reshaped by the forces of digital innovation. Indian business landscape is a vibrant mosaic where ancient artisanal traditions, kinship-based commerce, informal enterprises, and social ventures coexist with state-owned firms, family conglomerates, and home-grown blue chips. This landscape often collides with large multinationals, platform economies, and globally scaled startups. Together, India’s palimpsestic business environment, pluralistic culture, and demographic vastness form a powerful trifecta that offers a unique context for researchers. Specifically, unlike a monolith landscape, India represents a living, evolving environment of practices, identities, and aspirations.</p>
    
    <p>This special issue invites submissions focused on how rapid technological acceleration in India is strategically reshaping the country’s business environment. We particularly welcome submissions that explores how culture, capabilities, and commerce evolve amid the transformations of a historically layered, institutionally complex economy. Traditionally, India’s artisanal industries and cultural expressions were deeply entwined with its commercial practices (Tharoor, 2016). Centuries of colonial domination disrupted local crafts and knowledge systems; today, the digital wave carries a similar dual potential, risking the displacement of traditional modes of production while also offering new avenues for visibility and market access. India’s contemporary platform economy, with its roots in the historical bazaar and emporium systems (Athique, 2020), exemplifies this paradox.</p>
    
    <p>The expansion of digital technologies into an informal, fragmented economy has introduced elements of structure and visibility long described by Scott’s notion of “legibility” (1998), a concept which relevance persists as states and platforms alike seek to render local practices more standardized and governable in the digital age. Could the drive for scale, efficiency, and algorithmic appeal lead to a flattening of cultural nuance in favor of standardization and mass reproducibility? This scenario becomes real if Information Technology (IT) education and digital skilling emphasize surface-leveltechnical credentials and globalized templates of “digital competence” (Rangaswamy &amp; Narasimhan, 2022) rather than contextually grounded, socially attuned capabilities.</p>
    
    <p>Research on India’s digital transformation offers opportunities to develop new theoretical insights for the global IS community. India’s “digital revolution” began with the IT services boom of the 1990s, expanded through the telecom and mobile internet surge of the 2000s, and has accelerated since the mid-2010s (Seetharaman &amp; Cranefield, 2019) along with more recent initiatives such as Digital India (nationwide digital infrastructure and e-governance), Aadhaar (biometric digital identity) (Addo, 2022), UPI (Unified Payments Interface, i.e. inter-bank peer-to-peer and person-to-merchant real-time payments), and ONDC (Open Network for Digital Commerce - a decentralized, interoperable open e-commerce). The early IT services phase delivered major economic gains, creating an entire industry, generating jobs, boosting exports (Bhatnagar &amp; Madon, 1997). More recently, the focus has shifted to attracting foreign investment and expanding access to information (Parthiban et al., 2024). Yet some scholars have questioned the limited societal spillovers and skewed labor composition (Barnes, 2013) of India’s IT industry. Others note that emerging digital technologies may help move beyond low-end services toward more diversified, socially embedded growth (Das &amp; Sagara, 2017).</p>
    
    <p>The current IT development phase, characterized by digital platforms embedding services related to fintech, e-governance, and mobile ecosystems, has expanded access to resources, formalized parts of the informal sector, and holds promise for reducing poverty and inequality. These developments offer models for the wider global majority, even if significant challenges remain. The complex dynamics of new technological affordances and constraints, ranging from cross-platform interoperability to fraudulence (Kumar et al., 2025) and lack of sufficient regulations that balance conflicting interests (Marabelli &amp; Davison, 2025; De’ et al., 2024), hinder the equitable spread of these digital platforms across socio-economic groups.</p>
    
    <p>IS research, including studies published in JSIS, highlights how digital technologies may afford the creation of economic opportunities for the informal sector, help small and medium enterprises access new markets (Parthiban et al., 2024; Shirish et al., 2025), and transform service delivery in high impact industries such as healthcare (Hiriyur, 2022; Setia, 2023). In India and in the wider global majority countries, digital technology has also been socially transformative such as through, amplifying marginalized voices, lowering barriers to political participation (Kulshreshth, 2023), and supporting creative industries through digital media (Mehta &amp; Cunningham, 2023), though always mediated by prevailing social norms and values (Oreglia &amp; Srinivasan, 2016). This ongoing transformation is however complicated by geopolitical tensions, supply chain disruptions, and economic nationalism which are leading to a rethink of globalization’s promises (Butollo et al., 2024). Although digital technologies, AI (artificial intelligence) in particular, are deeply entangled with environmental sustainability challenges exacerbating global resource inequalities; yet they also enable strategic responses to climate risks through innovations in smart cities, agriculture, and disaster prediction (Marabelli &amp; Davison, 2025). For India too, this shift opens up both risks and opportunities: it may create greater space for indigenous enterprises, self-reliant supply chains, and localized innovation, while also changing the nature of export-led sectors and globally networked business models (Witt et al., 2023). The interplay between fractured globalizing forces and India’s own plural, multi-scale economy raises pressing questions about sovereignty, resilience, and cultural-economic autonomy.</p>
    
    <p>This special issue seeks to examine strategic opportunities, disruptions and challenges arising from the intersection of culture, commerce, capabilities and technology in the Indian context. We welcome research that shows how digital technologies reshape strategic choices, organizing logics, and competitive positioning while remaining embedded in India’s uniqueness. The special issue also aims to foreground location-specific research agendas and contextual theorization (Avgerou, 2019), emphasizing the need for research that is not only rigorous and relevant, but also responsible to its context (Seetharaman et al., 2024).</p>
    
    <p>By bringing together diverse ideas and a deeper understanding, this special issue aims to reframe India not as a battleground between tradition and modernity but as a dynamic site of ongoing negotiation, reinvention, and possibility.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Craft, Culture, Civilization, and Vernacular Economies</li>
        
        <li>Digital Platforms, Inclusion, and Ecosystems</li>
        
        <li>Innovation, Entrepreneurship, and Labor</li>
        
        <li>Policy, Scale, and Governance</li>
        
        <li>Firm-Level Strategy and Organizational Change</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>March 6, 2026: Developmental workshop for interested authors at InCIS 2026</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2026: Deadline to submit a 1000-words extended abstract on the JSIS portal (not required but highly recommended)</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2026: Submission of full papers opens</li>
        
        <li>September 30, 2026: Submission deadline for full papers</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2027: Initial feedback to authors</li>
        
        <li>April 30, 2027: Deadline for resubmission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>September 30, 2027: Final Submissions due</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2027: Final editorial decisions communicated to authors</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Amit Prakash</strong>, International Institute of Information Technology Bangalore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anuragini Shirish</strong>, Institute Mines-Télécom Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ashish Kumar Jha</strong>, Trinity Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ashish Gupta</strong>, Auburn University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Atta Addo</strong>, Surrey Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Bidisha Chaudhuri</strong>, University of Amsterdam</li>
        
        <li><strong>Devinder Thapa</strong>, University of Agder</li>
        
        <li><strong>Janaki Srinivasan</strong>, University of Oxford</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Monash University</li>
        
        <li><strong>M N Ravishankar</strong>, Queen&#39;s Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>M S Sandeep</strong>, UNSW Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nirup Menon</strong>, George Mason University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Onkar Malgonde</strong>, North Carolina State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Radhika Santhanam</strong>, University of Oklahoma</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rahul De</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Bangalore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rajiv Kishore</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Saji K Mathew</strong>, Indian Institute of Technology Madras</li>
        
        <li><strong>Samrat Gupta</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Ahmedabad</li>
        
        <li><strong>Satish Krishnan</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Kozhikode</li>
        
        <li><strong>Silvia Masiero</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Soumyakanti Chakraborty</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Calcutta</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sumeet Gupta</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Raipur</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sunil Wattal</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Suranjan Chakraborty</strong>, Towson University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Swanand Deodhar</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Ahmedabad</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>The Journal of Strategic Information Systems (JSIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unpacking the Multifaceted Impact of Generative Artificial Intelligence on Organisations]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jsis-unpacking-the-multifaceted-impact-of-generative-artificial-intelligence-on-organisations</link>
            <guid>jsis-unpacking-the-multifaceted-impact-of-generative-artificial-intelligence-on-organisations</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 03:09:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Jun Hwa Cheah (Jacky)</strong>, University of East Anglia</p>
        
        <p><strong>Brad McKenna</strong>, University of East Anglia</p>
        
        <p><strong>Shahper Richter</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>PK Senyo</strong>, University of Southampton</p>
        
        <p><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue examines Generative AI&#39;s dual impact on organisations, driving innovation, efficiency, and societal value while raising ethical, governance, and workforce challenges.</p>
    
    <p>Generative Artificial Intelligence (GAI) is at the forefront of technological innovation, with rapid growth and transformative potential. By 2032, the global GAI market is projected to reach $151.9 billion. This trajectory reflects the growing recognition of GAI&#39;s capabilities across multiple domains, fundamentally reshaping innovation paradigms and redefining organisational processes and structures. In particular, GAI is increasingly acknowledged as a transformative force in facilitating data-driven decision-making and optimising operational processes within and across organisations. Foundational GAI systems such as BERT, ChatGPT DALL-E, Deepseek and Gemini illustrate their adaptability and extensive applicability. These systems can execute a wide array of tasks, ranging from creative production and service delivery to organisational decision-making, offering novel opportunities for personalisation, operational efficiency, and interdisciplinary collaboration. As GAI continues to evolve, some organisations have commenced developing and disseminating regulatory frameworks to legitimise its deployment in organisational processes. There is growing interest in whether GAI can be repurposed as a strategic technology employed for advancing social justice and addressing grand challenges, from climate resilience to digital access and social welfare. At the same time, there are stakeholders, including organisational actors, that are concerned with the risks posed by GAI, such as data governance, epistemic reliability, trust, error propagation, and bias. This special issue aims to unfold strategic opportunities and challenges of GAI in organizations, networks, government bodies and society at large.</p>
    
    <p>While prior studies have examined AI more conceptually and broadly, a significant unexplored area remains, which concerns the multifaceted impacts of GAI on organisational decision-making within the information systems research. Because of the relevant strategic implications (and potentially ethical challenges) associated with implementing GAI in organisations, filling this gap becomes paramount. In particular, with this special issue we aim to stimulate research focusing on the dual nature of GAI, its simultaneous potential for value co-creation and value co-destruction in organisations; GAI presents promising opportunities and significant challenges. In particular, GAI used for automated content creation, internal reporting and predictive analytics, has the potential to improve operational efficiency by identifying workflow bottlenecks, reducing manual workload, and enabling data-driven insights into employee performance and strategic planning. With these capabilities, it can detect subtle signs of fatigue or burnout, such as slower response times, changes in communication tone, or altered work patterns. Hence it enables early intervention through tailored support or adjustments to the workload. Also, by synthesising vast amounts of information, GAI supports value co-creation and strategic agility in decision-making, promotes innovation and digital inclusion, and allows employees to focus on higher-level tasks such as problem-solving and strategic thinking. In fact, GAI can foster creativity and knowledge sharing, support employee well-being by automating repetitive tasks, and improve cross-functional collaboration. GAI can also detect subtle patterns indicative of fatigue or burnout, such as reduced response times, changes in communication tone, or shifts in work rhythms, allowing organisations to intervene early with tailored support or workload adjustments.</p>
    
    <p>However, these organisational benefits are tempered by critical concerns. The increasing reliance on opaque and complex GAI systems introduces risks related to hallucinations, diminished human oversight, and the externalisation of ethical responsibility onto non-accountable technologies. According to a 2023 global survey, 75% of companies have restricted or actively considered restricting technologies such as ChatGPT due to fears of data breaches, intellectual property loss, and declining trust in AI-generated content. More fundamentally, GAI threatens the nature of creative labour, raising questions about job security, intellectual integrity, and the automation of cognitively demanding work. GAI implementation may also generate unintended consequences for employee well-being, including role displacement, cognitive dependency, and reduced transparency in decision-making, which somehow affects the diversity, equality, and inclusion in the working environment. Concerning workplace surveillance, GAI can undermine employee autonomy by enabling constant monitoring that erodes trust and psychological safety. Employees may feel reduced to performance metrics, reflecting a shift toward Digital Taylorism, which prioritises algorithmic efficiency over human creativity. This dynamic can further intensify privacy concerns due to the opaque nature of many GAI systems, where data is often collected and used without clear consent. This will also heighten the risk of biased or discriminatory outcomes. Thus, all of these concerns highlight the potential for value co-destruction, wherein mismanaged or poorly governed GAI adoption undermines organisational integrity, ethical standards, and stakeholder trust. This resonates with recent developments in people analytics, where GAI-facilitated behavioural monitoring intersects with algorithmic control, potentially transforming managerial decision-making into a form of digital micromanagement.</p>
    
    <p>Given these growing uncertainties and tensions surrounding GAI, there is an urgent need to move beyond celebratory narratives and engage in critical, multidisciplinary inquiry into its dual-edged nature. On one hand, GAI serves as a powerful cognitive enabler, helping organisations to synthesise complex information, generate novel insights, and expand the boundaries of individual and collective knowledge. On the other hand, increasing reliance on these systems may gradually erode essential cognitive functions, such as critical thinking, independent reasoning, and problem-solving skills. Furthermore, the large-scale integration of GAI risks reinforcing existing cognitive biases, curating algorithmic filter bubbles, and narrowing exposure to diverse perspectives, thereby constraining informed decision-making. In light of these tensions, this special issue invites scholars and practitioners to adopt a perspective considering both the strategic, transformative potential and disruptive consequences of GAI. We welcome contributions that examine how GAI simultaneously enhances and challenges existing organisational frameworks and processes, ultimately reshaping the landscape of technological governance, human agency, and organisational transformation. Submissions may offer theoretical or empirical insights into the promises, ethical dilemmas, and societal shifts driven by GAI at the organisational level, including its application to grand societal challenges. We will not consider papers focusing on users, individuals, or manuscripts that do not align with the central focus of the special issue. Papers may use qualitative, quantitative, or pluralistic approaches.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>How is the utilisation of GAI reshaping workforce structures, labour division, and professional identity in public and/or private organisations?</li>
        
        <li>How can organisations effectively balance the efficiency and productivity gains promised by GAI with the risks related to data security, intellectual property theft, and regulatory compliance challenges?</li>
        
        <li>In what ways can organisations address the ethical implications of GAI, particularly concerning its potential to diminish human oversight and decision-making capabilities, while still harnessing its benefits for enhanced operational efficiency?</li>
        
        <li>How does GAI contribute to value co-destruction within organisations, in relation to resource misallocation, ethical compromises, and potential damage to organisational integrity or stakeholder trust?</li>
        
        <li>What strategies can organisations adopt to mitigate the risks of job displacement, deskilling, and workforce inequality while still leveraging GAI for innovation and competitiveness?</li>
        
        <li>How can organisational capabilities and leadership approaches evolve to ensure a balance between fostering innovation through GAI and managing its long-term impacts on employment, creativity, and organisational culture?</li>
        
        <li>How do organisational frameworks surrounding GAI affect the reinforcement or reduction of structural inequalities, especially in marginalised communities, and what measures can be taken to ensure inclusive and equitable use of GAI technologies?</li>
        
        <li>How are corporate governance frameworks evolving in response to GAI’s ethical challenges in decision-making, and how can these frameworks protect against algorithmic biases while fostering innovation?</li>
        
        <li>What role should organisational policies play in ensuring that GAI is used transparently and responsibly, particularly in high-stakes decisions involving human resources, operations, marketing, and customer relations?</li>
        
        <li>How is GAI being used for surveillance and control in organizational contexts, and what implications does this have for employee autonomy and governance, both in the workplace and in broader governmental settings?</li>
        
        <li>What is the potential and what are the limitations of GAI adoption in organisations across emerging economies and the Global South, particularly in relation to infrastructural, educational, and data governance challenges?</li>
        
        <li>Examining how different organisations (e.g., governments, healthcare providers, charities, or social enterprises) might deploy GAI to address grand challenges such as climate-adaptation, homelessness-prevention services, healthcare, strategically serving marginalised populations, or environmental disasters.</li>
        
        <li>Assessing the emerging role of corporate sustainability offices in leveraging GAI for supply-chain net-zero scenario planning.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>January 31, 2026: Submission of extended abstracts (~1,000 words including references). Submission of an abstract is not mandatory but is strongly encouraged.</li>
        
        <li>July 31, 2026: Deadline for full papers submission.</li>
        
        <li>October 31, 2026: Initial feedback to authors.</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2027: Deadline for resubmission of revised papers.</li>
        
        <li>April 30, 2027: Second-round feedback to authors.</li>
        
        <li>June 30, 2027: Final editorial decisions communicated to authors.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Ahmad Arslan</strong>, University of Oulu</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Richter</strong>, Victoria University of Wellington</li>
        
        <li><strong>Daniel Gozman</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Eleonora Pantano</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Federico Iannacci</strong>, University of Sussex</li>
        
        <li><strong>Francis Andoh Baidoo</strong>, University of Texas Rio Grande Valley</li>
        
        <li><strong>Imran Ali</strong>, Central Queensland University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ismail Golgeci</strong>, University of Auckland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jason Bennett Thatcher</strong>, University of Colorado Boulder</li>
        
        <li><strong>Linda Hollebeek</strong>, Sunway University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Margherita Pagani</strong>, SKEMA Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nisreen Ameen</strong>, Royal Holloway</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ryan Yung</strong>, University of Greenwich</li>
        
        <li><strong>Saima Qutab</strong>, University of Auckland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sandra Smith</strong>, University of Auckland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shohil Kishore</strong>, University of Auckland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stan Karanasios</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Weng Marc Lim</strong>, Sunway University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>The Journal of Strategic Information Systems (JSIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Algorithmic Assemblages—Fields, Ecosystems, and Platforms: An Interpretive Approach]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/io-algorithmic-assemblagesfields-ecosystems-and-platforms-an-interpretive-approach</link>
            <guid>io-algorithmic-assemblagesfields-ecosystems-and-platforms-an-interpretive-approach</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 03:15:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Timothy Hannigan</strong>, Telfer School of Business</p>
        
        <p><strong>P. Devereaux Jennings</strong>, Alberta School of Business</p>
        
        <p><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, Information Systems Sam M. Walton College of Business</p>
        
        <p><strong>Samer Faraj</strong>, Desautels Faculty of Management at McGill University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This Special Issue is devoted to interpretive approaches to studying algorithmic assemblages constitutive of and by fields, ecosystems, and platforms and combining research from an organizational and information systems view about such organizing features and their dynamics. Information technologies have progressively enabled a shift in the locus of value creation, capture, and resource orchestration and the processes they entail from within organizations to more loosely coupled and emergently structured sociotechnical systems. The interpretive approach stems from the relational turn in organization theory and considers assemblages and algorithmic organizing as views of key constructs and their associated processes.</p>
    
    <p>To date, there has been less theory-building and empirical research connecting macro constructs with the micro-dynamics of these systems. It is particularly unclear how algorithmic technologies enable the interconnections of organizational ecosystems and facilitate legitimacy dynamics of institutional fields. Furthermore, it is not clear how algorithmic technologies circumscribe meanings across global fields and societies. The call for theory and research relies on relational approaches coming from both organization theory and information systems.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Interpretive approaches to algorithmic assemblages</li>
        
        <li>Relational approaches from organization theory</li>
        
        <li>The dynamics of algorithmic technologies in organizational ecosystems</li>
        
        <li>Legitimacy dynamics of institutional fields</li>
        
        <li>Impact of AI and blockchain on organizational structures and meanings</li>
        
        <li>Methodological frameworks for studying technology-mediated organizing</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>May 15, 2026: Submission deadline for full papers</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2026: First round reviews due</li>
        
        <li>October 31, 2026: First round decision letters sent out</li>
        
        <li>February 28, 2027: First round paper resubmissions</li>
        
        <li>May 31, 2027: Second round reviews due</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2027: Second round decision letters sent out</li>
        
        <li>October 15, 2027: Second round paper resubmissions</li>
        
        <li>March 15, 2028: Final papers selected, introductory editorial paper written</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information and Organization (IO)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Critical National Infrastructure]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jmis-critical-national-infrastructure</link>
            <guid>jmis-critical-national-infrastructure</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 03:20:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Jason Chan</strong>, University of Minnesota</p>
        
        <p><strong>Alan Dennis</strong>, Indiana University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Daniel Gozman</strong>, The University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Kalle Lyytinen</strong>, Case Western Reserve University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Critical National Infrastructure (CNI) encompasses essential systems and services that are vital for societal stability, economic security, and national safety. The increasing digitalization of these infrastructures has introduced unprecedented efficiencies that have transformed economies, enabling faster service delivery, improved public safety, reduced corruption, and enhanced crisis response through data sharing and analytics.</p>
    
    <p>The United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) supports digital public infrastructure (DPI) as a driver for financial inclusion, social protection, and governance reforms. Digital advancements have also driven sustainability, with smart grids, environmental monitoring, and optimized resource management with potential for reducing carbon footprints and increasing resilience.</p>
    
    <p>Furthermore, technological innovation in financial services, transportation, and energy has the potential to stimulate economic growth through enabling new business models. While the increasing digitalization of Critical National Infrastructure has introduced efficiencies, it also created unprecedented vulnerabilities, including cyberattacks, cascading failures, and systemic interdependencies that amplify risks.</p>
    
    <p>Recognizing these challenges, governments in the UK, US, and Australia have developed regulatory frameworks such as the UK’s National Cyber Security Strategy, the US Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency (CISA) guidelines, and Australia’s Security of Critical Infrastructure Act (SOCI Act) to enhance resilience and mitigate emerging threats.</p>
    
    <p>CNI spans multiple critical sectors, each with unique security and operational challenges, including energy and utilities, telecommunications and information networks, financial services and payments, healthcare and public health, transportation and logistics, emergency services and law enforcement, and government and public sector infrastructure.</p>
    
    <p>As efforts to build CNIs have accelerated, issues around CNI security, resilience, and adaptability are becoming increasingly critical. At the same time significant research gaps remain in cybersecurity practices at the system level, governance, integration and management of emerging technologies such as Autonomous Driving Systems, and threat intelligence sharing.</p>
    
    <p>Addressing these gaps is essential for policymakers, businesses, and infrastructure operators to mitigate threats, optimize performance, and ensure long-term continuity.</p>
    
    <p>This Special Section aims to advance research on the design, adoption, and impact of digital solutions and services critical in building CNI to enhance governance, economic development, and public service delivery and safeguard CNI. We invite interdisciplinary contributions that explore how digital technologies and services can enhance CNI or impose new risks and challenges for the operation of CNIs. Papers that do not explicitly address or theorize about CNI design and operation and their digital components will be returned without review.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Emerging Technologies and Digital Transformation: Innovative technologies such as Artificial Intelligence, Digital Twins, Blockchain and IoT are transforming CNI, enabling predictive analytics, smart grids, and cyber-physical security enhancements.</li>
        
        <li>Cybersecurity, Resilience, and Risk Management: Cyber threats such as ransomware, insider attacks, and cyber-physical vulnerabilities continue to grow. Risk assessment frameworks and mitigation strategies are essential.</li>
        
        <li>Governance, Policy, and Public-Private Partnerships: CNI governance requires polycentric collaborative efforts between government agencies, private sector entities, and international stakeholders.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>June 1, 2025: Expression of Interest: one-page abstract, optional</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2026: Initial Submission Due</li>
        
        <li>May 31, 2026: Notification of First Round Decision</li>
        
        <li>September 30, 2026: 1st Resubmission Due</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2027: Notification of Second Round Decision</li>
        
        <li>April 30, 2027: 2nd Resubmission Due</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2027: Final Decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Management Information Systems (JMIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Sustainability and Information Systems Research: New challenges and theoretical perspectives]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-digital-sustainability-and-information-systems-research</link>
            <guid>jais-digital-sustainability-and-information-systems-research</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 12:54:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jacqueline Corbett</strong>, Université Laval</p>
        
        <p><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Monash University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Thomas Kude</strong>, University of Bamberg</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yenni Tim</strong>, University of New South Wales</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Sustainability is a moral and existential imperative of our time. As Information Systems (IS) scholars, we are aware of the immense impact of digital technologies on efforts and initiatives towards sustainable practice happening locally and globally. Furthermore, because digital phenomena lie at the heart of our discipline, IS researchers are well positioned to join these efforts. This Special Issue aims to champion new digital sustainability research programs targeting the planet’s most pressing sustainability challenges from the past decade. We hope it will contribute towards building novel collective knowledge and help shape digital sustainability research in IS.</p>
    
    <p>Human society is approaching the edge of a dangerous precipice. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change’s (IPCC) Sixth Assessment Report unequivocally confirms that human activities have caused global warming, predicting that even with current commitments and mitigation efforts, it will be difficult to limit warming below the critical threshold of 2 o C. The planet’s air, land, and water continue to be threatened on several fronts, with research suggesting that the safe operating zone for six of the nine planetary boundaries has already been breached. Over the past decade, extreme weather events such as droughts, floods, fires and heatwaves have not only increased in frequency but also in magnitude. In addition to causing environmental impacts, these events have a significant impact on society, further complicating the pursuit of social and economic sustainability.</p>
    
    <p>In 2020, about 724 million people were living in conditions of extreme poverty, with almost 30% of the world’s population suffering from some level of food insecurity. Equality for women and other marginalized groups continues to lag. The World Bank reports that 2.4 billion women globally do not have the same economic rights as men, and despite the adoption of the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples in 2007, Indigenous Peoples around the world continue to suffer the intergenerational trauma of colonization. The trend towards urbanization endures, with cities struggling to ensure inclusive, resilient, and sustainable living environments for all residents. On top of all these challenges, violent conflicts have led to the forced migration of millions of people and the deaths of thousands of civilians. These alarming circumstances highlight the lack of progress towards the United Nation’s Sustainable Development Goals.</p>
    
    <p>As argued in a recent JAIS editorial on digital sustainability, the IS research community has a strong foundation to draw upon, ranging from research into Green IS to studies addressing significant societal challenges. The poor cannot eat technology, but the mindful design and use of technology can contribute to innovative solutions and positive impacts. In particular, we consider that the recent shift in the way IS research approaches digital phenomena offers new perspectives on the relationship between digital technologies and sustainability. Building on a contention that the classical view of an information system as representing and reflecting physical reality has become obsolete, there exists an opportunity for the IS community to drive a more inclusive agenda on digital sustainability, one that encompasses phenomena in which the impact of digital technologies and macro-level environmental, social, and economic objectives converge.</p>
    
    <p>Accordingly, this Special Issue seeks contributions that delve into digital sustainability and encompass the development, deployment, and utilization of digital resources and artifacts toward improving the environment, society, and economic welfare.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Design and development considerations</li>
        
        <li>Research that investigates the processes, principles, resources or capabilities required for the design and development of digital sustainability artefacts</li>
        
        <li>Intervention-based research that engages directly in enhancing sustainability practices within organizations or communities through effective leveraging of digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>Studies examining how the different inter- and intra-organizational actors involved in digital sustainability projects engage and interact as they develop, deploy, and govern digital solutions for macro-level sustainability agenda</li>
        
        <li>Explorations of the relationships between digital objects and the physical reality they shape/create in the context of social and environmental sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Use considerations</li>
        
        <li>Research examining how digital technologies support key organizational activities in the management of macro-level sustainability challenges</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical and/or empirical investigations of the interplay between sustainability initiatives and other digital agendas</li>
        
        <li>Studies of ‘computed human experiences’ with respect to sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Research on the challenges and opportunities for reclaiming and rejuvenating Indigenous cultures and knowledge through decolonized digital artefacts</li>
        
        <li>Management and governance considerations</li>
        
        <li>Studies exploring the governance of digital sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Research on the role of different actors in the digital sustainability ecosystem</li>
        
        <li>Studies on the sustainability agenda at the community and societal levels</li>
        
        <li>Policy implications related to digital sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Outcomes and consequences</li>
        
        <li>Studies that incorporate multiple aspects of digital sustainability performance</li>
        
        <li>Case studies of real-world impacts of digital sustainability on vulnerable or marginalized communities</li>
        
        <li>Research investigating alternative ways of measuring progress toward long-term sustainability objectives</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>February 20, 2024: Online information session (we invite potential authors to send us specific questions to address during this session)</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2024: Deadline for paper submission</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2025: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>June 1, 2025: Deadline to submit revised papers</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2025: Second-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2026: Deadline to submit revised papers</li>
        
        <li>June 1, 2026: Provisional/Final decisions</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2026: Deadline to submit final paper (if minor revision is required)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Managing the Individual, Organizational, and Societal Challenges of Generative AI: Utopian, Dystopian, Neutropian Perspectives]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-managing-the-individual-organizational-and-societal-challenges-of-generative-ai-utopian-dystopian-neutropian-perspectives</link>
            <guid>jais-managing-the-individual-organizational-and-societal-challenges-of-generative-ai-utopian-dystopian-neutropian-perspectives</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 12:46:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Varun Grover</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Arpan Kumar Kar</strong>, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Sabherwal</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Spyros Angelopoulos</strong>, Durham University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Hartmut Hoehle</strong>, University of Mannheim</p>
        
        <p><strong>Anik Mukherjee</strong>, Indian Institute of Management</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The origins of generative AI (GAI) can be traced back to the 1950s, when Alan Turing proposed a test to determine whether a machine could be perceived as intelligent enough to generate responses to questions in a way indistinguishable from a human. Later, in the 1970s, researchers developed more advanced models capable of producing more realistic and coherent outcomes. Contemporary GAI models are based on state-of-the-art neural network architectures. They combine such architectures to develop large models that outperform existing benchmarked ones. Contemporary GAI solutions can produce large amounts of contextual outputs on any specific topic. They are highly trained and sophisticated, enabling users to produce various types of AI-generated content. Although GAI has been around for a while, recent developments have brought the potential of such solutions to the forefront. In particular, LLMs have the potential to transform the way we develop textual content and communicate with one another.</p>
    
    <p>The ongoing discourse on GAI seems to extol the promises of AI and the dangers. Our goal for this Special Issue is to offer a careful examination of the challenges faced in managing this powerful set of technologies for individuals, organizations, and society. Many of the challenges around GAI concern data. As per a Forbes report, over 90% of internet data will be produced by GAI models, triggering serious concerns about harmful and abusive content generation. Most current GAI-triggered use involves chat-based digital assistants. While the outcome of GAI in these digital assistant-based applications is indeed remarkable, their effectiveness depends on the level of task specificity and the need for information synthesis.</p>
    
    <p>At the individual level, a number of challenges exist on how to effectively use GAI to augment individual productivity. For instance, how can GAI-based interactions positively or negatively affect customer experiences, how can GAI augment (vs. replace) human skills, and broader questions of how over-reliance on GAI systems may adversely impact the cognitive inability of users and learners. At the organizational level, there are many challenges around governance. For instance, how can we govern the quality of content by GAI, how can the adoption of GAI lead to disruption, how do we set up appropriate governance structures to manage GAI projects, and how can we avoid unintended consequences of GAI adoption in firms? At the societal level, there are extensive challenges around misinformation, bias, and privacy. Our broad goal for the special issue is to attract papers that articulate the challenges theoretically and study them empirically, while making a strong contribution to the theory and practice in the deployment of GAI.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Challenges in managing GAI for individuals, organizations, and society</li>
        
        <li>Impact of GAI on individual productivity and customer experiences</li>
        
        <li>Governance challenges related to content quality generated by GAI</li>
        
        <li>Misinformation and privacy issues at the societal level</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>August 31, 2024: Article Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>November 30, 2024: First Review</li>
        
        <li>July 31, 2026: Article Final Decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Shahriar Akter</strong>, University of Wollongong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hillol Bala</strong>, Indiana University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kevin Bauer</strong>, University of Mannheim</li>
        
        <li><strong>Roberta Bernardi</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michael Chau</strong>, The University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alain Chong</strong>, University of Nottingham Ningbo China</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kieran Conboy</strong>, National University of Ireland Galway</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yogesh Dwivedi</strong>, Swansea University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Amany Elbanna</strong>, Royal Holloway University of London</li>
        
        <li><strong>Weiguo (Patrick) Fan</strong>, University of Iowa</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sumeet Gupta</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Raipur</li>
        
        <li><strong>Karlheinz Kautz</strong>, RMIT University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stan Karaniosis</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yeongin Kim</strong>, Virginia Commonwealth</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ajay Kumar</strong>, EM Lyon</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marijn Janssen</strong>, TU Delft</li>
        
        <li><strong>Agam Gupta</strong>, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shivam Gupta</strong>, NEOMA Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Taha Havakhor</strong>, McGill University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mary Lacity</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xin (Robert) Luo</strong>, University of New Mexico</li>
        
        <li><strong>Patrick Mikalef</strong>, Norwegian University of Science &amp; Tech</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ilias O Pappas</strong>, University of Agder</li>
        
        <li><strong>Uthaysankar Sivarajah</strong>, University of Bradford</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kai Spohrer</strong>, Frankfurt School of Finance and Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sujeet Sharma</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Nagpur</li>
        
        <li><strong>Samuel Fosso Wamba</strong>, Toulouse Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Amber Young</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Health Analytics and IS Theorizing]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-health-analytics-and-theorizing</link>
            <guid>jais-health-analytics-and-theorizing</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 12:50:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Aaron Baird</strong>, Georgia State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yusen Xia</strong>, Georgia State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Kohli</strong>, William &amp; Mary</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The objective of this special issue is to showcase how health analytics can be used to enhance theorizing in the field of IS. In addition to its contribution to deep analysis, the power of health analytics research lies in theory development that leverages the unique context of health care. Specifically, the special issue aims to foster research that addresses the question: How can the application and design of analytics methods identify insights from health data and extend IS theory?</p>
    
    <p>This special issue places analytics at the forefront of IS research so that health care researchers can make a theoretical contribution to IS research. Through this special issue, we hope to provide an opportunity for emerging and innovative health analytics research to be published that will showcase how new forms and combinations of theoretical reasoning, methods, and data can contribute to theory building. Our hope is that this special issue will contribute to deeper descriptions, explanations, and predictions of emerging health phenomena relevant to IS scholars as well as demonstrate to clinicians and patients opportunities that will enrich health care management and delivery. We welcome research at the intersection of traditional and emerging approaches, exploratory research, phenomenon-based research, novel methods, and data from any relevant source (with IRB approval, as needed). While we are open to discoveries of all kinds, we expect application of rigorous methods, presentation of persuasive reasoning, and inclusion of strong evidence.</p>
    
    <p>Health analytics can be generally described as generating insights from health data through analysis. Significant and impactful work in health analytics is emerging in the IS literature, but there are also significant opportunities to leverage health analytics research to contribute to theorizing in IS. For instance, while interesting findings within IS have been presented in the context of health analytics use in hospitals and clinical diagnostics or care, many health analytics research contexts have yet to be exploited in IS research. The diversity of data and contexts within which to conduct health analytics research is substantial and such diversity is currently underrepresented in IS journals. We propose that health analytics research can advance beyond presentation of context specific models and methods. We see considerable promise in applying such innovative approaches to the enhancement of IS theory, particularly in explaining IS-enabled mechanisms, through research conducted in the health analytics context.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Heterogenous treatment effects in areas such as health care performance, social determinants of health, use of patient generated health data, and offering or pricing of health care, pharmaceutical, medical device, or insurance products.</li>
        
        <li>AI/ML based tools that can reduce information asymmetry, improve decision-making, or optimize information flows.</li>
        
        <li>Unstructured data analysis, such as of digital trace data, images, or user-generated content, that yields insights about topical or trend dynamics.</li>
        
        <li>Impact of, or disparities in, health analytic capabilities or investments by hospitals, clinics, or less frequently considered entities such as laboratories, pharmacies, medical device manufacturers, public health agencies, or charitable organizations.</li>
        
        <li>Integration of personal device data to analyze trends, identify public health issues, and efficacy of treatments.</li>
        
        <li>Any interesting or creative area we have yet to research in-depth in IS, such as topics in genomics, signal processing/telemetry, clinical trials, or epidemiology.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>February 1, 2023: Extended abstract submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2023: Extended abstract decision</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2023: 1st round full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2023: 1st round full paper decision</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2024: 2nd round full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2024: 2nd round full paper decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Corey Angst</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hilal Atasoy</strong>, Rutgers University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sezgin Ayabakan</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ofir Ben Assuli</strong>, Tel Aviv University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sangeeta Shah Bharadwaj</strong>, Management Development Institute</li>
        
        <li><strong>Langtao Chen</strong>, Missouri University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yichen Cheng</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anton Ivanov</strong>, University of Illinois</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juhee Kwon</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nakyung Kyung</strong>, National University of Singapore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Oklahoma</li>
        
        <li><strong>Abhay Mishra</strong>, Iowa State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sunil Mithas</strong>, University of South Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Min-Seok Pang</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sujeet Sharma</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Tiruchirappalli</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sriram Somanchi</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Junbo Son</strong>, University of Delaware</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ankita Srivastava</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Monica Tremblay</strong>, William &amp; Mary</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hongyi Zhu</strong>, The University of Texas at San Antonio</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Blockchain Technology and Applications]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/dss-blockchain-technology-and-applications</link>
            <guid>dss-blockchain-technology-and-applications</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 06:37:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Shaokun Fan</strong>, Oregon State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Noyan Ilk</strong>, Florida State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Akhil Kumar</strong>, Penn State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>J. Leon Zhao</strong>, Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shenzhen</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Blockchain technology has received enormous attention since Bitcoin was launched in 2009 and has become the frontier of technology advancements and application innovations in recent years. In particular, blockchain is now recognized as a critical part of the new ABCD of modern technology, that is, Artificial intelligence, Blockchain, Cloud computing, and big Data. However, many research challenges and opportunities remain to be tackled and surmounted in areas such as blockchain infrastructure decentralization, blockchain network governance, blockchain security and privacy, and the nature of machine trust in blockchain-based systems. Because blockchain is an integral part of automated business processes, the implementation of this technology can vary greatly between organizations across different industries.</p>
    
    <p>The aim of this special issue is to highlight novel and high-quality research in blockchain technology and applications, and to examine the current and future impact of blockchain systems, and related technologies including data verification before block confirmation, authentication of data ownership, and dataflow across blockchain systems. Considering the decision-making focus of DSS publications that bridge the gap between managerial and technical perspectives, this special issue is open to all manuscripts that make a significant research contribution to blockchain systems and applications in business sectors such as finance, insurance, healthcare, manufacturing, supply chain, education, and government.</p>
    
    <p>In terms of research paradigm, we invite manuscripts with system-based implications that draw on various analytical, empirical, and technical methodologies including, but not limited to, system development, econometrics, decision theory, operations management, experimentation, and engineering. We strongly encourage submissions that follow a design science research perspective, which aims to develop cutting-edge IT artifacts. That is, all technical and quantitative research methods that are helpful in tackling real-world challenges confronted by managers, engineers, and researchers via blockchain technology are welcome.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Process-aware blockchain design and management</li>
        
        <li>Blockchain applications in metaverse platforms</li>
        
        <li>Design and implementation issues in the transition from PoW to PoS</li>
        
        <li>Data management issues on the blockchain</li>
        
        <li>Security and privacy issues on the blockchain</li>
        
        <li>Design and implementation issues of Metaverse systems</li>
        
        <li>Integration of blockchain into existing business infrastructure</li>
        
        <li>Modeling, design and implementation of trust mechanisms in blockchain-based systems</li>
        
        <li>New and faster consensus algorithms for blockchain implementation</li>
        
        <li>NFT analysis and design paradigms in various business sectors</li>
        
        <li>Blockchain-based NFT casting models and mechanisms</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>October 15, 2022: Submissions System opens</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2023: Paper Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>January 30, 2023: Initial Screening of Submissions</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2023: First Review Decisions</li>
        
        <li>June 30, 2023: Revision Due</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2023: Acceptance Decisions</li>
        
        <li>November 15, 2023: Final Manuscript Due</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Michael Adams</strong>, Queensland University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Arthur Carvalho</strong>, Miami University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Daning Hu</strong>, South University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Qiqi Jiang</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jiewu Leng</strong>, Guangdong University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rong Liu</strong>, Stevens Institute</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xin Luo</strong>, The University of New Mexico</li>
        
        <li><strong>Chih-Hung Peng</strong>, National Chengchi University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zhe Shan</strong>, Miami University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hemang Subramanian</strong>, Florida International University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yinliang Tan</strong>, University of Houston</li>
        
        <li><strong>Chih-Ping Wei</strong>, National Taiwan University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ling Xue</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wenping Zhang</strong>, Remin University of China</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xi Zhao</strong>, Xi&#39;an Jiaotong University</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Decision Support Systems (DSS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Responsibility: Social, Ethical, and Ecological Implications of IS]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-digital-responsibility-social-ethical-and-ecological-implications-of-is</link>
            <guid>jais-digital-responsibility-social-ethical-and-ecological-implications-of-is</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 06:37:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Jan Recker</strong>, Universität Hamburg</p>
        
        <p><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Janina Sundermeier</strong>, Freie Universität Berlin</p>
        
        <p><strong>Monideepa Tarafdar</strong>, University of Massachusetts Amherst</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Pervasive digitalization has influenced practically all aspects of the human experience and our institutions in business, society, and government. Diverse areas such as organizational management and strategy, urban affairs and city planning, healthcare, entertainment, safety, politics, and transportation have all been inexorably shaped by digital technologies. Such technologies have created non-trivial and non-reversible changes to our individual and collective behaviors, our institutions and organizations, as well as to human society and our planet at large. But with great power also comes great responsibility. The transformational changes from digitalization are neither unequivocally positive nor negative; more often than not, they are laden with ethical tensions between the contrasting outcomes they engender. For example, personal data digitalization can help individuals live longer and heal their lives, but it also challenges individual rights, obligations, and our sense of dignity. Social media allows us greater connectivity and access, upholding the democratic principle of collective voice, but also becomes a vehicle for manipulating public opinion and spreading fake news and falsehood. Emerging technologies such as shared electric vehicles are coining a revolution in the mobility and energy sector, but also increase fears of labor substitution. The datafication of everyday behaviors has led to new healthcare opportunities but also increased surveillance. The wide embracement of Artificial Intelligence (AI) propels new opportunities for automation and decision-making, but also raises thorny ethical issues in terms of accountability, privacy, fairness, discrimination, and further biases. These observations surface the fact that digital technologies invoke competing narratives: the transformational and innovative powers of digital technologies often contrast dysfunctional outcomes of digitalization, such as social endangerment or loss of human voice and autonomy. While digital technologies promise an exciting future, we have been cautioned that “the journey to the fully pervasive digitized world is also likely to be perilous” and “as much as the potential benefits of digital technology are real, so too are the risks and complexity that ride with them.” Therefore, the key question that we must ask is: how can we positively leverage the transformational powers of digital technologies without falling prey to their possible dysfunctional outcomes? We believe that the answer to this complex question partly lies in the consideration of an important construct: responsibility. Responsibility allows us to evaluate transformational digital technologies in a balanced manner, by factoring in both harmful and positive outcomes from the engagement with such artifacts. Responsibility has become a salient term in this digital age, inspiring new streams of research such as corporate digital responsibility and responsible innovation. Forcing us to engage in meta-ethical reflection, responsibility is crucial to addressing some of the dysfunctional outcomes associated with the rapid proliferation of digital technologies – thus allowing for normative action consistent with human values and ethical defensibility. As information systems researchers, it must be on us to better understand the concept of responsibility as it pertains to the enablement of positive outcomes of the ongoing digitalization of our everyday lives while safeguarding the human experience against possible negative consequences of the same. We term this concept “digital responsibility”, which we believe can serve as an organizing construct of research that aims to inform the balancing of ethical and humanistic tensions pertaining to the rapid proliferation of digital technologies. Notably, focusing on digital responsibility allows us to challenge the often-embraced utopic narrative of digitalization – thus problematizing our vision for this special issue. Digital responsibility is antithetical to “mindlessness” in designing and implementing digital technologies, which is often associated with the inability “to cope gracefully with changing, complex situations characteristic of high-risk domains.” The lens of digital responsibility necessitates that we embark upon rigorously analyzing, explaining, predicting, as well as influencing, the potential costs, duties, and obligations of decisions that relate to the development, implementation, and use of digital information and communication technologies. Following such observations, unpacking the phenomenon of “digital responsibility” should be of utmost concern to IS researchers – and this is the central theme of this special issue.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Designing and using digital technologies for and with responsibility</li>
        
        <li>Considerations of accountability, liability, fairness, and/or responsibility for digital technology design, implementation, and use</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical perspectives and/or empirical insights on the (un)intended social, ethical, and ecological consequences of digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical underpinnings of the concept of digital responsibility, such as from an ethical theory perspective</li>
        
        <li>Design of digital technology to address social, ethical, and/or ecological challenges</li>
        
        <li>Individual, organizational, institutional, or societal strategies for leveraging IS for social, ethical, and/or ecological challenges and innovations</li>
        
        <li>The role of digital technology in promoting social, ethical, and ecological advancements</li>
        
        <li>Applications of emerging digital technologies (e.g., AI) to social, ethical, and/or ecological realms</li>
        
        <li>Societal, ethical, and ecological consequences of emerging digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>(Un-)ethical issues of IS and the data they generate</li>
        
        <li>Dignity, respect, and moral behavior in a digital world</li>
        
        <li>Social support and inclusion enabled by or embodied in digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>The balance of contradicting implications of IS (e.g., IS as a means for social change vs. IS for manipulating public opinion)</li>
        
        <li>The affordances of existing and emerging digital technologies for enacting digital responsibility</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 3, 2023: Deadline for paper submissions</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2024: First-round review decisions</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2024: Hybrid Paper development workshop</li>
        
        <li>July 11, 2024: Deadline for submission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2024: Second-round review decisions</li>
        
        <li>December 8, 2024: Deadline for submission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2025: Provisional decision and final round of comments</li>
        
        <li>February 27, 2025: Deadline for submission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2025: Notification of final decisions</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Jose Benitez</strong>, EDHEC Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Benlian</strong>, TU Darmstadt</li>
        
        <li><strong>Roberta Bernardi</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michelle Carter</strong>, Washington State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dubravka Cecez-Kecmanovic</strong>, University of New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>John D&#39;Arcy</strong>, University of Delaware</li>
        
        <li><strong>James Gaskin</strong>, Brigham Young University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Oliver Laasch</strong>, ESCP Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shan Pan</strong>, University of New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hannes Rothe</strong>, University of Duisburg-Essen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Saonee Sarker</strong>, Lund University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Olgerta Tona</strong>, University of Gothenburg</li>
        
        <li><strong>John Tripp</strong>, Clemson University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tuure Tuunanen</strong>, University Jyväskylä</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>