<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: ethics</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/ethics</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers tagged with 'ethics'.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 03:40:40 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: ethics</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/ethics</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ethics, Regulation, and Policy]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/misq-ethics-regulation-and-policy</link>
            <guid>misq-ethics-regulation-and-policy</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 03:16:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Stefan Seidel</strong>, University of Cologne</p>
        
        <p><strong>Nicholas Berente</strong>, University of Notre Dame</p>
        
        <p><strong>Hong Guo</strong>, Arizona State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Wonseok Oh</strong>, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Wave upon wave of digital technologies and the fast-advancing frontier of artificial intelligence (AI) are disrupting well-established, institutionalized ways of doing things, resulting in a host of ethical, regulatory, and policy challenges. The challenge involves addressing social, ecological, moral, and economic risks associated with technological advancements while, at the same time, encouraging competitiveness, innovation, and value generation from ubiquitous digital data. To address current ethical challenges and risks and anticipate future issues related to emerging technologies, governments are seeking to adjust regulations and set policy. Organizations are seeking to adapt their governance schemes to regulatory and ethical issues. This special issue seeks sociotechnical and information systems contributions to our thinking on ethics, regulation, and policy around digital technologies, data, and AI.</p>
    
    <p>Ethical tensions abound in relation to the pervasiveness of digital data and the widespread adoption of AI, including tensions between data privacy, fairness, and bias on the one hand, and business needs for using data for market and innovation purposes on the other. AI systems that increasingly replace cognitive tasks previously done by humans raise questions about deskilling and labor substitution and ultimately human dignity. While AI systems promise productivity gains and the potential to address key social and environmental issues, they also generate significant threats to sustainability and social challenges. Moreover, the responsibility of algorithms for the tasks they perform and the decisions they make is often not clear. The autonomy, interconnectedness, and increasing agency of digital technologies present challenges to established individualistic responsibility approaches since they make it difficult to attribute responsibility.</p>
    
    <p>The tension between addressing ethical risks and encouraging innovation requires balancing data privacy, fairness, and bias concerns with business needs for competitiveness and value generation from digital data and AI systems. Ethical challenges have inspired regulatory and policy action around digital technologies, particularly with respect to data and AI. The United States National Artificial Intelligence Act of 2020 sets forth programs and activities and highlights values like trustworthiness; at the same time, it aims at creating competitive advantage for the US economy by aiming at creating an innovation ecosystem or fostering public-private partnership mechanisms. The European Union&#39;s AI Act embeds fundamental values as it seeks to accomplish &quot;a high level of protection of health, safety, fundamental rights&quot; and defines requirements for transparency monitoring, market surveillance, governance that provide legitimacy for the use of AI systems.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Technology/AI/data ethics</li>
        
        <li>Technology/AI/data regulation</li>
        
        <li>Technology/AI/data policy</li>
        
        <li>Governance</li>
        
        <li>Organizational challenges in regulatory compliance</li>
        
        <li>Value generation from digital data</li>
        
        <li>Sustainable development and technology regulation</li>
        
        <li>Ethical challenges and governance</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 13, 2026: Submission Deadline</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Alessandro Acquisti</strong>, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Benlian</strong>, Technical University of Darmstadt</li>
        
        <li><strong>Min Chen</strong>, George Mason University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aaron Cheng</strong>, The London School of Economics and Political Science</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ioanna Constantiou</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>John Dong</strong>, Nanyang Technological University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anna Essén</strong>, Stockholm School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Haiyang Feng</strong>, Tianjin University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stefan Feuerriegel</strong>, Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich</li>
        
        <li><strong>Uri Gal</strong>, The University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>James Gaskin</strong>, Brigham Young University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Goh Khim Yong</strong>, National University of Singapore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anand Gopal</strong>, Nanyang Technological University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Brad Greenwood</strong>, George Mason University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dominik Gutt</strong>, RWTH Aachen University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ola Henfridsson</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nina Huang</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jannis Kallinikos</strong>, The London School of Economics and Political Science</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gerald C (Jerry) Kane</strong>, University of Georgia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wolf Ketter</strong>, University of Cologne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Cameron Kormylo</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Natalia Levina</strong>, New York University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zhepeng (Lionel) Li</strong>, The University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kalle Lyytinen</strong>, Case Western Reserve University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Min-Seok Pang</strong>, University of Wisconsin-Madison</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hani Safadi</strong>, University of Georgia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nachiketa Sahoo</strong>, Boston University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Monash University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mari-Klara Stein</strong>, TalTech</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lai Wei</strong>, Shanghai Jiao Tong University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yi Yang</strong>, The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lior Zalmanson</strong>, Tel Aviv University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nan Zhang</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xia Zhao</strong>, University of Georgia</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>MIS Quarterly (MISQ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ethical Issues and Unintended Consequences of Digitalization and Platformization]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-ethical-issues-and-unintended-consequences-of-digitalization-and-platformization</link>
            <guid>jit-ethical-issues-and-unintended-consequences-of-digitalization-and-platformization</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:30:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Matti Rossi</strong>, Aalto University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Christy M. K. Cheung</strong>, Hong Kong Baptist University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Supratek Sarker</strong>, University of Virginia</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jason B. Thatcher</strong>, Temple University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Disruptive digital innovations do not come without pain – the disorder that they introduce can create negative externalities and unintended consequences for people, communities, industries and economies. In the worst case, there is disruption with little innovation. This can lead to job losses for individuals, loss of human dignity, negative health impacts, lost revenue for communities, obsolescence of industries and loss of the traditional values that underpin modern societies.</p>
    
    <p>Sarker et al. (2019) note that “humanistic concerns arising from the curtailing of human freedom and development, and from racism, sexism and commodification of the human body are overlooked for the apparent benefits that systems, including widely used search engines and medical databases, promise to deliver (Noble 2018; Wachter-Boettcher 2017). Indeed, there is a rising need for a thorough ethical interrogation of algorithms (O’Neil 2016) that underlie systems mediating many critical human activities, so as not to marginalize certain stakeholders, especially those ‘who are already in the margin’ (Noble 2018, p. 171).</p>
    
    <p>In this special issue, we take this critical, yet constructive view of technological and social changes associated with “digital transformation” (Zuboff 2015, Wood et al. 2019, Larsson and Teigland 2020). We are interested in contrarian papers that reject the taken-for-granted assumptions of positive impacts of technology, as in cases of digital platforms, telework enabled by mobility, growth of the gig economy, fintech/blockchain, and so on, and investigate relatively unexamined platform externalities as a means to identify ways to resolve paradoxes, discontinuities and challenges posed by technology and the unintended consequences of technology applications.</p>
    
    <p>We also seek papers that shed light on the problems of information technology (IT)-enabled phenomena such as the implications of winner-takes-all platform economics; highlight the social, environmental and economic implications of blockchain and similar innovative digital technologies; or propose solutions that mitigate negative societal impacts of innovation (e.g., through leveraging the power social networks to disseminate information and strengthen democratic discourse).</p>
    
    <p>We encourage the submission of manuscripts taking either of two stances: 1) Submissions considering a critical or dystopian view of the social, technological and moral implications of digitization and digital transformation. Here, “the dark side” – ethical issues, unintended digitalization and other problematic aspects – of digitalization and platformization are front and centre the argument. An example may be Zuboff’s (2015, 2019) recent work on surveillance capitalism and her analyses of large-scale digitization “gone wrong”. 2) Submissions seeking to balance or reconcile “the dark side” and “the bright side” of digitalization and platformization. Here, analyses, exemplars and theoretical frameworks considered ethical issues and negative consequences explicitly, in addition to intended benefits of digitalization too often exclusively focused on. An example may be social media research: initial writings trumpeted the benefits of social media for building relationships, with later work highlighting problematic behaviours such as cyberbullying or doxxing.</p>
    
    <p>In this special issue, we are open to all forms of inquiry, including surveys, experiments, case studies, design science projects and conceptual work that probe “the dark side”, ethical issues and unintended consequences of digitization, platformization and the rapid diffusion of digital infrastructures and digital work models based thereon.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Digital Taylorism and the race to the bottom for workers</li>
        
        <li>Destruction of jobs by “botization”</li>
        
        <li>Risks for society from fast-spreading false information</li>
        
        <li>Systemic risks and vulnerability of digital platforms</li>
        
        <li>Management incompetence in digital transformation</li>
        
        <li>Risks of IoT and blockchain</li>
        
        <li>Dark side and ethics of sharing economy and gig economy</li>
        
        <li>Digital privacy and surveillance capitalism</li>
        
        <li>Bias in algorithms and artificial intelligence</li>
        
        <li>Digital inequity and digital divide between “the North” and “the South”</li>
        
        <li>Fake news, misinformation, and disinformation in social media</li>
        
        <li>Fake and biased online reviews and co-creation on digital platforms</li>
        
        <li>The emergence of deep web/dark net marketplaces</li>
        
        <li>Subjective well-being (e.g., FOMO and social media fatigue)</li>
        
        <li>Cyberharassment, cyberbullying and cyberstalking</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>June 1, 2021: First round submission</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2021: First round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2022: Second round submission</li>
        
        <li>April 1, 2022: Second round decision to authors (reject or accept with minor revision)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Margunn Aanestad</strong>, Agder University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Benlian</strong>, TU Darmstadt</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michelle Carter</strong>, Washington State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tommy Chan</strong>, Northumbria University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mike Dinger</strong>, University of South Carolina - Upstate</li>
        
        <li><strong>Taha Havakor</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>J. J. Po - An Hsieh</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hanna Krasnova</strong>, University of Potsdam</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, UNSW Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alvin Leung</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juho Lindman</strong>, University of Gothenburg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jani Merikivi</strong>, Grenoble Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Daniel Pienta</strong>, Baylor University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marten Risius</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Markus Salo</strong>, University of Jyvaskyla</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sebastian Schuetz</strong>, Florida International University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carsten Sorensen</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ali Sunyaev</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Lancaster University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Manuel Trenz</strong>, University of Göttingen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Xiao Xiao</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>