<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: health analytics</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/health-analytics</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers tagged with 'health analytics'.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 03:04:13 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: health analytics</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/health-analytics</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Health Analytics and IS Theorizing]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-health-analytics-and-theorizing</link>
            <guid>jais-health-analytics-and-theorizing</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 12:50:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Aaron Baird</strong>, Georgia State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yusen Xia</strong>, Georgia State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Kohli</strong>, William &amp; Mary</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The objective of this special issue is to showcase how health analytics can be used to enhance theorizing in the field of IS. In addition to its contribution to deep analysis, the power of health analytics research lies in theory development that leverages the unique context of health care. Specifically, the special issue aims to foster research that addresses the question: How can the application and design of analytics methods identify insights from health data and extend IS theory?</p>
    
    <p>This special issue places analytics at the forefront of IS research so that health care researchers can make a theoretical contribution to IS research. Through this special issue, we hope to provide an opportunity for emerging and innovative health analytics research to be published that will showcase how new forms and combinations of theoretical reasoning, methods, and data can contribute to theory building. Our hope is that this special issue will contribute to deeper descriptions, explanations, and predictions of emerging health phenomena relevant to IS scholars as well as demonstrate to clinicians and patients opportunities that will enrich health care management and delivery. We welcome research at the intersection of traditional and emerging approaches, exploratory research, phenomenon-based research, novel methods, and data from any relevant source (with IRB approval, as needed). While we are open to discoveries of all kinds, we expect application of rigorous methods, presentation of persuasive reasoning, and inclusion of strong evidence.</p>
    
    <p>Health analytics can be generally described as generating insights from health data through analysis. Significant and impactful work in health analytics is emerging in the IS literature, but there are also significant opportunities to leverage health analytics research to contribute to theorizing in IS. For instance, while interesting findings within IS have been presented in the context of health analytics use in hospitals and clinical diagnostics or care, many health analytics research contexts have yet to be exploited in IS research. The diversity of data and contexts within which to conduct health analytics research is substantial and such diversity is currently underrepresented in IS journals. We propose that health analytics research can advance beyond presentation of context specific models and methods. We see considerable promise in applying such innovative approaches to the enhancement of IS theory, particularly in explaining IS-enabled mechanisms, through research conducted in the health analytics context.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Heterogenous treatment effects in areas such as health care performance, social determinants of health, use of patient generated health data, and offering or pricing of health care, pharmaceutical, medical device, or insurance products.</li>
        
        <li>AI/ML based tools that can reduce information asymmetry, improve decision-making, or optimize information flows.</li>
        
        <li>Unstructured data analysis, such as of digital trace data, images, or user-generated content, that yields insights about topical or trend dynamics.</li>
        
        <li>Impact of, or disparities in, health analytic capabilities or investments by hospitals, clinics, or less frequently considered entities such as laboratories, pharmacies, medical device manufacturers, public health agencies, or charitable organizations.</li>
        
        <li>Integration of personal device data to analyze trends, identify public health issues, and efficacy of treatments.</li>
        
        <li>Any interesting or creative area we have yet to research in-depth in IS, such as topics in genomics, signal processing/telemetry, clinical trials, or epidemiology.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>February 1, 2023: Extended abstract submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2023: Extended abstract decision</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2023: 1st round full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2023: 1st round full paper decision</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2024: 2nd round full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2024: 2nd round full paper decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Corey Angst</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hilal Atasoy</strong>, Rutgers University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sezgin Ayabakan</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ofir Ben Assuli</strong>, Tel Aviv University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sangeeta Shah Bharadwaj</strong>, Management Development Institute</li>
        
        <li><strong>Langtao Chen</strong>, Missouri University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yichen Cheng</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anton Ivanov</strong>, University of Illinois</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juhee Kwon</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nakyung Kyung</strong>, National University of Singapore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Oklahoma</li>
        
        <li><strong>Abhay Mishra</strong>, Iowa State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sunil Mithas</strong>, University of South Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Min-Seok Pang</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sujeet Sharma</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Tiruchirappalli</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sriram Somanchi</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Junbo Son</strong>, University of Delaware</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ankita Srivastava</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Monica Tremblay</strong>, William &amp; Mary</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hongyi Zhu</strong>, The University of Texas at San Antonio</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>