<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: information behaviour</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/information-behaviour</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers tagged with 'information behaviour'.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 03:37:46 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: information behaviour</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/information-behaviour</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Theory and Practice of Informational Transitions]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jasist-the-theory-and-practice-of-informational-transitions</link>
            <guid>jasist-the-theory-and-practice-of-informational-transitions</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:25:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Jenny Bronstein</strong>, Bar-Ilan University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Alison Hicks</strong>, University College London</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jette Hyldegård</strong>, University of Copenhagen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Pam McKenzie</strong>, The University of Western Ontario</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ian Ruthven</strong>, University of Strathclyde</p>
        
        <p><strong>Gunilla Widén</strong>, Åbo Akademi</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Life transitions forms a rich area of scholarship for Information Science research. The last five years have seen a steady growth in the publication of empirical studies related to transition, including PhD work and longitudinal studies, in a variety of areas including health, social, academic and employment contexts. At the same time, emerging conceptual work has also started to re-examine transition through a historical lens, including how change and adjustment has been treated in historical Information Science scholarship. This adds significant scope for complex conceptual work. The breadth of interest further means that transition has the potential to unify various related fields of study, including information behaviour, practice, and literacy research as well as various disciplinary fields. This Special Issue will provide a platform for the exploration of life transitions from an information behaviour, information practice, or information literacy perspective.</p>
    
    <p>Transitions are a natural state in everyday life. In a broader sense, individuals could be said to be in a constant state of transition, or &#39;transitioning&#39; with every passage in life. According to the Oxford English Dictionary, transition is defined both as a noun and adverb: &#39;A passing or passage from one condition, action, or (rarely) place, to another; change&#39; and, &#39;To make or undergo a transition (from one state, system, etc. to or into another); to change over or switch.&#39; From a research perspective, transition is a complex topic that has been variously conceptualised and defined. Transitions can be personal (changes due to changes in life cycle), situational (changes in circumstances in personal or professional life), or environmental (changes in the organisational environment impacting individuals). These emphases mean that transition has been most comprehensively explored to date within the field of Education and Nursing.</p>
    
    <p>Conceptual work in these areas has focused on the process through which people in transition move beyond a disrupted reality to construct a new reality. Information has been found to be a strong trigger in the transition process. Transitions fracture the individual’s information landscapes and require them to learn new &#39;ways of knowing&#39;, a process that often requires both seeking and avoiding information as a coping mechanism to reduce uncertainty.</p>
    
    <p>Although transitions are permeated with information practices of many kinds, information behaviour/practices/literacy research has engaged only peripherally with ideas of transition and the concept remains underexplored. Consequently, the aim of this special issue is to extend these initial explorations of transition through an information lens. We invite empirical, conceptual or methodological submissions for this special issue that address one or more of these questions:</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>How should transition be conceptualised, studied, evaluated within the field of information behaviour, information practice or information literacy?</li>
        
        <li>What is the role of information and information activities, including information avoidance, in a transition?</li>
        
        <li>What models, theories and concepts from Information Science and beyond are useful for studying transitions?</li>
        
        <li>What research methods/methodologies can we use to study transition?</li>
        
        <li>What types of life transitions exist and how can they be conceptualised in information behaviour, information practice or information literacy?</li>
        
        <li>What informational strategies might support transitions?</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>September 13, 2023: Paper development workshop</li>
        
        <li>June 13, 2024: Submissions due</li>
        
        <li>September 11, 2024: Decisions after first round of reviews</li>
        
        <li>November 1, 2025: Special Issue to be published</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology (JASIST)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>