<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: information systems</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/information-systems</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers tagged with 'information systems'.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 03:06:48 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: information systems</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/information-systems</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Algorithmic Assemblages—Fields, Ecosystems, and Platforms: An Interpretive Approach]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/io-algorithmic-assemblagesfields-ecosystems-and-platforms-an-interpretive-approach</link>
            <guid>io-algorithmic-assemblagesfields-ecosystems-and-platforms-an-interpretive-approach</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 03:15:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Hannigan, Timothy</strong>, University of Ottawa</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jennings, P. Devereaux</strong>, University of Alberta</p>
        
        <p><strong>Miranda, Shaila</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Faraj, Samer</strong>, McGill University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This Special Issue is devoted to interpretive approaches to studying algorithmic assemblages constitutive of and by fields, ecosystems, and platforms and combining research from an organizational and information systems view about such organizing features and their dynamics. Information technologies have progressively enabled, even necessitated, a shift in the locus of value creation, capture, and resource orchestration and the processes they entail from within organizations to these more loosely coupled and emergently structured sociotechnical systems. The interpretive approach broadly stems from the relational turn in organization theory, but more proximately, considers assemblages and algorithmic organizing as views of these key constructs and their associated processes. To date, there has been less theory-building and empirical research connecting these more mezzo and macro constructs with the more micro-dynamics of these systems. In particular, it is not clear how algorithmic technologies enable the discursive and material interconnections of organizational ecosystems and facilitate the legitimacy dynamics of institutional fields. Nor is it clear the ways in which algorithmic technologies differentially circumscribe meaning across global fields and societies.</p>
    
    <p>For example, blockchain communities contain organizational imaginaries around decentralized organization, and ongoing work is needed to examine how protocols are governed and established as new “rules of the game” and how community discourses around digital technologies shape institutional fields. Relatedly, the metaverse offers novel opportunities for commerce, government, and society within emerging ecosystems. Similarly, for AI technologies it is important to parse through the rhetoric and reality of how field level discourse influences organizational adoption and vice versa. As quantum computing threatens to disrupt our digital world, it is important to understand the broad material, social, and cultural ecosystem with the potential to reshape global business and geopolitics. To examine the institutional dynamics of technologically mediated organizing, it is necessary to methodologically zoom in and out with configurations to examine how realities are constructed based on shared meanings and interpretations.</p>
    
    <p>To unpack these dynamics around technology-based and –mediated fields, ecosystems and platform we call for theory and research that relies on relational approaches coming from both organization theory and information systems. In those approaches, we see how theories of assemblages and algorithmic organizing, when combined with more traditional organizational views such as of routines and institutions, offer powerful new ways of thinking about these dynamics.</p>
    
    <p>The objectives of this Special Issue are twofold. First, we wish to foster the development of cutting-edge research (theory and method) among scholars interested in organizational and institutional studies of the use and effects of data science and algorithms on decision-making. Second, we wish to continue building and strengthening the community of scholars engaged in that work, especially at the intersection of organization theory and information systems. In doing so, we reiterate Orlikowski and Barley’s call for synthesis of information systems and organizational studies scholars’ knowledge trajectories of technology change and institutional contexts. Since their call, there has been a growing convergence between these knowledge trajectories, culminating in studies of how actors remake institutional fields, change power relationships, and construct meanings about technology beyond institutionalized paths.</p>
    
    <p>We can envision a variety of ways in which empirical papers can showcase the way in which interpretive algorithms affect assemblages, ecosystems, and fields. We stand on the shoulders of Barley &amp; Orlikowski (2023:4) and their call for papers that navigate “futures far different from the pasts we have known” with “more in-depth empirical studies and less speculation and hype.”</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Interpretive approaches to studying algorithmic assemblages</li>
        
        <li>Relational theories in organizational and information systems contexts</li>
        
        <li>Empirical research on algorithmic technologies</li>
        
        <li>Intersection of organization theory and information systems</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>August 18, 2025: </li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2026: Submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>October 30, 2026: First round decision letters sent out</li>
        
        <li>February 28, 2027: First round paper resubmissions</li>
        
        <li>May 31, 2027: Second round reviews due</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2027: Second round decision letters sent out</li>
        
        <li>October 15, 2027: Second round paper resubmissions</li>
        
        <li>March 15, 2028: Final papers selected, introductory editorial paper written</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information and Organization (IO)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Designing our Digital Futures: Challenging Current Assumptions and Envisioning the Future of IS Design and Development]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/ejis-designing-our-digital-futures</link>
            <guid>ejis-designing-our-digital-futures</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 04:14:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Leona Chandra Kruse</strong>, University of Agder</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mahdi Fahmideh</strong>, University of Southern Queensland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Brian Fitzgerald</strong>, University of Limerick</p>
        
        <p><strong>Tabitha James</strong>, Virginia Tech</p>
        
        <p><strong>Kieran Conboy</strong>, University of Galway</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Information systems (IS) design and development, heretofore a core topic in the IS field, is arguably at a critical juncture as it faces challenges unlike ever before in its short history. On one hand, there have been significant technological advances in areas such as artificial intelligence, blockchain, quantum computing that potentially provide and require different ways of designing and developing. Complementing this, the ‘digital native’ consumers of new information systems seek rapid continuous delivery of large-scale information systems, tailored to individual needs while delivering responsibly on all aspects such as privacy, fairness and transparency.</p>
    
    <p>At this critical juncture, the goal of this special issue is to consider the next generation of IS design and development. Looking at the present, we invite researchers to challenge the fundamental prevailing assumptions of the field embracing the ‘contrarian’ and ‘pragmatic’ perspectives that underpin the ethos of the European Journal of Information Systems. We welcome papers that question the logic, methods, and tools in contemporary IS design and address topics or take perspectives that some may find uncomfortable. We invite papers that explore alternative approaches and perspectives to the design of digital futures. In addition to examining the immediate future, we encourage researchers that take a ‘Promethean’ perspective examining radically different ways of designing technology, and taking perspectives that are very different or even unrecognisable in comparison to those envisaged by current research and practice.</p>
    
    <p>We invite papers on any and all aspects of IS design and development, but below are some guiding themes related to the call.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>The role of emerging technologies in shaping the future of IS design: AI, blockchain, and quantum computing</li>
        
        <li>The limits of current design and development methods: continuous development and DevOps</li>
        
        <li>Design science beyond the science of the artificial</li>
        
        <li>Design and development in an era of heightened responsibility</li>
        
        <li>The impact of AI on any or all aspects of IS design and development</li>
        
        <li>Contrarian perspectives that challenge assumptions and norms of existing methods</li>
        
        <li>New methods for designing digital futures anchored in IS design and development heritage</li>
        
        <li>Unique perspectives on the consideration and integration of privacy and security by design</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Invalid DateTime: Projected publication</li>
        
        <li>January 30, 2026: Initial paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>April 30, 2026: First round authors notification</li>
        
        <li>August 15, 2026: Invited revisions deadline</li>
        
        <li>November 30, 2026: Second round authors notification</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2027: Final revision deadline</li>
        
        <li>April 1, 2027: Final authors notification</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Pär Ågerfalk</strong>, Uppsala University</li>
        
        <li><strong>David Agogo</strong>, University of Utah</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wasana Bandara</strong>, Queensland University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Richard Baskerville</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Laura Brandimarte</strong>, University of Arizona</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tone Bratteteig</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Noel Carroll</strong>, University of Galway</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shahla Ghobadi</strong>, University of Leeds</li>
        
        <li><strong>Asif Gill</strong>, University of Technology Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shirley Gregor</strong>, Australian National University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Samrat Gupta</strong>, IIM Ahmedabad</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alan Hevner</strong>, University of South Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gwanhoo Lee</strong>, American University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Madche</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sabine Matook</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Lorraine Morgan</strong>, University of Galway</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jeffrey Parsons</strong>, Memorial University of Newfoundland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Bala Ramesh</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Cynthia K. Riemenschneider</strong>, Baylor University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sofia Schöbel</strong>, University of Osnabrück</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yash Shreshta</strong>, University of Lausanne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Thorsten Schoormann</strong>, Roskilde University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Klaas Jan Stol</strong>, University College Cork</li>
        
        <li><strong>Monica Chiarini Tremblay</strong>, William &amp; Mary</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tuure Tuunanen</strong>, University of Jyväskylä</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jan vom Brocke</strong>, University of Münster</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sofie Wass</strong>, University of Agder</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>European Journal of Information Systems (EJIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Futuring: ‘Digital’ Futures as a Novel Site of Inquiry and Imagination]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-futuring-digital-futures-as-a-novel-site-of-inquiry-and-imagination</link>
            <guid>jit-futuring-digital-futures-as-a-novel-site-of-inquiry-and-imagination</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 03:16:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Dirk S. Hovorka</strong>, The University of Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Benjamin Mueller</strong>, University of Bremen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Elizabeth Davidson</strong>, University of Hawaii - Manoa</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mike Chiasson</strong>, University of British Columbia</p>
        
    
    
    <p>What attention do we owe the future(s)? The Information Systems (IS) and adjacent research fields engage with the design, implementation, and evaluation of increasingly powerful digital technologies and with studies of their impact on work, knowledge, sustainability, and organizing. Given the rich and growing body of theories and findings from research on these wide and long-term impacts, the potential for researchers to help envision, inform, critique, and shape how these technologically-infused futures – &#39;digital futures&#39; – develop are immense.</p>
    
    <p>Despite this rich potential, most discussions of the future implications of digitalization in IS research are abstract and nominal, typically assuming a singular &#39;future&#39; will arise from the technological advances studied. Discourses on the future with digital technologies rarely bring the worlds and practices that emerge from, shape, and transform futures to the foreground for a close and critical examination. Similarly, whether or to what extent such worlds and practices will discernibly be digital to any meaningful degree is often just assumed, which focuses our attention on specific aspects that may no longer be salient in futures. As a result, researchers tend to cede these important discussions and considerations to visionaries, technology firms, and &#39;evangelists&#39; in business and consultancy.</p>
    
    <p>To the degree that IS research does consider the future, the implications of digital technologies in the discourse are often contradictory. On the one hand, an optimistic, instrumental view depicts the broad range of technologies as &#39;tools&#39; under social control, which can (and will) produce an economically, socially, and environmentally sustainable future. On the other hand, a substantive view of technology casts technology as dark, uncontrollable forces that (inevitably) result in personal, societal, and environmental distress. For instance, the dominating discussions of AI in research illustrate these contradictory &#39;hopes and fears&#39;. Neither view of technology sufficiently challenges researchers to engage actively with futuring – that is, the envisioning, informing, critiquing, and helping to shape possible futures systematically through research practices. Hence, the purpose and focus of this special issue is on futuring work – active, imaginary, forward-looking research work in IS or related fields that is informing or shaping our &#39;digital&#39; futures.</p>
    
    <p>Research approaches that address the worlds and practices that shape digital possibilities and the multiplicity of futures that could result are possible. These strategies can overcome nominal approaches to considering the future and build on the rich socio-technical positions already present in IS research. To do so, researchers need to consider new ways of futuring that go beyond simple extrapolations of current trends into the future or tacit acceptance of technology’s inevitable path. One way to do so is to loosen the grip of empiricism in IS research and broaden our relationship to futures, for instance, by engaging with speculation and imagination in research, creating speculative engagements with future possibilities, and deconstructing the narratives and expectations of the present. These and other approaches to futuring can be highly significant to what emerging phenomena can be observed, where present-day research interests and practices are directed, and ultimately, what future worlds are realized through the technologies we study.</p>
    
    <p>There is enormous potential for present-day research to consider the futures of lived social life, environmental conditions, and economies with digitalization and technological enactments. To foray into, conceptualize, and perform the variety of futuring approaches, we must take the theoretical, methodological, and philosophical implications of futures seriously in our research. Our goal in this special issue is to encourage researchers in the IS and adjacent managerial fields to do so. The intended types of contributions to this special issue follow the &#39;digital futures&#39; editorial referenced above and encourage submissions with novel contributions within (or across) three main categories: Engaging in Futuring, Envisioning Futures, and Conceptualizing Futures.  Submissions may examine our relationships with short-term events and technologies or with the long, slow shifts in social norms; moral reasoning; and the power, weight, and significance of institutions, practices, and technologies. We encourage consideration of the philosophical bases for connecting past-present-futures, new methods of futuring, and conceptions of the future as a site of inquiry. Traditional futures-studies approaches are welcome insofar as they contribute to the special issue’s goals. The special issue seeks to be inclusive in terms of diverse approaches to futuring and studying digital futures.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Researching futures to inform present theory and action.</li>
        
        <li>Anthropologic, ethnographic, or speculative design approaches.</li>
        
        <li>Ethical futures: what do we owe the future?</li>
        
        <li>Beyond trajectories of the digital: Anticipating and modelling future worlds.</li>
        
        <li>Precautionary principles: guardrails for dual-use technologies?</li>
        
        <li>Socio-technical construction of the future.</li>
        
        <li>Utopias, dystopias, and science fiction as forms of speculative science.</li>
        
        <li>Non-empirical approaches to knowledge.</li>
        
        <li>Bridging epistemic distance.</li>
        
        <li>Digital transformation in a digital world.</li>
        
        <li>Reconceptualizing the organization.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Invalid DateTime: Target publication date.</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2025: AOM workshop introducing special issue.</li>
        
        <li>August 15, 2025: Submit extended abstract for feedback and workshop admission, max 1500 words, via submission system</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2025: Abstracts invited for workshop.</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2025: Special Issue Workshop Hybrid at ICIS 2025 and online (recommended).</li>
        
        <li>February 15, 2026: First round submission deadline.</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2026: First round decision to authors.</li>
        
        <li>October 15, 2026: Second round submission deadline.</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2026: Second round decision to authors. Papers will be accepted or rejected after the second round of peer review.</li>
        
        <li>January 31, 2027: Final revision due (if applicable).</li>
        
        <li>February 28, 2027: Final decision to authors.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Paper Development Workshop]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isj-isj-paper-development-workshop</link>
            <guid>isj-isj-paper-development-workshop</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2025 03:07:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ravi Patnayakuni</strong>, University of Alabama in Huntsville</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yingqin Zheng</strong>, University of Essex</p>
        
        <p><strong>Zhongyun (Phil) Zhou</strong>, Tongji University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Information Systems Journal, as part of its outreach efforts, will be holding a Paper Development Workshop along with the 2025 Pacific-Asia Conference on Information Systems in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. The half-day workshop will be held on Sunday, July 6, 2025, from 8:30 am to 12:30 pm as an in-person pre-conference workshop. ISJ welcomes research that spans across the diverse and interdisciplinary IS field.</p>
    
    <p>The paper development workshop aims to nurture scholarship across the broad spectrum of information systems researchers. We welcome work that examines both established and emerging areas within IS. The workshop aims to provide a supportive environment for researchers to develop their ideas and receive constructive feedback on their work from the journal’s editorial board members. We especially encourage submissions from author(s) planning to submit their work to ISJ’s forthcoming special issue on &#39;Theorising the Impacts of Generative Artificial Intelligence&#39;, which has a submission deadline of December 31, 2025, and any other special issues announced before the workshop deadline.</p>
    
    <p>The workshop welcomes papers at various stages of development, from early conceptual work to papers nearing completion. We encourage submissions that show potential for theoretical or practical contribution to the IS field, regardless of their current stage. The workshop particularly aims to support researchers who would benefit from early guidance and feedback on their work.</p>
    
    <p>Interested authors are invited to submit papers for possible inclusion in the workshop. Papers that have been accepted, under review, or under revision at other journals, workshops, or conferences should not be submitted. Please note that not all submissions received may be accepted. Papers that are not accepted will not receive feedback. The selected papers will be mentored by at least two members of the ISJ Editorial Board. Additionally, attending author(s) of accepted papers may be assigned manuscripts as discussants.</p>
    
    <p>Please note that the workshop is not associated with any publication. The goal is to offer feedback to the authors that can help enhance the quality of the paper as it is prepared for submission to a suitable journal. Authors do not have an obligation to submit the paper to ISJ but are encouraged to submit their completed papers for publication consideration to the journal in the future. Also, please note that participation in the workshop does not imply favorable consideration or outcome at ISJ.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Submissions from PACIS community</li>
        
        <li>Relationship between technology, business, economy, and society</li>
        
        <li>Examining established and emerging areas within Information Systems</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical or practical contribution to the IS field</li>
        
        <li>Support for early-stage researchers</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>May 12, 2025: Submission Begin</li>
        
        <li>May 19, 2025: Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>June 6, 2025: Decisions</li>
        
        <li>July 6, 2025: ISJ Trending Topics Workshop</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Journal (ISJ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Theorising the Impacts of Generative Artificial Intelligence]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isj-theorising-the-impacts-of-generative-artificial-intelligence</link>
            <guid>isj-theorising-the-impacts-of-generative-artificial-intelligence</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 07:52:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Robert Davison</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</p>
        
        <p><strong>Antonio Díaz Andrade</strong>, University of Agder</p>
        
        <p><strong>Manuel Trenz</strong>, University of Gottingen</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Since 2022, we have witnessed an inexorable flood of information about Generative Artificial Intelligence (GAI) and its various components and manifestations. As hypes go, this one seems overdue for a cyclical correction; however, the enthusiasm for GAI across a wide range of contexts still rises. The euphoria permeates not just mainstream society and popular culture, but also business, politics, warfare and, of course, academia. The tone of inevitability about GAI and its benefits is fervent and the passion of many (notably academics, tech pundits and businesspeople) is abundant. This is not to say that there are no critical voices: there are, but their concerns risk being submerged by the tide of optimism and it may seem heretical to critique, let alone excoriate, the GAI phenomenon.</p>
    
    <p>For example, at some institutions, even measured critiques of GAI are viewed as misaligned with their forward-looking visions, creating an environment where scholars may feel pressured to conform to a predominantly positive narrative. Almost as soon as GAI was released and became a topic of discussion, we quickly saw a spate of opinions, accompanied by the wisdom of pundits and some speculative analyses of what the impact on a variety of societal and organizational functions might be. These early discussions lacked grounding in robust empirical or theoretical insights, instead reflecting speculative or overly generalized narratives. In many ways, these initial reactions paralleled the reactions to Artificial Intelligence almost forty years earlier (Sheil, 1987).</p>
    
    <p>Some academic publishers quickly outlawed the use of GAI by submitting authors and other notes of caution were expressed regarding the potential negative impacts. However, as the technology evolved, so in parallel did the restrictions on academic use, most of which were just as quickly retracted and replaced with more nuanced advisories. Academic institutions, journal publishers, and universities started to promulgate guidelines, essentially legitimizing GAI application, yet also unleashing peer and institutional pressure to take advantage of this new opportunity.</p>
    
    <p>In parallel to these academic perspectives, business organizations have expressed both enthusiasm for the technology and concerns about such issues as data protection, truth, trust, and errors, as well as how to train people to use GAI correctly. Today we see that AI-themed programmes and research centres are being created in profusion. This proliferation is worrisome not because of the exploration of GAI itself, but because it often lacks critical engagement with the potential harms and adverse consequences.</p>
    
    <p>At the ISJ, we have already seen both submissions and reviews where GAI appears to have played a role not so far from either co-author or some form of assistant. In response, we have published cautionary editorials (Davison et al., 2023, 2024). When it comes to AI-themed research submissions, our sense is that we are at the stage of the trickle before the deluge. Given the normative process of empirical (qualitative or quantitative) research, it is not surprising that few such AI-themed articles (e.g., Susarla et al., 2023; Grover, 2024) have been published. However, in a pre-GAI special issue (Mikalef et al., 2022), a more critical tone was adopted with an explicit focus on the dark side of AI.</p>
    
    <p>At the ISJ, the vast majority of GAI-themed submissions to date tend to emphasise the novelty of application area yet actually have little to do with IS and fail to engage with its broader sociotechnical axis. This reflects an ongoing challenge for IS scholars: how to meaningfully situate GAI research within the discipline’s core concerns. Nevertheless, this also presents an opportunity for IS researchers to engage critically with GAI through theoretical and methodological innovation and empirical rigor. What we also find to be absent from much of the GAI-related work done so far is either a more critical stance or attempts to engage in rigorous and novel theoretical development on the impacts of GAI.</p>
    
    <p>This is troubling because of the risks that GAI poses to individuals, organizations, society more broadly, and the natural environment. In fact, poorly vetted applications of GAI run the risk of such negative outcomes as violating privacy, facilitating research misconduct, insulting customers, and discriminating unfairly against specific groups. Given this backdrop, we argue that the time is now ripe for researchers to critically investigate the diverse impacts of GAI. Analyzing these impacts through a sociotechnical lens is essential to bridge the gap between technological advancements and their broader implications.</p>
    
    <p>We can expect that a wide variety of impacts may be experienced globally, some of which will be legal in one jurisdiction even as they are illegal elsewhere; this heightens concerns about widening digital and AI-related divides. To explain these phenomena and anticipate their future trajectories, researchers must employ appropriate theoretical frameworks and remain open to innovative forms of theorizing. GAI&#39;s emergence necessitates both the adaptation of existing theories and the development of new theoretical arguments that reflect its distinctive characteristics, such as its effects on human agency and the contextual nuances of its applications.</p>
    
    <p>We encourage the application of grounded research, given that GAI is still an emerging phenomenon. For example, theories of disruption, given the undeniably disruptive nature of GAI, may offer more fruitful opportunities for theoretical innovation, while critical design approaches rooted in theories of emancipation could illuminate issues of AI oppression. A robust theoretical foundation that explores the ‘dark side’ of GAI is indispensable for advancing sociotechnical research and addressing its complex, often adverse, societal impacts.</p>
    
    <p>In a positive sense, the research that we aim to publish in this special issue should contribute to our understanding of the potential negative impacts of GAI, with the hope that we can also mitigate them. In-depth ethnographic fieldwork, critical case studies, and grounded theory can help reveal and address the otherwise hidden aspects of GAI in practice. Action Researchers may go a step further to propose and even enact those mitigation strategies in particular contexts, thus subjecting their theoretical ideas to empirical tests.</p>
    
    <p>For this special issue, we specifically solicit research that draws on primary data. Primary data allows for a deeper understanding of GAI’s real-world impact and enables researchers to engage directly with stakeholders, such as individuals and organizations affected by GAI. We aim to foster research that is grounded in real-world experiences and produces theoretically innovative, methodologically rigorous work that can truly advance our understanding of GAI&#39;s sociotechnical consequences. We expect that authors will make a direct contribution to knowledge by developing a new theory or theorisations that acknowledge the unique characteristics of GAI. We welcome interdisciplinary work. We also welcome action research and design science studies if they empirically demonstrate how the negative impacts of GAI can be mitigated, and in addition develop theory.</p>
    
    <p>For this special issue, we do not accept the submission of stand-alone reviews of the technology, opinion papers and purely conceptual papers. Submissions to this special issue must align closely with the sociotechnical axis central to IS research. Specifically, we seek studies that explore the interplay between human, technological, environmental and organizational dimensions of GAI in real-world contexts. The range of topics and contexts that may be suitable is clearly extensive, and thus we only provide a partial list below. As we indicate above, we are particularly interested in the dark side of GAI.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Human - GAI Relationships and Collaboration (e.g., Anthropomorphism in AI and human identity; Dehumanized interactions; Relationships with robots or chatbots; Power dynamics in human - AI collaboration and hegemonic interactions)</li>
        
        <li>Human Agency, Creativity, and Cognition (e.g., Erosion of human agency and GAI dependency; Challenges to human creativity in the era of AI - driven pattern generation; Mediocrity as a new norm, and the struggle for excellence; Cognitive enhancement, deterioration, and dependence in GAI - mediated environments)</li>
        
        <li>Social Inequalities and Marginalization (e.g., Impacts on marginalized populations and inequality by design; Educational equity and impact on learning; Global and cultural distortions and digital exclusion; Data colonialism and global inequalities)</li>
        
        <li>Work and Organizational Shifts (e.g., Transformation, decline and disappearance of professions; Deskilling and disempowering of individuals; Disruptions to work, routines, and shifts in organizational dynamics)</li>
        
        <li>Governance and Policy (e.g., Implications of strong or absent governance frameworks; Regulation and policy development by governments and organizations; National policies and their differences; Environmental and societal trade-offs)</li>
        
        <li>Disinformation and Trust (Development &amp; dissemination of disinformation, misinformation, and conspiracy theories; Erosion of trust in human and organizational communication)</li>
        
        <li>Fundamental Risks (e.g., Systemic risk, resilience, and dependencies in AI - enhanced infrastructure; Vulnerabilities and data poisoning; Misuse of intellectual property; Warfare automation)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>June 30, 2025: Deadline for extended abstract submissions for early feedback</li>
        
        <li>December 31, 2025: Full paper submission deadline</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Angsana Techatassanasoontorn</strong>, AUT University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carla Bonina</strong>, University of Surrey</li>
        
        <li><strong>Christoph Breidbach</strong>, University of Queensland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dimitra Petrakaki</strong>, University of Sussex</li>
        
        <li><strong>Efpraxia Zamani</strong>, Durham University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gilbert Fridgen</strong>, University of Luxembourg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hameed Chughtai</strong>, University of Lancaster</li>
        
        <li><strong>Han-fen Hu</strong>, University of Nevada Las Vegas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Harminder Singh</strong>, AUT University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Johan Sæbo</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Luiz Joia</strong>, Getulio Vargas Foundation</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Martin Adam</strong>, University of Göttingen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maximilian Schreieck</strong>, University of Innsbruck</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mike Lee</strong>, University of Nevada Las Vegas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mira Slavova</strong>, Warwick Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Mylene Struijk</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nancy Deng</strong>, California State University Dominguez Hills</li>
        
        <li><strong>Petros Chamakiotis</strong>, ESCP</li>
        
        <li><strong>Petter Nielsen</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Phil Zhou</strong>, Tongji University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pierre-Emmanuel Arduin</strong>, Paris Dauphine University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sven Laumer</strong>, Friedrich-Alexander University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tommy Chan</strong>, University of Manchester</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Journal (ISJ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Contemporary Innovation in Information Infrastructures]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-contemporary-innovation-in-information-infrastructures</link>
            <guid>jais-contemporary-innovation-in-information-infrastructures</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 12:55:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Margunn Aanestad</strong>, University of Oslo</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ahmed Abbasi</strong>, University of Notre Dame</p>
        
        <p><strong>Dubravka Cecez-Kecmanovic</strong>, UNSW Sydney</p>
        
        <p><strong>Robert Gregory</strong>, University of Miami</p>
        
        <p><strong>Kalle Lyytinen</strong>, Case Western Reserve University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Annalisa Pelizza</strong>, University of Bologna</p>
        
        <p><strong>Joan Rodon</strong>, Esade Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Robin Williams</strong>, University of Edinburgh</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This call for a special issue in Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS) focuses on contemporary innovation in information infrastructures – especially the emergence of new technological capabilities such as block-chain, big data and Artificial Intelligence (AI), and Internet of Things (IoT) technologies- and consequent emerging new (inter) organizational forms and processes encompassing contemporary infrastructuring.</p>
    
    <p>The special issue builds on and expands the earlier stream of studies on information infrastructures (Monteiro et al. 2014) to garner a deeper understanding of the new, emerging forms of digitally enabled infrastructural formations and their design, growth patterns, and local, organizational, societal and institutional uses and impacts (Yeow et al, forthcoming). In particular, we encourage multi-level analyses, studies of infrastructures in heterogeneous contexts (developing economies; new industry contexts such as new financial services around cryptocurrencies), and so on. The studies are expected to give due consideration to both organizational and societal level relevance and significance, including double-edged effects that have often been missed in the past analyses of infrastructural formations.</p>
    
    <p>These effects include but are not limited to changes in social justice, climate change, immigration, human or personal rights. Personalised technology infrastructures such as social media and smart phones have for example created novel societal problems that range from the accelerating mental health crisis among children and adolescents, growing anomie among social groups, threats to privacy and security, to the breakdown of consensual politics. At the same time, infrastructural solutions are being proposed to resolve many critical challenges of contemporary society including the rising cost of public services, responses to climate change, or creating engines of economic growth by providing personalized health care, optimized agriculture, or new ‘clean’ manufacturing systems.</p>
    
    <p>More broadly, societal level information infrastructures play an increasingly central role across many spheres of social organizing and engineering including governance, health care, education and most public services, energy, commerce, culture and entertainment, and even cold and hot warfare between nations.</p>
    
    <p>Whilst engaging with these empirical developments, research on contemporary topics such as AI, block-chain and IoT solutions increasingly adopt an infrastructural perspective. There is currently a worldwide shift of attention towards recent rapid technical developments and early adoption and use of AI solutions, which has stimulated diverse empirical studies of specific, local AI applications.</p>
    
    <p>At the same time these studies struggle to analyze the broader context that makes such systems technologically and organizationally feasible and pushes organizations, industries and societies towards new AI based solutions. To address these questions requires the application of an infrastructural perspective which opens up under-theorised aspects of AI enabling such applications, such as digital data governance and digital storage and processing power, which all have become infrastructural.</p>
    
    <p>Such analyses must go beyond portrayals of AI as discrete “things” with ‘effects’: a self-contained algorithm, or a singular application. Rather, from an infrastructural perspective AI should be treated as a comprehensive and evolving assemblage of heterogeneous technological and social elements (models, parameterization, optimization, training data) and their ever-expanding relationships. On top of this, AI is shaping and is shaped by communities of practices, one of the main tenets of infrastructural studies (Star and Ruhleder 1996; Hanseth et al. 1996)).</p>
    
    <p>We invite original papers that engage with, scrutinize and highlight contemporary developments in a world composed of increasingly pervasive and rapidly changing information infrastructures and their component systems integrated into daily routines and widely shared services provided across time and space.</p>
    
    <p>We appreciate generally any analytic work that mobilises and resonates with the broad aims and approach outlined above in novel, interesting ways, and explores empirically and/or theoretically the landscape and manifestations of ongoing digitalization and expansion of infrastructures within the contemporary society. The expected contributions are not confined to any particular &#39;school&#39; or position of infrastructure studies and can take any feasible theoretical and methodological stance towards the subject matter.</p>
    
    <p>Our scope is highly inclusive: we wish to recruit all scholarly work showing an interest in building upon, extending, or modifying current streams of work focused on information infrastructures.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Infrastructuring of Platforms, Platformisation of Infrastructures</li>
        
        <li>Governance of/by Information Infrastructures</li>
        
        <li>Societal Challenges addressed through Information Infrastructures</li>
        
        <li>Approaches to Data &amp; AI Informed by Information Infrastructure Perspectives</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical Frames and Methodologies Salient to Infrastructure Studies</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>July 31, 2025: Initial submissions</li>
        
        <li>November 30, 2025: 1st Round Decision on Submission</li>
        
        <li>May 30, 2026: Revised submission</li>
        
        <li>September 30, 2026: 2nd Round Decision</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2027: Revised Submission</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2027: Final decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Roberta Bernardi</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Claudio Coletta</strong>, University of Bologna</li>
        
        <li><strong>Morgan Currie</strong>, University of Edinburgh</li>
        
        <li><strong>Miria Grisot</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ole Hanseth</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ole Hendfridsson</strong>, University of Miami</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ola Michalec</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Eric Monteiro</strong>, Norwegian University of Science and Technology NTNU</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marko Niemimaa</strong>, University of Agder</li>
        
        <li><strong>David Ribes</strong>, University of Washington</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alain Sandoz</strong>, Université de Neuchâtel</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pankaj Setia</strong>, Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad</li>
        
        <li><strong>Franz Strich</strong>, Deakin University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maha Shaikh</strong>, Esade Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Antti Silvasti</strong>, LUT University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carsten Sorensen</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Léa Stiefel</strong>, University of Lausanne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Stefan Tams</strong>, HEC Montréal</li>
        
        <li><strong>David Tilson</strong>, Rochester Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jonathan Wareham</strong>, Esade Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Will Venters</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Adrian Yeow Yong Kwang</strong>, Singapore University of Social Sciences</li>
        
        <li><strong>Aljona Zorina</strong>, IESEG School of Management</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Future of Information Systems in the Enterprise]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-the-future-of-information-systems-in-the-enterprise</link>
            <guid>jit-the-future-of-information-systems-in-the-enterprise</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 03:00:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Robert Winter</strong>, University of St. Gallen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Karlheinz Kautz</strong>, RMIT University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Sabherval</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Leona Chandra Kruse</strong>, University of Agder</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The use of information systems in the enterprise is the backbone of digital transformation and digital business, acting as the binding force between technological, managerial, and organizational innovations. The design and use of information systems in the enterprise evolve alongside technological advancements, shifting managerial strategies, and changing organisational forms and needs (Kotusev, 2019).</p>
    
    <p>&quot;Enterprise information systems&quot; has been the key term for information systems that transcend narrow functions, processes, products, markets, or concerns (e.g., ERP, SCM, CRM) and integrate these elements, supporting end-to- end, creating synergy, and ensuring coherence in the enterprise context (Cao et al., 2022; Robey et al., 2002).</p>
    
    <p>Given the rapid pace of change and advancements in emerging technologies (e.g., artificial intelligence, edge computing), alternative approaches to information systems used in enterprises (e.g., shadow IT, cloud/as-a-service), and structures beyond single enterprises (e.g., platforms, ecosystems), this special issue is focused on the future of information systems in the enterprise context and deliberately uses this broader term to emphasise our interest in both conventional enterprise information systems and alternative IS/IT solutions used for similar enterprise-level issues.</p>
    
    <p>Information systems in the enterprise have undergone fundamental paradigm shifts in the past four decades. First, the integration scope of such systems has expanded to include customer activities, supply chains, and business ecosystems (Ignatiadis &amp; Nandhakumar, 2007; Sambhara et al., 2022). Second, technological innovations have fundamentally changed the characteristics and positioning of information systems in the enterprise. These innovations include, among others, transitioning from on-premises to cloud-based operations, shifting from traditional license to as-a-service models, incorporating analytic and execution functionalities, integrating with or evolving into digital platforms, adopting edge computing, and adding artificial intelligence functionalities (Dong et al., 2009; Flak et al., 2022). These developments set the stage for future challenges, such as how enterprises will further enhance agility and innovation through emerging technologies.</p>
    
    <p>Third, managerial innovations require greater flexibility from information systems in the enterprise. These include, among others, the rise of digital platforms and business ecosystems, end-to-end process integration, agile business organization, and continuous development and integration (Aral et al., 2024). Fourth, new types of enterprise systems and other information systems in the enterprise enhance value creation for old and new stakeholders, justifying significant investment while necessitating more sophisticated approaches for their design, development, governance, and operations (see further, Nah et al., 2001; Scott &amp; Vessey, 2002; Dong et al., 2009; Pang et al., 2014; Haki et al., 2020; Mikalef et al., 2020; Flak et al., 2022).</p>
    
    <p>The future of information systems in the enterprise is complex. IS practice must adapt to technological, managerial, and organizational innovations while IS research may need to integrate insights from work on enterprise systems, enterprise architecture, as well as IS governance, digital transformation, IS sourcing, and digital platforms. This special issue aims to address these challenges by inviting disciplinary and interdisciplinary submissions that provide important insights on the direction and future of information systems in the enterprise. Specifically, &quot;The Future of Information Systems in the Enterprise&quot; special issue seeks to generate new knowledge that addresses key practical or theoretical challenges.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Alternatives to traditional enterprise information systems such as digital platforms, shadow IT, no-code/low-code, and how the challenges they bring for coherent management, and our understanding of enterprise-level systems</li>
        
        <li>Designing future information systems in the enterprise with concerns for both business and societal values</li>
        
        <li>Exploring how technological or organizational innovations in the enterprise / enterprise-level context challenge and extend existing knowledge and theory</li>
        
        <li>Extending and adapting the body of knowledge to encompass specific contexts, such as strategies, industries, ecosystems, or specific organizational configurations</li>
        
        <li>Horizontal (cross-unit) and vertical (technology-to-business) integration through information systems in the enterprise</li>
        
        <li>Specific integration challenges of technology, organization, and humans in the enterprise / enterprise-level context</li>
        
        <li>Intersection of artificial intelligence and other emerging technologies in information systems in the enterprise</li>
        
        <li>Intersection/relation of enterprise and platform/ecosystem-level systems and technologies, and the corresponding challenges such as for organizational strategy</li>
        
        <li>Understanding and harnessing the complexity of enterprise computing</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 1, 2024: Extended abstract submissions via email to the corresponding special issue editor for early feedback and invitation to the special issue paper development workshop.</li>
        
        <li>November 15, 2024: Results are announced.</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2024: Special issue paper development workshop at ICIS 2024.</li>
        
        <li>April 1, 2025: First-round submissions.</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2025: First-round decisions.</li>
        
        <li>December 1, 2025: Second-round submissions.</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2026: Second-round decisions (Papers are either acceptable with minor changes or rejected).</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2026: Final versions (Final decisions and online publication soon afterwards).</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Pär Ågerfalk</strong>, Uppsala University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rainer Alt</strong>, University of Leipzig</li>
        
        <li><strong>Vanessa Cooper</strong>, RMIT University Melbourne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rob Gleasure</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Kazem Haki</strong>, HES Geneva</li>
        
        <li><strong>Taha Havakhor</strong>, McGill University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hartmut Hoehle</strong>, University of Mannheim</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sherah Kurnia</strong>, University of Melbourne</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, UNSW</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jan Mendling</strong>, Humboldt-Universität</li>
        
        <li><strong>Annette Mills</strong>, University of Canterbury</li>
        
        <li><strong>Petter Nielsen</strong>, University of Oslo</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ralf Plattfaut</strong>, University Duisburg-Essen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Matti Rossi</strong>, Aalto University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Helana Scheepers</strong>, Swinburne University of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Priya Seetharaman</strong>, Indian Institute of Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Pankaj Setia</strong>, Indian Institute of Management</li>
        
        <li><strong>Matthias Söllner</strong>, University of Kassel</li>
        
        <li><strong>Zach Steelman</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tuure Tuunanen</strong>, University of Jyväskylä</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Addressing Refugees and Migration Issues through Critical Information Systems Research]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isj-addressing-refugees-and-migration-issues-through-critical-information-systems</link>
            <guid>isj-addressing-refugees-and-migration-issues-through-critical-information-systems</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 10:34:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Safa’a AbuJarour</strong>, An-Najah National University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Hameed Chughtai</strong>, Lancaster University Management School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yingqin Zheng</strong>, University of Essex</p>
        
    
    
    <p>United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) reports that there are approximately 110 million forcibly displaced people worldwide, as of mid-2023, because of persecution, conflict, war, violence, human rights violations, or events seriously disturbing public order. These include 36.4 million refugees and 62.5 million internally displaced people (IDP), asylum seekers, and several other people in need of international protection. There is a strong history of research highlighting the issues faced by refugees, ranging from accounts of violence in the developing world, exploring the gendered experience of refugees, questioning racist thinking about immigration, case studies of asylum seekers, and philosophical inquiry into the fair treatment of refugees. The global refugee and forced migration crisis and the persistent challenges faced by these vulnerable communities call for an urgent need for innovative solutions that foster social inclusion and empower these populations.</p>
    
    <p>In our field, information systems (IS) researchers have been acutely aware of the refugee and migrant crises. Researchers have examined the critical issues related to social inclusion of refugees, social inclusion and activation of refugee agency, information and communication technology (ICT) enabled refugee integration, refugees and pedagogy, digitization and refugee settlement, refugee women and information-precarity, and migrant identity. Nonetheless, recent research in refugee studies has shown that critical areas at the intersection of technology, refugees, and broader migration crises have remained underexamined, for example, social media and device vetting, digitally mediated lived experiences of minority refugees, refugees and a sense of uncertainty in the digital age, refugee aid and digital capitalism, and networked refugees.</p>
    
    <p>We observe that despite some progress in our field, much remains underexplored in addressing these pressing issues, underscoring the need for rigorous research. This special issue aims to explore how IS research could contribute to illuminating the refugee crises and alleviating the deterioration of refugee and migrant social circumstances. These sensitive topics are situated within the broader debate on digital inclusion and empowerment and the discussions related to inequality and demarginalization and decolonization in our field.</p>
    
    <p>Exploring the critical research questions surrounding IS and migrant/refugee populations is essential for developing comprehensive and ‘good’ IS solutions and making the world a better place for all of us. We encourage submissions from diverse researchers with multidisciplinary perspectives, including experts in IS, social sciences, public policy, humanitarian studies, and other relevant fields. Such interdisciplinary collaborations will contribute to a holistic understanding of the problems and foster innovative solutions. We seek submissions that focus on real-world issues at the intersection of refugees and migrant crises and technology.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Critical analyses of the interrelated themes of identity, refugeeness, and belonging.</li>
        
        <li>Exploring the ethics of (forced) migration.</li>
        
        <li>Analysing the politics of responsibility and the integration of refugees and migrants in digital contexts.</li>
        
        <li>Technology, racial marginalization and refugees experience.</li>
        
        <li>Digital biopolitics, identities, and datafication of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Online activism and digital social movements in the context of refugees or migrants.</li>
        
        <li>Agency, resistance and coping mechanisms of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Examining the issues at the intersections of gender, technology, and migrants/refugees (including queering migration and issues of gender-based violence).</li>
        
        <li>Digitally-entangled lived experiences of minorities among refugee populations.</li>
        
        <li>Datafication of borders and algorithmic management of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Decolonial justice and /for migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Digital justice and human rights issues affecting migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Digital and data surveillance and control on migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Issues related to power and exploitation of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Critical narratives of displacement.</li>
        
        <li>Digital accounts and narratives of refugee experience.</li>
        
        <li>Technology and the political philosophy of migration and refuge.</li>
        
        <li>Novel theoretical lenses to study migration and refugee issues such as decolonial theory, spatial and temporal perspectives, Indigenous viewpoints, critical race theory, and feminist approaches.</li>
        
        <li>Novel methodological approaches to examine refugee issues such as visual ethnography, visual research, and digitally mediated bodily experiences.</li>
        
        <li>Application of novel technologies such as Blockchain and AI.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 30, 2024: Submission of extended abstract (optional)</li>
        
        <li>March 30, 2025: Submission of manuscript</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Petros Chamakiotis</strong>, ESCP Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Andrea Jimenez</strong>, University of Sheffield</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shirin Madon</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, University of New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Priyanka Panday</strong>, Kings College London</li>
        
        <li><strong>Israr Qureshi</strong>, Australian National University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maximilian Schreieck</strong>, University of Innsbruck</li>
        
        <li><strong>Devinder Thapa</strong>, University of Agder</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ranjan Vaidya</strong>, Auckland University of Technology</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Journal (ISJ)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Emerging Technologies and IS Sourcing]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-emerging-technologies-and-is-sourcing</link>
            <guid>jit-emerging-technologies-and-is-sourcing</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:31:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ilan Oshri</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Oliver Krancher</strong>, IT University of Copenhagen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Sabherwal</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The last decade has seen a significant proliferation of new technologies. These include robotic process automation, big data, machine/deep learning and artificial intelligence, blockchain, and other &quot;emerging technologies&quot;. Consulting and market research companies have consistently predicted that the current wave of technologies will transform both front and back office operations, requiring firms to rethink their business models and strategies.</p>
    
    <p>While evidence suggests that firms will continue to invest in emerging technologies, there has so far been little evidence about the involvement of service providers and advisory in the selection, design, and adoption of such emerging technologies. IS sourcing research has conventionally accounted for three main areas of interest: sourcing decision, contractual structures, and relationship management. Emerging technologies challenge these traditional conventions in the IS sourcing literature. Particular challenges include but are not limited to: greater dependency on data in emerging technologies, which triggers clients to source data science services; the actual implementation of emerging technology often happens through platforms that involve multiple players and services; the asset transfer model has become less relevant and yet client firms are still expected to reduce their headcount; there is greater emphasis on the redesign of the value chain as services have become digitized and decisions are now driven by smart algorithms; emerging technologies are viewed as a black box, posing a skills and expertise challenge to client firms to ensure acquiring and retaining knowledge of the technology.</p>
    
    <p>Further, the IS sourcing literature which has traditionally relied on three main reference theories, namely, transaction cost economics, resource dependency, and social exchange. Emerging technologies emphasize the need to expand this theoretical base and accommodate new paradigms of capturing and analyzing data in IS sourcing research. Taking into account the above observations, the IS sourcing literature thus begs for the re-examination of client-supplier-advisory relationships by challenging core concepts of sourcing decision, contractual structure, and relationship management as offering new theoretical landscapes that accommodate the sourcing phenomenon in a digital age.</p>
    
    <p>This special issue seeks to facilitate an empirical and theoretical re-examination of &quot;IS sourcing&quot; in the light of the current wave of emerging technologies. We invite research papers that investigate issues relating to emerging technologies and IS sourcing, particularly focusing on robotic process automation, big data, machine/deep learning and artificial intelligence, and blockchain. Other technologies are less of interest for this special issue.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Governance and control structures between client-supplier-advisory in emerging technology settings</li>
        
        <li>Sourcing decision making in emerging technology settings</li>
        
        <li>Ecosystem and platforms in emerging technology sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Contract management in emerging technology sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Full data lifecycle in emerging technologies and its implications for sourcing management</li>
        
        <li>Skills and capability development and retention in emerging technology sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Implications for innovations within the client-supplier-advisory eco-system</li>
        
        <li>Ethical and societal implications deriving from such sourcing settings</li>
        
        <li>Impact of emerging technologies on client’s, supplier’s and advisory’s strategies, business models and capabilities</li>
        
        <li>Implications of crowdsourcing, big data, analytics as well as machine/deep learning and artificial intelligence for the contemporary IS outsourcing</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>April 15, 2021: First round submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>July 25, 2021: First round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>October 25, 2021: Second round submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>January 28, 2022: Second round decision to authors</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2022: Third and final round submissions deadline</li>
        
        <li>June 15, 2022: Final decision to authors</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Products of Theorizing: Towards Native Theories of Emerging IT]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-products-of-theorizing-towards-native-theories-of-emerging-it</link>
            <guid>jit-products-of-theorizing-towards-native-theories-of-emerging-it</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:29:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Nik Hassan</strong>, University of Minnesota Duluth</p>
        
        <p><strong>Suzanne Rivard</strong>, HEC Montreal</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ulrike Schultze</strong>, Southern Methodist University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Leslie Willcocks</strong>, London School of Economics and Political Science</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Theorizing is one of the defining aspects of academic research. Articulating insights generated from situated empirical observations into relatively stable abstractions (e.g., concepts, propositions, models) that elucidate, explain or predict events occurring at another time and place is the hallmark of knowledge generation (King 2021). Of late, much attention has been paid to theory development in the Information Systems (IS) field. For example, the MIS Quarterly (MISQ) special issue on &#39;Next-Generation Information Systems Theorizing&#39; reflects a sense of urgency felt within the IS field to make sense of an increasingly unruly and complex reality given the increasing pace of technological innovation (Burton-Jones et al. 2021). In similar vein, two 2021 Journal of Information Technology (JIT) debates sections focused on &#39;IS Research and Science&#39; (Siponen and Klaavuniemi 2020, and commentaries) and &#39;Theorising as Craft&#39; (Rivard 2021, and commentaries) and a recent Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS) special issue focused on &#39;Envisioning Digital Transformation – Advancing Theoretical Diversity&#39;. New and native IS theories ensure that the IS field remains vibrant, diverse, academically and socially relevant and influential (Hassan 2011; Hassan and Willcocks 2021; Lowry et al. 2020; Markus and Saunders 2007). Researchers, however, often set the bar too high for theory delivered within individual research contributions by viewing theory as a comprehensive and detailed explanation of a phenomenon (Rivard 2021), an object that Weick (1995) refers to as a &#39;theory that sweeps away all others&#39; (p. 386). This mindset may lead IS researchers to adopt theories from other fields as a foundation rather than creatively developing new and native theories from empirical observations (Grover and Lyytinen 2015).</p>
    
    <p>To maintain the long-term growth and vitality of the IS field, a definition of theory that encourages cumulative and novel theorizing over time is needed (Hassan and Willcocks 2021; King 2021). One way of achieving this is by advancing a &#39;products of theorizing&#39; perspective (Weick 1995). The theorizing perspective celebrates both the final outcomes and the &#39;interim struggles&#39; that characterize theory generation (Weick 1995). It holds the promise that interim conceptual artifacts of theorizing such as metaphors, frameworks and concepts (Lowry et al. 2020) are valuable to the discipline as they can be leveraged and exploited further in subsequent research. In this way, a discipline might inch its way towards native theories over time. The goal of this special issue is to solicit and showcase exemplars from the &#39;products of theorizing&#39; approach. We are looking for articles that go beyond verification dimensions of the natural-science approach to IS research (Schlagwein 2021) and push the envelope of theorizing towards native products of theorizing (Hassan et al. forthcoming): theory frame devices (i.e., questions, paradigms, laws and frameworks), theory generators (i.e., myths, analogies, metaphors and models) and theory components (i.e., concepts, constructs, statements and hypotheses).</p>
    
    <p>The time is ripe to embark upon the development of native theories in the IS field, as IT has leaped into the consciousness of the public in unprecedented ways. Big data and AI applications are part of consumers’ and workers’ everyday lives, either enhancing them or increasing their visibility (Aral 2020; Benbya et al. 2021; Zuboff 2019); firms increasingly deploy robotic process automation and cognitive automation, aiming to achieve benefits for themselves, their employees and their customers (Lacity and Willcocks 2021); and governments rely on new forms of data collection about citizens (e.g., blood samples, vaccination data, fingerprints, iris-recognition systems) in support of the services they provide (Kolas et al. 2021). To take advantage of the theorizing opportunities that these emergent information technology (IT) phenomena provide, the goal of this special issue is to encourage research that generates products of theorizing derived from and related to IT phenomena. We are seeking contributions that develop products of theorizing, that is, interim constructions, that are useful as precursors to strong native IS theory. To increase the likelihood of a theorizing product’s value, we are particularly interested in research that tackles phenomena that are core to the IS discipline. Given the multifaceted nature of the IS discipline, we do not expect agreement on what constitutes a core IS phenomenon. We therefore encourage authors to make the case that the products of theorizing they develop are valuable for articulating native theories that are defining of the field of IS or are substantially valuable for their specific area.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Use of theory generators (e.g., analogies, myths, models and metaphors) for understanding and guiding research of emergent phenomena such as surveillance capitalism, fake news, social media, or the performativity of big data and AI.</li>
        
        <li>Constructing or formulating novel frameworks derived from or relevant to emerging technologies.</li>
        
        <li>Adopting a genealogical lens to uncover the products of theorizing that have been instrumental in the theories that have become popular in the IS discipline (e.g., socio-technical, sociomateriality, imbrication).</li>
        
        <li>Reviewing and analysing the foundations of core concepts of the IS field such as that of &#39;information,&#39; &#39;system&#39; and &#39;technology&#39;.</li>
        
        <li>Re-theorizing areas or subfields within IS (e.g., design science, data analytics, big data, AI) where native products of theorizing are sparse.</li>
        
        <li>Problematizing the IS field (i.e., going beyond gap-spotting and borrowing theory from reference disciplines) to identify questions and challenges that the field of IS is uniquely qualified to address.</li>
        
        <li>Inventing native original concepts in the IS field that will serve as foundations for the scientific IS research method and declare to the world, the field’s core concerns.</li>
        
        <li>Exploring the role of scientific laws in IS research as a product of theorizing with relevance to emerging phenomena.</li>
        
        <li>Unpacking products of theorizing (e.g., questions, models and frameworks) that uncover deep-seated assumptions about contemporary IS phenomena (e.g., symbols of value, solidarity, social structure, conflict and contradictions within a technology-driven society) that are especially relevant to emerging technologies.</li>
        
        <li>Distinguishing between non-observable constructs from more observable concepts that are rarely discussed in IS research but form the mainstay of scientific studies.</li>
        
        <li>Aggregating the statements, claims and propositions that have been made by a stream of IS literature and that are deemed most impactful on and relevant for contemporary users, organizations and society, to set the stage for the further progress towards native IS theory.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>October 24, 2021: Extended abstracts (for workshop and feedback) due</li>
        
        <li>December 12, 2021: Workshop at ICIS 2021 SIG PHIL</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2022: First-round submissions version due</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2022: First-round reviews returned</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2022: Second-round submissions due</li>
        
        <li>August 30, 2022: Second-round reviews returned</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2022: Final versions due</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2022: Final decisions and publication online</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Next-Generation Information Systems Research Methods]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-next-generation-information-systems-research-methods</link>
            <guid>jit-next-generation-information-systems-research-methods</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:27:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Ivo Blohm</strong>, University of St. Gallen</p>
        
        <p><strong>Susanna Ho</strong>, Australian National University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Oklahoma</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jan Marco Leimeister</strong>, University of St. Gallen</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue is interested in &#39;next-generation&#39; research methods for studying information technology (IT) phenomena – particularly in the information system (IS) research field. So far, IS researchers have applied a range of quantitative, qualitative and engaged methods to study IT-related phenomena. Quantitative IS research has often followed a positivist approach of hypothesis testing, with sometimes &#39;first-generation&#39; regression models distinguished from &#39;second-generation&#39; structural equation models (Gerow et al. 2011). Data used in such methods stems from surveys, experiments, panel studies, etc. The primary objective of this research stream typically is theory testing. Qualitative IS research has ranged from positivist to interpretivist, seeking rich situated insights via case studies, grounded theory or ethnographies. One objective of this research stream is theory construction. Critical and emancipatory IS research adds a strong value orientation and theoretical basis to qualitative research. Another type of IS research seeks to generate new knowledge with &#39;engaged&#39; methods like design science or action research. The objective of this stream that differentiates it from the first two is the focus on solving important individual, organizational or societal challenges; or extending the boundaries of human and organizational capabilities by creating new and innovative artifacts (Baskerville and Wood-Harper 1996; Hevner et al. 2004).</p>
    
    <p>In recent years, the scope of and possibilities for IS research have tremendously widened. Digital IT have become mainstream at the individual, organizational and societal levels (Burton-Jones et al. 2021). Digital IT is key to innovation in various domains from medicine to education, from psychology to the arts. Hence, these domains have become of interest and relevance to IS researchers, yet also overlap with other fields and are hence interdisciplinary in nature. These innovations are increasing the volume and variety of trace data available to researchers but necessitate a shift in our research practices (Johnson et al. 2019). Further, big data, machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI) technologies provide a plethora of powerful approaches for collecting and analysing data at a scale not possible before such that we might need to adapt our research methods and tools to make this data actionable and to generate novel knowledge. These ML technologies are being applied not only to theory testing but also to theory construction – in conjunction with or independent of qualitative methods (Miranda et al. 2022).</p>
    
    <p>This special issue focuses on the next generation of research methods to study IT – new methods relevant to the IS research field that account for a) the interdisciplinary nature and wider scope of IT phenomena, and/or b) the novel capacities afforded by new technologies/techniques (e.g., ML/AI). The way that novel technologies and techniques afford new possibilities is quite apparent in quantitative IS research. In contrast to &#39;first-generation&#39; regression-based approaches and &#39;second-generation&#39; structural equation modelling, a new generation of research methods including the predictive analytics (Shmueli and Koppius 2011), data mining (Smith 2020), ML (Shrestha et al. 2020) or explainable AI (Gunning et al. 2019) come with substantial new opportunities and challenges. For instance, these methods potentially allow for more fine-grained measurements and analyses to extend our knowledge of existing phenomena and may help us study novel phenomena including those that were, methodologically speaking, &#39;out of reach&#39; (George et al. 2016). These technological advancements enable us to progress our research toolkit and inform new ways of generating knowledge and theorizing (Burton-Jones et al. 2021; Shrestha et al. 2020). Increased recognition of abduction as a counterpart to deductive and inductive reasoning (Behfar and Okhuysen 2018; Sætre and Van de Ven 2021) pits concerns about practices such as HARKing (Kerr 1998) – hypothesizing after the results are known (aka p-hacking) – believed to lead to logically and scientifically flawed hypotheses, against concerns about stifling the advancement of knowledge (Pratt et al. 2019). ML/AI techniques are now so powerful that they can test millions of models on large data sets to find the &#39;best-matching&#39; model (of all possible) for what needs to be explained. This is a fundamental gear change in what can be done with quantitative data sets, the promise and validity of which are hotly debated (Kitchin 2014; Smith 2020).</p>
    
    <p>In terms of changes to the nature of the IS domains, qualitative-interpretative researchers seek to find new methods suitable for the wider, interdisciplinary scope of IS research. This is done via finding or developing analytical new grounds and looking at digital IT differently (e.g. via sociomaterial or affordances perspectives), seeking additional foundations in other fields (e.g., Zuboff’s (2015) political economy informed analysis of surveillance capitalism and &#39;Big Tech&#39;) or via the modification of methods to suit digital environments (e.g., virtual ethnographies or computational grounded theory). Other forms of qualitative research such as meta-synthesis, qualitative comparative analysis and discourse analysis also seem promising and relevant but are seldomly used in IS research. Digital IT (e.g., social media, digital platforms, AI/ML) has increasing and substantial impacts on society (e.g., mental health, trust in science, misinformation and polarization, monopolization and industry disruption). Hence, ethical, critical, value-based and political-economy questions are increasingly and necessarily asked about digital IT. Similarly, today’s pace of innovation may also warrant novel approaches to engaged scholarship and design science. For instance, researchers are calling for methods that can accumulate and update evidence more effectively (Lacity et al. 2021) and better ensure the generalizability of prescriptive knowledge (Brendel et al. 2021; Iivari et al. 2021).</p>
    
    <p>This special issue invites contributions that propose, introduce, debate or critique novel quantitative, qualitative or design-oriented methods research, with a focus on the &#39;how&#39; (i.e., origins, processes, steps of the method) and the &#39;why&#39; (e.g., &#39;rigour vs relevance&#39; and &#39;it is new, but is it better&#39; questions) these approaches should be used in IS research. The goal of the special issue is to provide a space for introducing and discussing innovative &#39;next-generation&#39; methods for studying IT-related phenomena, relative to the IS research field.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Critical reflection of research methods used in IS.</li>
        
        <li>Introducing new qualitative, quantitative or design research methods.</li>
        
        <li>Transferability of non-IS research methods such as from other fields or praxis.</li>
        
        <li>Novel combinations of research methods such as cross-disciplinary or mixed-method approaches.</li>
        
        <li>Innovative approaches to analyze big data.</li>
        
        <li>Approaches dealing with special types of unstructured data.</li>
        
        <li>Problems of null hypothesis testing via big data and AI/ML.</li>
        
        <li>AI, ML and explainable AI for knowledge creation and theory generation.</li>
        
        <li>Transparent, robust and replicable research designs and methodologies.</li>
        
        <li>Transferability and generalizability of insights generated with specific methods.</li>
        
        <li>Approaches to evaluating and communicating practical relevance of findings.</li>
        
        <li>Critical assessment of novel approaches on practical, conceptual, ethical or philosophical grounds.</li>
        
        <li>Philosophy of science-based proposals for or critiques of methods.</li>
        
        <li>Culture and values-driven proposals for or critiques of methods.</li>
        
        <li>Methods to study the past, the present and/or the future.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 20, 2022: Abstract submissions: (optional; authors are invited to submit extended abstracts of papers for early reactions)</li>
        
        <li>April 15, 2023: First-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>July 15, 2023: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>December 15, 2023: Second-round submissions</li>
        
        <li>February 15, 2024: Second-round decisions: (papers are either acceptable with minor changes or rejected at this stage)</li>
        
        <li>May 15, 2024: Final versions due: (final decisions and online publication soon afterwards)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Decentralised Information Systems: New Thinking and New Paradigms]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jit-decentralised-information-systems-new-thinking-and-new-paradigms</link>
            <guid>jit-decentralised-information-systems-new-thinking-and-new-paradigms</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 12:26:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Ali Sunyaev</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</p>
        
        <p><strong>Mary Lacity</strong>, University of Arkansas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Michel Avital</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</p>
        
    
    
    <p>This special issue seeks to explore and extend the conceptualisation, design, development, implementation and governance of contemporary “decentralised” information systems. “Decentralised” information systems are often seen as an important anti-thesis to “centralised” such systems. Modern societies and economies rely more highly on data, information systems, and technologies than ever. Pioneering organisations brought forth major milestones in developing and providing information technologies (e.g., TCP/IP and the Internet). However, with the significance of information technology increasing over the past decades, a small number of organisations have emerged as “tech giants” (e.g., Alphabet/Google or Meta/Facebook). Those organisations offer digital services and infrastructures for data processing that gained large-scale adoption by individuals, organisations, governments and society at large. As a result, societies, economies and technical systems became strongly dependent on services from a handful of organisations. The increase of the resulting dependencies leads to a centralisation of information systems. Highly-centralised information systems can result in global organisations and central social actors that abuse their power and pursue their own interests at the expense of others (e.g., by manipulation), exclude participation from social actors who disagree with them (e.g., by censorship) or invade their privacy through monitoring (e.g., by tracking actions of individuals on the internet). Highly-centralised information systems can also pose several further risks. For example, governance rights – such as rights of access, validation, software updates, data policies, and data overrides – may be centralised with few social actors in control. From a technical perspective, successful attacks on and crashes of central computing devices for network message propagation can interrupt communication in computing systems and even bring about system failures.</p>
    
    <p>To avert risks of over-centralization, the purposeful decentralisation of information systems has become a prominent topic of public discourse, for example, around Internet search, cloud computing, social media and financial systems. An information system’s degree of decentralisation refers to the degree to which the information system is independent of central actors and technical constructs. Several attempts have been made to design decentralised information systems to improve collaboration between actors while reducing dependencies on central authorities. Such endeavours include the development of decentralised token economies based on distributed ledger technology, decentralised identity management systems and distributed collaborative machine learning systems (e.g., federated learning systems). Although information systems decentralisation may resolve several of the above issues of over-centralisation, it also comes with its own challenges. For example, maintaining decentralised information systems can become difficult when multiple social actors need to update their technical components independently. Extensive data replication across technical components in decentralised information systems (e.g., in blockchain systems) can facilitate detecting and exploiting software vulnerabilities. If too many social actors have opposing ideas, decentralised governance risks never reaching an agreement. When only a few social actors participate in governance, information systems envisioned to be decentralised may de facto centralise.</p>
    
    <p>To purposefully achieve the benefits of information system decentralisation, we need to consider both the design of information systems as such and the behaviour of the social actors involved. Information systems decentralisation is driven by interdependent economic, political, social and technical factors. As an example of technical factors, the innovation of blockchain technology supports the decentralisation of asset ownership management. Changes to corporate information system designs, corporate ecosystems, and regulatory refinements are required to facilitate the development and adoption of such technical innovations. Such changes can lead to the centralisation of information systems in other aspects, such as their organisational structures. The entanglement of interdisciplinary factors tightly makes information systems decentralisation an interdisciplinary topic, relevant to several research fields, including computer science, organisational studies and information systems. The interdependence between information system designs and the influence of interdisciplinary factors makes the purposeful decentralisation of information systems an important yet complex undertaking that this special issue seeks new knowledge about.</p>
    
    <p>The complexity of information system decentralisation leads to various open questions, such as “how to achieve and sustain appropriate degrees of decentralisation of information systems so that individuals, organisations, and entire business ecosystems can benefit”, “how decentralised enterprise information systems need to be designed”, and “what technical know-how and involvement is required from actors to decentralise information systems appropriately”? This special issue seeks to improve the understanding of how the various factors affect the decentralisation of information systems used in business and other societal contexts, how different degrees of decentralisation of such information systems emerge over time, and how different degrees of decentralisation of information systems can affect business ecosystems, business processes, and societies overall. We invite applied, empirical, and theoretical research works that investigate information system decentralisation in a way that acknowledges its interdisciplinary nature and significantly contributes to understanding information system decentralisation, its manifestations, antecedents, and its impact on individuals and organisations, ecosystems and societies. We welcome and encourage submissions from researchers using diverse epistemological and methodological approaches. The manuscripts will be evaluated for the interestingness and novelty of their contributions.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Decentralised information systems for enterprises (e.g., information systems design and implementation for enterprises)</li>
        
        <li>Decentralised organisations and information systems decentralisation, including decentralised autonomous organizations (DAOs), decentralised platforms, token-driven governance and work practices</li>
        
        <li>Asset monetisation and similar information systems decentralisation, including web3, non-fungible tokens (NFTs) and digital assets</li>
        
        <li>Consumer privacy and information systems decentralisation, including self-sovereignty vs. self-responsibility</li>
        
        <li>The token economy, including tokenomics business models, effects of regulation and standardisation on decentralised token economies</li>
        
        <li>Digital resilience and information systems decentralisation, including critical information infrastructures</li>
        
        <li>Information systems decentralisation for the public good and social benefit, including decentralised voting, decentralised universal basic income (UBI) schemes and support of the decentralised supply of green energy by information systems</li>
        
        <li>Financial information systems decentralisation, including cryptocurrencies and community coins</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>January 15, 2024: Manuscript submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>April 19, 2024: First round reviews and decisions</li>
        
        <li>August 30, 2024: Second round (revision) submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>November 29, 2024: Second round reviews and decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 7, 2025: Final submission deadline for accepted manuscripts (subject to minor revisions)</li>
        
        <li>May 9, 2025: Final approval of manuscripts</li>
        
        <li>March 31, 2026: Online publication of special issue (anticipated date)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Roman Beck</strong>, IT University of Copenhagen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Erran Carmel</strong>, American University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada</li>
        
        <li><strong>Klitos Christodoulou</strong>, University of Nicosia</li>
        
        <li><strong>Raffaele Ciriello</strong>, University of Sydney</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gilbert Fridgen</strong>, University of Luxembourg</li>
        
        <li><strong>Rob Gleasure</strong>, Copenhagen Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Robert Wayne Gregory</strong>, University of Miami Herbert Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hanna Halaburda</strong>, New York University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Niclas Kannengiesser</strong>, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Johann Kranz</strong>, Ludwig-Maximilians-University Munich</li>
        
        <li><strong>George Kuk</strong>, Nottingham Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Gerhard Schwabe</strong>, University of Zurich</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carsten Sørensen</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alfred Taudes</strong>, Vienna University of Economics and Business</li>
        
        <li><strong>Jason Bennett Thatcher</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nils Urbach</strong>, Universität Bayreuth</li>
        
        <li><strong>Wenqian Wang</strong>, Perdue</li>
        
        <li><strong>Edgar Whitley</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of Information Technology (JIT)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Sustainability and Information Systems Research: New challenges and theoretical perspectives]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-digital-sustainability-and-information-systems-research</link>
            <guid>jais-digital-sustainability-and-information-systems-research</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 12:54:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jacqueline Corbett</strong>, Université Laval</p>
        
        <p><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Monash University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Thomas Kude</strong>, University of Bamberg</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yenni Tim</strong>, University of New South Wales</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Sustainability is a moral and existential imperative of our time. As Information Systems (IS) scholars, we are aware of the immense impact of digital technologies on efforts and initiatives towards sustainable practice happening locally and globally. Furthermore, because digital phenomena lie at the heart of our discipline, IS researchers are well positioned to join these efforts. This Special Issue aims to champion new digital sustainability research programs targeting the planet’s most pressing sustainability challenges from the past decade. We hope it will contribute towards building novel collective knowledge and help shape digital sustainability research in IS.</p>
    
    <p>Human society is approaching the edge of a dangerous precipice. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change’s (IPCC) Sixth Assessment Report unequivocally confirms that human activities have caused global warming, predicting that even with current commitments and mitigation efforts, it will be difficult to limit warming below the critical threshold of 2 o C. The planet’s air, land, and water continue to be threatened on several fronts, with research suggesting that the safe operating zone for six of the nine planetary boundaries has already been breached. Over the past decade, extreme weather events such as droughts, floods, fires and heatwaves have not only increased in frequency but also in magnitude. In addition to causing environmental impacts, these events have a significant impact on society, further complicating the pursuit of social and economic sustainability.</p>
    
    <p>In 2020, about 724 million people were living in conditions of extreme poverty, with almost 30% of the world’s population suffering from some level of food insecurity. Equality for women and other marginalized groups continues to lag. The World Bank reports that 2.4 billion women globally do not have the same economic rights as men, and despite the adoption of the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples in 2007, Indigenous Peoples around the world continue to suffer the intergenerational trauma of colonization. The trend towards urbanization endures, with cities struggling to ensure inclusive, resilient, and sustainable living environments for all residents. On top of all these challenges, violent conflicts have led to the forced migration of millions of people and the deaths of thousands of civilians. These alarming circumstances highlight the lack of progress towards the United Nation’s Sustainable Development Goals.</p>
    
    <p>As argued in a recent JAIS editorial on digital sustainability, the IS research community has a strong foundation to draw upon, ranging from research into Green IS to studies addressing significant societal challenges. The poor cannot eat technology, but the mindful design and use of technology can contribute to innovative solutions and positive impacts. In particular, we consider that the recent shift in the way IS research approaches digital phenomena offers new perspectives on the relationship between digital technologies and sustainability. Building on a contention that the classical view of an information system as representing and reflecting physical reality has become obsolete, there exists an opportunity for the IS community to drive a more inclusive agenda on digital sustainability, one that encompasses phenomena in which the impact of digital technologies and macro-level environmental, social, and economic objectives converge.</p>
    
    <p>Accordingly, this Special Issue seeks contributions that delve into digital sustainability and encompass the development, deployment, and utilization of digital resources and artifacts toward improving the environment, society, and economic welfare.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Design and development considerations</li>
        
        <li>Research that investigates the processes, principles, resources or capabilities required for the design and development of digital sustainability artefacts</li>
        
        <li>Intervention-based research that engages directly in enhancing sustainability practices within organizations or communities through effective leveraging of digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>Studies examining how the different inter- and intra-organizational actors involved in digital sustainability projects engage and interact as they develop, deploy, and govern digital solutions for macro-level sustainability agenda</li>
        
        <li>Explorations of the relationships between digital objects and the physical reality they shape/create in the context of social and environmental sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Use considerations</li>
        
        <li>Research examining how digital technologies support key organizational activities in the management of macro-level sustainability challenges</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical and/or empirical investigations of the interplay between sustainability initiatives and other digital agendas</li>
        
        <li>Studies of ‘computed human experiences’ with respect to sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Research on the challenges and opportunities for reclaiming and rejuvenating Indigenous cultures and knowledge through decolonized digital artefacts</li>
        
        <li>Management and governance considerations</li>
        
        <li>Studies exploring the governance of digital sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Research on the role of different actors in the digital sustainability ecosystem</li>
        
        <li>Studies on the sustainability agenda at the community and societal levels</li>
        
        <li>Policy implications related to digital sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Outcomes and consequences</li>
        
        <li>Studies that incorporate multiple aspects of digital sustainability performance</li>
        
        <li>Case studies of real-world impacts of digital sustainability on vulnerable or marginalized communities</li>
        
        <li>Research investigating alternative ways of measuring progress toward long-term sustainability objectives</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>February 20, 2024: Online information session (we invite potential authors to send us specific questions to address during this session)</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2024: Deadline for paper submission</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2025: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>June 1, 2025: Deadline to submit revised papers</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2025: Second-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2026: Deadline to submit revised papers</li>
        
        <li>June 1, 2026: Provisional/Final decisions</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2026: Deadline to submit final paper (if minor revision is required)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Health Analytics and IS Theorizing]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-health-analytics-and-theorizing</link>
            <guid>jais-health-analytics-and-theorizing</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 12:50:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Aaron Baird</strong>, Georgia State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yusen Xia</strong>, Georgia State University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rajiv Kohli</strong>, William &amp; Mary</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The objective of this special issue is to showcase how health analytics can be used to enhance theorizing in the field of IS. In addition to its contribution to deep analysis, the power of health analytics research lies in theory development that leverages the unique context of health care. Specifically, the special issue aims to foster research that addresses the question: How can the application and design of analytics methods identify insights from health data and extend IS theory?</p>
    
    <p>This special issue places analytics at the forefront of IS research so that health care researchers can make a theoretical contribution to IS research. Through this special issue, we hope to provide an opportunity for emerging and innovative health analytics research to be published that will showcase how new forms and combinations of theoretical reasoning, methods, and data can contribute to theory building. Our hope is that this special issue will contribute to deeper descriptions, explanations, and predictions of emerging health phenomena relevant to IS scholars as well as demonstrate to clinicians and patients opportunities that will enrich health care management and delivery. We welcome research at the intersection of traditional and emerging approaches, exploratory research, phenomenon-based research, novel methods, and data from any relevant source (with IRB approval, as needed). While we are open to discoveries of all kinds, we expect application of rigorous methods, presentation of persuasive reasoning, and inclusion of strong evidence.</p>
    
    <p>Health analytics can be generally described as generating insights from health data through analysis. Significant and impactful work in health analytics is emerging in the IS literature, but there are also significant opportunities to leverage health analytics research to contribute to theorizing in IS. For instance, while interesting findings within IS have been presented in the context of health analytics use in hospitals and clinical diagnostics or care, many health analytics research contexts have yet to be exploited in IS research. The diversity of data and contexts within which to conduct health analytics research is substantial and such diversity is currently underrepresented in IS journals. We propose that health analytics research can advance beyond presentation of context specific models and methods. We see considerable promise in applying such innovative approaches to the enhancement of IS theory, particularly in explaining IS-enabled mechanisms, through research conducted in the health analytics context.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Heterogenous treatment effects in areas such as health care performance, social determinants of health, use of patient generated health data, and offering or pricing of health care, pharmaceutical, medical device, or insurance products.</li>
        
        <li>AI/ML based tools that can reduce information asymmetry, improve decision-making, or optimize information flows.</li>
        
        <li>Unstructured data analysis, such as of digital trace data, images, or user-generated content, that yields insights about topical or trend dynamics.</li>
        
        <li>Impact of, or disparities in, health analytic capabilities or investments by hospitals, clinics, or less frequently considered entities such as laboratories, pharmacies, medical device manufacturers, public health agencies, or charitable organizations.</li>
        
        <li>Integration of personal device data to analyze trends, identify public health issues, and efficacy of treatments.</li>
        
        <li>Any interesting or creative area we have yet to research in-depth in IS, such as topics in genomics, signal processing/telemetry, clinical trials, or epidemiology.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>February 1, 2023: Extended abstract submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2023: Extended abstract decision</li>
        
        <li>August 1, 2023: 1st round full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2023: 1st round full paper decision</li>
        
        <li>January 15, 2024: 2nd round full paper submission deadline</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2024: 2nd round full paper decision</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Corey Angst</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hilal Atasoy</strong>, Rutgers University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sezgin Ayabakan</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ofir Ben Assuli</strong>, Tel Aviv University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sangeeta Shah Bharadwaj</strong>, Management Development Institute</li>
        
        <li><strong>Langtao Chen</strong>, Missouri University of Science and Technology</li>
        
        <li><strong>Yichen Cheng</strong>, Georgia State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Anton Ivanov</strong>, University of Illinois</li>
        
        <li><strong>Juhee Kwon</strong>, City University of Hong Kong</li>
        
        <li><strong>Nakyung Kyung</strong>, National University of Singapore</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Oklahoma</li>
        
        <li><strong>Abhay Mishra</strong>, Iowa State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sunil Mithas</strong>, University of South Florida</li>
        
        <li><strong>Min-Seok Pang</strong>, Temple University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sujeet Sharma</strong>, Indian Institute of Management Tiruchirappalli</li>
        
        <li><strong>Sriram Somanchi</strong>, University of Notre Dame</li>
        
        <li><strong>Junbo Son</strong>, University of Delaware</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ankita Srivastava</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Monica Tremblay</strong>, William &amp; Mary</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hongyi Zhu</strong>, The University of Texas at San Antonio</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Responsibility: Social, Ethical, and Ecological Implications of IS]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-digital-responsibility-social-ethical-and-ecological-implications-of-is</link>
            <guid>jais-digital-responsibility-social-ethical-and-ecological-implications-of-is</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 06:37:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Jan Recker</strong>, Universität Hamburg</p>
        
        <p><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Janina Sundermeier</strong>, Freie Universität Berlin</p>
        
        <p><strong>Monideepa Tarafdar</strong>, University of Massachusetts Amherst</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Pervasive digitalization has influenced practically all aspects of the human experience and our institutions in business, society, and government. Diverse areas such as organizational management and strategy, urban affairs and city planning, healthcare, entertainment, safety, politics, and transportation have all been inexorably shaped by digital technologies. Such technologies have created non-trivial and non-reversible changes to our individual and collective behaviors, our institutions and organizations, as well as to human society and our planet at large. But with great power also comes great responsibility. The transformational changes from digitalization are neither unequivocally positive nor negative; more often than not, they are laden with ethical tensions between the contrasting outcomes they engender. For example, personal data digitalization can help individuals live longer and heal their lives, but it also challenges individual rights, obligations, and our sense of dignity. Social media allows us greater connectivity and access, upholding the democratic principle of collective voice, but also becomes a vehicle for manipulating public opinion and spreading fake news and falsehood. Emerging technologies such as shared electric vehicles are coining a revolution in the mobility and energy sector, but also increase fears of labor substitution. The datafication of everyday behaviors has led to new healthcare opportunities but also increased surveillance. The wide embracement of Artificial Intelligence (AI) propels new opportunities for automation and decision-making, but also raises thorny ethical issues in terms of accountability, privacy, fairness, discrimination, and further biases. These observations surface the fact that digital technologies invoke competing narratives: the transformational and innovative powers of digital technologies often contrast dysfunctional outcomes of digitalization, such as social endangerment or loss of human voice and autonomy. While digital technologies promise an exciting future, we have been cautioned that “the journey to the fully pervasive digitized world is also likely to be perilous” and “as much as the potential benefits of digital technology are real, so too are the risks and complexity that ride with them.” Therefore, the key question that we must ask is: how can we positively leverage the transformational powers of digital technologies without falling prey to their possible dysfunctional outcomes? We believe that the answer to this complex question partly lies in the consideration of an important construct: responsibility. Responsibility allows us to evaluate transformational digital technologies in a balanced manner, by factoring in both harmful and positive outcomes from the engagement with such artifacts. Responsibility has become a salient term in this digital age, inspiring new streams of research such as corporate digital responsibility and responsible innovation. Forcing us to engage in meta-ethical reflection, responsibility is crucial to addressing some of the dysfunctional outcomes associated with the rapid proliferation of digital technologies – thus allowing for normative action consistent with human values and ethical defensibility. As information systems researchers, it must be on us to better understand the concept of responsibility as it pertains to the enablement of positive outcomes of the ongoing digitalization of our everyday lives while safeguarding the human experience against possible negative consequences of the same. We term this concept “digital responsibility”, which we believe can serve as an organizing construct of research that aims to inform the balancing of ethical and humanistic tensions pertaining to the rapid proliferation of digital technologies. Notably, focusing on digital responsibility allows us to challenge the often-embraced utopic narrative of digitalization – thus problematizing our vision for this special issue. Digital responsibility is antithetical to “mindlessness” in designing and implementing digital technologies, which is often associated with the inability “to cope gracefully with changing, complex situations characteristic of high-risk domains.” The lens of digital responsibility necessitates that we embark upon rigorously analyzing, explaining, predicting, as well as influencing, the potential costs, duties, and obligations of decisions that relate to the development, implementation, and use of digital information and communication technologies. Following such observations, unpacking the phenomenon of “digital responsibility” should be of utmost concern to IS researchers – and this is the central theme of this special issue.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Designing and using digital technologies for and with responsibility</li>
        
        <li>Considerations of accountability, liability, fairness, and/or responsibility for digital technology design, implementation, and use</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical perspectives and/or empirical insights on the (un)intended social, ethical, and ecological consequences of digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical underpinnings of the concept of digital responsibility, such as from an ethical theory perspective</li>
        
        <li>Design of digital technology to address social, ethical, and/or ecological challenges</li>
        
        <li>Individual, organizational, institutional, or societal strategies for leveraging IS for social, ethical, and/or ecological challenges and innovations</li>
        
        <li>The role of digital technology in promoting social, ethical, and ecological advancements</li>
        
        <li>Applications of emerging digital technologies (e.g., AI) to social, ethical, and/or ecological realms</li>
        
        <li>Societal, ethical, and ecological consequences of emerging digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>(Un-)ethical issues of IS and the data they generate</li>
        
        <li>Dignity, respect, and moral behavior in a digital world</li>
        
        <li>Social support and inclusion enabled by or embodied in digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>The balance of contradicting implications of IS (e.g., IS as a means for social change vs. IS for manipulating public opinion)</li>
        
        <li>The affordances of existing and emerging digital technologies for enacting digital responsibility</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 3, 2023: Deadline for paper submissions</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2024: First-round review decisions</li>
        
        <li>May 1, 2024: Hybrid Paper development workshop</li>
        
        <li>July 11, 2024: Deadline for submission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2024: Second-round review decisions</li>
        
        <li>December 8, 2024: Deadline for submission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2025: Provisional decision and final round of comments</li>
        
        <li>February 27, 2025: Deadline for submission of revised papers</li>
        
        <li>March 1, 2025: Notification of final decisions</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Jose Benitez</strong>, EDHEC Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Alexander Benlian</strong>, TU Darmstadt</li>
        
        <li><strong>Roberta Bernardi</strong>, University of Bristol</li>
        
        <li><strong>Michelle Carter</strong>, Washington State University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Dubravka Cecez-Kecmanovic</strong>, University of New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>John D&#39;Arcy</strong>, University of Delaware</li>
        
        <li><strong>James Gaskin</strong>, Brigham Young University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</li>
        
        <li><strong>Oliver Laasch</strong>, ESCP Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shan Pan</strong>, University of New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>Hannes Rothe</strong>, University of Duisburg-Essen</li>
        
        <li><strong>Saonee Sarker</strong>, Lund University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Olgerta Tona</strong>, University of Gothenburg</li>
        
        <li><strong>John Tripp</strong>, Clemson University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Tuure Tuunanen</strong>, University Jyväskylä</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>