<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: paper development</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/paper-development</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers tagged with 'paper development'.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 03:05:28 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: paper development</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/paper-development</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Paper Development Workshop]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isj-isj-paper-development-workshop</link>
            <guid>isj-isj-paper-development-workshop</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2025 03:07:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Sutirtha Chatterjee</strong>, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</p>
        
        <p><strong>Ravi Patnayakuni</strong>, University of Alabama in Huntsville</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yingqin Zheng</strong>, University of Essex</p>
        
        <p><strong>Zhongyun (Phil) Zhou</strong>, Tongji University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Information Systems Journal, as part of its outreach efforts, will be holding a Paper Development Workshop along with the 2025 Pacific-Asia Conference on Information Systems in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. The half-day workshop will be held on Sunday, July 6, 2025, from 8:30 am to 12:30 pm as an in-person pre-conference workshop. ISJ welcomes research that spans across the diverse and interdisciplinary IS field.</p>
    
    <p>The paper development workshop aims to nurture scholarship across the broad spectrum of information systems researchers. We welcome work that examines both established and emerging areas within IS. The workshop aims to provide a supportive environment for researchers to develop their ideas and receive constructive feedback on their work from the journal’s editorial board members. We especially encourage submissions from author(s) planning to submit their work to ISJ’s forthcoming special issue on &#39;Theorising the Impacts of Generative Artificial Intelligence&#39;, which has a submission deadline of December 31, 2025, and any other special issues announced before the workshop deadline.</p>
    
    <p>The workshop welcomes papers at various stages of development, from early conceptual work to papers nearing completion. We encourage submissions that show potential for theoretical or practical contribution to the IS field, regardless of their current stage. The workshop particularly aims to support researchers who would benefit from early guidance and feedback on their work.</p>
    
    <p>Interested authors are invited to submit papers for possible inclusion in the workshop. Papers that have been accepted, under review, or under revision at other journals, workshops, or conferences should not be submitted. Please note that not all submissions received may be accepted. Papers that are not accepted will not receive feedback. The selected papers will be mentored by at least two members of the ISJ Editorial Board. Additionally, attending author(s) of accepted papers may be assigned manuscripts as discussants.</p>
    
    <p>Please note that the workshop is not associated with any publication. The goal is to offer feedback to the authors that can help enhance the quality of the paper as it is prepared for submission to a suitable journal. Authors do not have an obligation to submit the paper to ISJ but are encouraged to submit their completed papers for publication consideration to the journal in the future. Also, please note that participation in the workshop does not imply favorable consideration or outcome at ISJ.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Submissions from PACIS community</li>
        
        <li>Relationship between technology, business, economy, and society</li>
        
        <li>Examining established and emerging areas within Information Systems</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical or practical contribution to the IS field</li>
        
        <li>Support for early-stage researchers</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>May 12, 2025: Submission Begin</li>
        
        <li>May 19, 2025: Submission Deadline</li>
        
        <li>June 6, 2025: Decisions</li>
        
        <li>July 6, 2025: ISJ Trending Topics Workshop</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Journal (ISJ)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>