<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: review articles</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/review-articles</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers tagged with 'review articles'.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 03:03:57 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: review articles</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/review-articles</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Review Articles in the Realm of Strategic Information Systems]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jsis-call-for-special-issue-review-articles</link>
            <guid>jsis-call-for-special-issue-review-articles</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 10:47:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Rohit Nishant</strong>, Queen&#39;s Business School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Tuure Tuunanen</strong>, University of Jyväskylä</p>
        
        <p><strong>Wenyu (Derek) Du</strong>, Beihang University</p>
        
    
    
    <p>The Journal of Strategic Information Systems dedicates an issue of JSIS each year to review articles in the realm of strategic information systems, broadly defined.</p>
    
    <p>We are now inviting authors to submit review articles for the 2027 Review Issue. Papers should be submitted before 1 September 2025 via JSIS’s online submission portal. Submissions will be evaluated concerning the following criteria: relevance, scope of interest, organization and coherence, insight for future work, timeliness/contribution.</p>
    
    <p>The review article should follow a logical structure, read clearly, and represent extant research in the topic area concerned. It should convey important implications for future research in strategic information systems.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>High-impact scholarly surveys of important research literatures in the strategic information systems domain</li>
        
        <li>Synthesis of recent research and future inquiries</li>
        
        <li>Established and emerging topics in strategic information systems</li>
        
        <li>Research methods relevant to the context of strategic information systems</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>September 1, 2025: Full draft of paper due</li>
        
        <li>September 1, 2027: Special issue published</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>The Journal of Strategic Information Systems (JSIS)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>