<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: social inclusion</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/social-inclusion</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers tagged with 'social inclusion'.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 06:01:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: social inclusion</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/social-inclusion</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Addressing Refugees and Migration Issues through Critical Information Systems Research]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/isj-addressing-refugees-and-migration-issues-through-critical-information-systems</link>
            <guid>isj-addressing-refugees-and-migration-issues-through-critical-information-systems</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 10:34:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Safa’a AbuJarour</strong>, An-Najah National University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Hameed Chughtai</strong>, Lancaster University Management School</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yingqin Zheng</strong>, University of Essex</p>
        
    
    
    <p>United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) reports that there are approximately 110 million forcibly displaced people worldwide, as of mid-2023, because of persecution, conflict, war, violence, human rights violations, or events seriously disturbing public order. These include 36.4 million refugees and 62.5 million internally displaced people (IDP), asylum seekers, and several other people in need of international protection. There is a strong history of research highlighting the issues faced by refugees, ranging from accounts of violence in the developing world, exploring the gendered experience of refugees, questioning racist thinking about immigration, case studies of asylum seekers, and philosophical inquiry into the fair treatment of refugees. The global refugee and forced migration crisis and the persistent challenges faced by these vulnerable communities call for an urgent need for innovative solutions that foster social inclusion and empower these populations.</p>
    
    <p>In our field, information systems (IS) researchers have been acutely aware of the refugee and migrant crises. Researchers have examined the critical issues related to social inclusion of refugees, social inclusion and activation of refugee agency, information and communication technology (ICT) enabled refugee integration, refugees and pedagogy, digitization and refugee settlement, refugee women and information-precarity, and migrant identity. Nonetheless, recent research in refugee studies has shown that critical areas at the intersection of technology, refugees, and broader migration crises have remained underexamined, for example, social media and device vetting, digitally mediated lived experiences of minority refugees, refugees and a sense of uncertainty in the digital age, refugee aid and digital capitalism, and networked refugees.</p>
    
    <p>We observe that despite some progress in our field, much remains underexplored in addressing these pressing issues, underscoring the need for rigorous research. This special issue aims to explore how IS research could contribute to illuminating the refugee crises and alleviating the deterioration of refugee and migrant social circumstances. These sensitive topics are situated within the broader debate on digital inclusion and empowerment and the discussions related to inequality and demarginalization and decolonization in our field.</p>
    
    <p>Exploring the critical research questions surrounding IS and migrant/refugee populations is essential for developing comprehensive and ‘good’ IS solutions and making the world a better place for all of us. We encourage submissions from diverse researchers with multidisciplinary perspectives, including experts in IS, social sciences, public policy, humanitarian studies, and other relevant fields. Such interdisciplinary collaborations will contribute to a holistic understanding of the problems and foster innovative solutions. We seek submissions that focus on real-world issues at the intersection of refugees and migrant crises and technology.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Critical analyses of the interrelated themes of identity, refugeeness, and belonging.</li>
        
        <li>Exploring the ethics of (forced) migration.</li>
        
        <li>Analysing the politics of responsibility and the integration of refugees and migrants in digital contexts.</li>
        
        <li>Technology, racial marginalization and refugees experience.</li>
        
        <li>Digital biopolitics, identities, and datafication of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Online activism and digital social movements in the context of refugees or migrants.</li>
        
        <li>Agency, resistance and coping mechanisms of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Examining the issues at the intersections of gender, technology, and migrants/refugees (including queering migration and issues of gender-based violence).</li>
        
        <li>Digitally-entangled lived experiences of minorities among refugee populations.</li>
        
        <li>Datafication of borders and algorithmic management of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Decolonial justice and /for migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Digital justice and human rights issues affecting migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Digital and data surveillance and control on migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Issues related to power and exploitation of migrants and refugees.</li>
        
        <li>Critical narratives of displacement.</li>
        
        <li>Digital accounts and narratives of refugee experience.</li>
        
        <li>Technology and the political philosophy of migration and refuge.</li>
        
        <li>Novel theoretical lenses to study migration and refugee issues such as decolonial theory, spatial and temporal perspectives, Indigenous viewpoints, critical race theory, and feminist approaches.</li>
        
        <li>Novel methodological approaches to examine refugee issues such as visual ethnography, visual research, and digitally mediated bodily experiences.</li>
        
        <li>Application of novel technologies such as Blockchain and AI.</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>November 30, 2024: Submission of extended abstract (optional)</li>
        
        <li>March 30, 2025: Submission of manuscript</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Associate editors</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li><strong>Petros Chamakiotis</strong>, ESCP Business School</li>
        
        <li><strong>Andrea Jimenez</strong>, University of Sheffield</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shirin Madon</strong>, London School of Economics</li>
        
        <li><strong>Marco Marabelli</strong>, Bentley University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Carmen Leong</strong>, University of New South Wales</li>
        
        <li><strong>Shaila Miranda</strong>, University of Arkansas</li>
        
        <li><strong>Priyanka Panday</strong>, Kings College London</li>
        
        <li><strong>Israr Qureshi</strong>, Australian National University</li>
        
        <li><strong>Maximilian Schreieck</strong>, University of Innsbruck</li>
        
        <li><strong>Devinder Thapa</strong>, University of Agder</li>
        
        <li><strong>Ranjan Vaidya</strong>, Auckland University of Technology</li>
        
    </ul>
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Information Systems Journal (ISJ)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>