<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: sustainability challenges</title>
        <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/sustainability-challenges</link>
        <description>Latest calls for papers tagged with 'sustainability challenges'.</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 03:03:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <image>
            <title>Calls for Papers | Tag: sustainability challenges</title>
            <url>https://callsforpapers.org/public/favicon/android-chrome-96x96.png</url>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/tag/sustainability-challenges</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>Calls for Papers © 2025</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Sustainability and Information Systems Research: New challenges and theoretical perspectives]]></title>
            <link>https://callsforpapers.org/call/jais-digital-sustainability-and-information-systems-research</link>
            <guid>jais-digital-sustainability-and-information-systems-research</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2023 12:54:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
    
        
        <p><strong>Julia Kotlarsky</strong>, University of Auckland</p>
        
        <p><strong>Jacqueline Corbett</strong>, Université Laval</p>
        
        <p><strong>Juliana Sutanto</strong>, Monash University</p>
        
        <p><strong>Thomas Kude</strong>, University of Bamberg</p>
        
        <p><strong>Yenni Tim</strong>, University of New South Wales</p>
        
    
    
    <p>Sustainability is a moral and existential imperative of our time. As Information Systems (IS) scholars, we are aware of the immense impact of digital technologies on efforts and initiatives towards sustainable practice happening locally and globally. Furthermore, because digital phenomena lie at the heart of our discipline, IS researchers are well positioned to join these efforts. This Special Issue aims to champion new digital sustainability research programs targeting the planet’s most pressing sustainability challenges from the past decade. We hope it will contribute towards building novel collective knowledge and help shape digital sustainability research in IS.</p>
    
    <p>Human society is approaching the edge of a dangerous precipice. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change’s (IPCC) Sixth Assessment Report unequivocally confirms that human activities have caused global warming, predicting that even with current commitments and mitigation efforts, it will be difficult to limit warming below the critical threshold of 2 o C. The planet’s air, land, and water continue to be threatened on several fronts, with research suggesting that the safe operating zone for six of the nine planetary boundaries has already been breached. Over the past decade, extreme weather events such as droughts, floods, fires and heatwaves have not only increased in frequency but also in magnitude. In addition to causing environmental impacts, these events have a significant impact on society, further complicating the pursuit of social and economic sustainability.</p>
    
    <p>In 2020, about 724 million people were living in conditions of extreme poverty, with almost 30% of the world’s population suffering from some level of food insecurity. Equality for women and other marginalized groups continues to lag. The World Bank reports that 2.4 billion women globally do not have the same economic rights as men, and despite the adoption of the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples in 2007, Indigenous Peoples around the world continue to suffer the intergenerational trauma of colonization. The trend towards urbanization endures, with cities struggling to ensure inclusive, resilient, and sustainable living environments for all residents. On top of all these challenges, violent conflicts have led to the forced migration of millions of people and the deaths of thousands of civilians. These alarming circumstances highlight the lack of progress towards the United Nation’s Sustainable Development Goals.</p>
    
    <p>As argued in a recent JAIS editorial on digital sustainability, the IS research community has a strong foundation to draw upon, ranging from research into Green IS to studies addressing significant societal challenges. The poor cannot eat technology, but the mindful design and use of technology can contribute to innovative solutions and positive impacts. In particular, we consider that the recent shift in the way IS research approaches digital phenomena offers new perspectives on the relationship between digital technologies and sustainability. Building on a contention that the classical view of an information system as representing and reflecting physical reality has become obsolete, there exists an opportunity for the IS community to drive a more inclusive agenda on digital sustainability, one that encompasses phenomena in which the impact of digital technologies and macro-level environmental, social, and economic objectives converge.</p>
    
    <p>Accordingly, this Special Issue seeks contributions that delve into digital sustainability and encompass the development, deployment, and utilization of digital resources and artifacts toward improving the environment, society, and economic welfare.</p>
    
    
    <h2>Potential topics</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>Design and development considerations</li>
        
        <li>Research that investigates the processes, principles, resources or capabilities required for the design and development of digital sustainability artefacts</li>
        
        <li>Intervention-based research that engages directly in enhancing sustainability practices within organizations or communities through effective leveraging of digital technologies</li>
        
        <li>Studies examining how the different inter- and intra-organizational actors involved in digital sustainability projects engage and interact as they develop, deploy, and govern digital solutions for macro-level sustainability agenda</li>
        
        <li>Explorations of the relationships between digital objects and the physical reality they shape/create in the context of social and environmental sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Use considerations</li>
        
        <li>Research examining how digital technologies support key organizational activities in the management of macro-level sustainability challenges</li>
        
        <li>Theoretical and/or empirical investigations of the interplay between sustainability initiatives and other digital agendas</li>
        
        <li>Studies of ‘computed human experiences’ with respect to sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Research on the challenges and opportunities for reclaiming and rejuvenating Indigenous cultures and knowledge through decolonized digital artefacts</li>
        
        <li>Management and governance considerations</li>
        
        <li>Studies exploring the governance of digital sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Research on the role of different actors in the digital sustainability ecosystem</li>
        
        <li>Studies on the sustainability agenda at the community and societal levels</li>
        
        <li>Policy implications related to digital sustainability</li>
        
        <li>Outcomes and consequences</li>
        
        <li>Studies that incorporate multiple aspects of digital sustainability performance</li>
        
        <li>Case studies of real-world impacts of digital sustainability on vulnerable or marginalized communities</li>
        
        <li>Research investigating alternative ways of measuring progress toward long-term sustainability objectives</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
    <h2>Timeline</h2>
    <ul>
        
        <li>February 20, 2024: Online information session (we invite potential authors to send us specific questions to address during this session)</li>
        
        <li>October 1, 2024: Deadline for paper submission</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2025: First-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>June 1, 2025: Deadline to submit revised papers</li>
        
        <li>September 15, 2025: Second-round decisions</li>
        
        <li>February 1, 2026: Deadline to submit revised papers</li>
        
        <li>June 1, 2026: Provisional/Final decisions</li>
        
        <li>July 1, 2026: Deadline to submit final paper (if minor revision is required)</li>
        
    </ul>
    
    
</div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>Journal of the Association for Information Systems (JAIS)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>